<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">Arms, and the man I sing, who, forc'd by fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And haughty Juno's unrelenting hate,</l>
<l n="tr">Expell'd and exil'd, left the Trojan shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Long labors, both by sea and land, he bore,</l>
<l n="tr">And in the doubtful war, before he won</l>
<l n="tr">The Latian realm, and built the destin'd town;</l>
<l n="tr">His banish'd gods restor'd to rites divine,</l>
<l n="tr">And settled sure succession in his line,</l>
<l n="tr">From whence the race of Alban fathers come,</l>
<l n="tr">And the long glories of majestic <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="8" unit="card"/>O Muse! the causes and the crimes relate;</l>
<l n="tr">What goddess was provok'd, and whence her hate;</l>
<l n="tr">For what offense the Queen of Heav'n began</l>
<l n="tr">To persecute so brave, so just a man;</l>
<l n="tr">Involv'd his anxious life in endless cares,</l>
<l n="tr">Expos'd to wants, and hurried into wars!</l>
<l n="tr">Can heav'nly minds such high resentment show,</l>
<l n="tr">Or exercise their spite in human woe?</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="12" unit="card"/>Against the <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s mouth, but far away,</l>
<l n="tr">An ancient town was seated on the sea;</l>
<l n="tr">A Tyrian colony; the people made</l>
<l n="tr">Stout for the war, and studious of their trade:</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> the name; belov'd by Juno more</l>
<l n="tr">Than her own <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, or the Samian shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Here stood her chariot; here, if Heav'n were kind,</l>
<l n="tr">The seat of awful empire she design'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet she had heard an ancient rumor fly,</l>
<l n="tr">(Long cited by the people of the sky,)</l>
<l n="tr">That times to come should see the Trojan race</l>
<l n="tr">Her <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> ruin, and her tow'rs deface;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thus confin'd, the yoke of sov'reign sway</l>
<l n="tr">Should on the necks of all the nations lay.</l>
<l n="tr">She ponder'd this, and fear'd it was in fate;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor could forget the war she wag'd of late</l>
<l n="tr">For conqu'ring <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> against the Trojan state.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, long causes working in her mind,</l>
<l n="tr">And secret seeds of envy, lay behind;</l>
<l n="tr">Deep graven in her heart the doom remain'd</l>
<l n="tr">Of partial <persName>Paris</persName>, and her form disdain'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The grace bestow'd on ravish'd Ganymed,</l>
<l n="tr">Electra's glories, and her injur'd bed.</l>
<l n="tr">Each was a cause alone; and all combin'd</l>
<l n="tr">To kindle vengeance in her haughty mind.</l>
<l n="tr">For this, far distant from the Latian coast</l>
<l n="tr">She drove the remnants of the Trojan host;</l>
<l n="tr">And sev'n long years  th'  unhappy wand'ring train</l>
<l n="tr">Were toss'd by storms, and scatter'd thro' the main.</l>
<l n="tr">Such time, such toil, requir'd the Roman name,</l>
<l n="tr">Such length of labor for so vast a frame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="34" unit="card"/>Now scarce the Trojan fleet, with sails and oars,</l>
<l n="tr">Had left behind the fair Sicilian shores,</l>
<l n="tr">Ent'ring with cheerful shouts the wat'ry reign,</l>
<l n="tr">And plowing frothy furrows in the main;</l>
<l n="tr">When, lab'ring still with endless discontent,</l>
<l n="tr">The Queen of Heav'n did thus her fury vent:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Then am I vanquish'd? must I yield?” said she,</l>
<l n="tr">“And must the Trojans reign in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>?</l>
<l n="tr">So Fate will have it, and Jove adds his force;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor can my pow'r divert their happy course.</l>
<l n="tr">Could angry Pallas, with revengeful spleen,</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian navy burn, and drown the men?</l>
<l n="tr">She, for the fault of one offending foe,</l>
<l n="tr">The bolts of Jove himself presum'd to throw:</l>
<l n="tr">With whirlwinds from beneath she toss'd the ship,</l>
<l n="tr">And bare expos'd the bosom of the deep;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, as an eagle gripes the trembling game,</l>
<l n="tr">The wretch, yet hissing with her father's flame,</l>
<l n="tr">She strongly seiz'd, and with a burning wound</l>
<l n="tr">Transfix'd, and naked, on a rock she bound.</l>
<l n="tr">But I, who walk in awful state above,</l>
<l n="tr">The majesty of heav'n, the sister wife of Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">For length of years my fruitless force employ</l>
<l n="tr">Against the thin remains of ruin'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>!</l>
<l n="tr">What nations now to Juno's pow'r will pray,</l>
<l n="tr">Or off'rings on my slighted altars lay?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="50" unit="card"/>Thus rag'd the goddess; and, with fury fraught.</l>
<l n="tr">The restless regions of the storms she sought,</l>
<l n="tr">Where, in a spacious cave of living stone,</l>
<l n="tr">The tyrant Aeolus, from his airy throne,</l>
<l n="tr">With pow'r imperial curbs the struggling winds,</l>
<l n="tr">And sounding tempests in dark prisons binds.</l>
<l n="tr">This way and that  th'  impatient captives tend,</l>
<l n="tr">And, pressing for release, the mountains rend.</l>
<l n="tr">High in his hall  th'  undaunted monarch stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And shakes his scepter, and their rage commands;</l>
<l n="tr">Which did he not, their unresisted sway</l>
<l n="tr">Would sweep the world before them in their way;</l>
<l n="tr">Earth, air, and seas thro' empty space would roll,</l>
<l n="tr">And heav'n would fly before the driving soul.</l>
<l n="tr">In fear of this, the Father of the Gods</l>
<l n="tr">Confin'd their fury to those dark abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">And lock'd 'em safe within, oppress'd with mountain loads;</l>
<l n="tr">Impos'd a king, with arbitrary sway,</l>
<l n="tr">To loose their fetters, or their force allay.</l>
<l n="tr">To whom the suppliant queen her pray'rs address'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus the tenor of her suit express'd:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="65" unit="card"/>“O Aeolus! for to thee the King of Heav'n</l>
<l n="tr">The pow'r of tempests and of winds has giv'n;</l>
<l n="tr">Thy force alone their fury can restrain,</l>
<l n="tr">And smooth the waves, or swell the troubled main—</l>
<l n="tr">A race of wand'ring slaves, abhorr'd by me,</l>
<l n="tr">With prosp'rous passage cut the Tuscan sea;</l>
<l n="tr">To fruitful <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> their course they steer,</l>
<l n="tr">And for their vanquish'd gods design new temples there.</l>
<l n="tr">Raise all thy winds; with night involve the skies;</l>
<l n="tr">Sink or disperse my fatal enemies.</l>
<l n="tr">Twice sev'n, the charming daughters of the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Around my person wait, and bear my train:</l>
<l n="tr">Succeed my wish, and second my design;</l>
<l n="tr">The fairest, Deiopeia, shall be thine,</l>
<l n="tr">And make thee father of a happy line.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="76" unit="card"/>To this the god: “'T is yours, O queen, to will</l>
<l n="tr">The work which duty binds me to fulfil.</l>
<l n="tr">These airy kingdoms, and this wide command,</l>
<l n="tr">Are all the presents of your bounteous hand:</l>
<l n="tr">Yours is my sov'reign's grace; and, as your guest,</l>
<l n="tr">I sit with gods at their celestial feast;</l>
<l n="tr">Raise tempests at your pleasure, or subdue;</l>
<l n="tr">Dispose of empire, which I hold from you.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="81" unit="card"/>He said, and hurl'd against the mountain side</l>
<l n="tr">His quiv'ring spear, and all the god applied.</l>
<l n="tr">The raging winds rush thro' the hollow wound,</l>
<l n="tr">And dance aloft in air, and skim along the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, settling on the sea, the surges sweep,</l>
<l n="tr">Raise liquid mountains, and disclose the deep.</l>
<l n="tr">South, East, and West with mix'd confusion roar,</l>
<l n="tr">And roll the foaming billows to the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">The cables crack; the sailors' fearful cries</l>
<l n="tr">Ascend; and sable night involves the skies;</l>
<l n="tr">And heav'n itself is ravish'd from their eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">Loud peals of thunder from the poles ensue;</l>
<l n="tr">Then flashing fires the transient light renew;</l>
<l n="tr">The face of things a frightful image bears,</l>
<l n="tr">And present death in various forms appears.</l>
<l n="tr">Struck with unusual fright, the Trojan chief,</l>
<l n="tr">With lifted hands and eyes, invokes relief;</l>
<l n="tr">And, “Thrice and four times happy those,” he cried,</l>
<l n="tr">“That under Ilian walls before their parents died!</l>
<l n="tr">Tydides, bravest of the Grecian train!</l>
<l n="tr">Why could not I by that strong arm be slain,</l>
<l n="tr">And lie by noble Hector on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Or great Sarpedon, in those bloody fields</l>
<l n="tr">Where Simois rolls the bodies and the shields</l>
<l n="tr">Of heroes, whose dismember'd hands yet bear</l>
<l n="tr">The dart aloft, and clench the pointed spear!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="102" unit="card"/>Thus while the pious prince his fate bewails,</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Boreas drove against his flying sails,</l>
<l n="tr">And rent the sheets; the raging billows rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And mount the tossing vessels to the skies:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor can the shiv'ring oars sustain the blow;</l>
<l n="tr">The galley gives her side, and turns her prow;</l>
<l n="tr">While those astern, descending down the steep,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' gaping waves behold the boiling deep.</l>
<l n="tr">Three ships were hurried by the southern blast,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the secret shelves with fury cast.</l>
<l n="tr">Those hidden rocks  th'  Ausonian sailors knew:</l>
<l n="tr">They call'd them Altars, when they rose in view,</l>
<l n="tr">And show'd their spacious backs above the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">Three more fierce Eurus, in his angry mood,</l>
<l n="tr">Dash'd on the shallows of the moving sand,</l>
<l n="tr">And in mid ocean left them moor'd aland.</l>
<l n="tr">Orontes' bark, that bore the Lycian crew,</l>
<l n="tr">(A horrid sight!) ev'n in the hero's view,</l>
<l n="tr">From stem to stern by waves was overborne:</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling pilot, from his rudder torn,</l>
<l n="tr">Was headlong hurl'd; thrice round the ship was toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Then bulg'd at once, and in the deep was lost;</l>
<l n="tr">And here and there above the waves were seen</l>
<l n="tr">Arms, pictures, precious goods, and floating men.</l>
<l n="tr">The stoutest vessel to the storm gave way,</l>
<l n="tr">And suck'd thro' loosen'd planks the rushing sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Ilioneus was her chief: Aletes old,</l>
<l n="tr">Achates faithful, Abas young and bold,</l>
<l n="tr">Endur'd not less; their ships, with gaping seams,</l>
<l n="tr">Admit the deluge of the briny streams.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="124" unit="card"/>Meantime imperial Neptune heard the sound</l>
<l n="tr">Of raging billows breaking on the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Displeas'd, and fearing for his wat'ry reign,</l>
<l n="tr">He rear'd his awful head above the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Serene in majesty; then roll'd his eyes</l>
<l n="tr">Around the space of earth, and seas, and skies.</l>
<l n="tr">He saw the Trojan fleet dispers'd, distress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">By stormy winds and wintry heav'n oppress'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Full well the god his sister's envy knew,</l>
<l n="tr">And what her aims and what her arts pursue.</l>
<l n="tr">He summon'd Eurus and the western blast,</l>
<l n="tr">And first an angry glance on both he cast;</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus rebuk'd:<milestone ed="p" n="132" unit="card"/>“Audacious winds! from whence</l>
<l n="tr">This bold attempt, this rebel insolence?</l>
<l n="tr">Is it for you to ravage seas and land,</l>
<l n="tr">Unauthoriz'd by my supreme command?</l>
<l n="tr">To raise such mountains on the troubled main?</l>
<l n="tr">Whom I—but first 't is fit the billows to restrain;</l>
<l n="tr">And then you shall be taught obedience to my reign.</l>
<l n="tr">Hence! to your lord my royal mandate bear—</l>
<l n="tr">The realms of ocean and the fields of air</l>
<l n="tr">Are mine, not his. By fatal lot to me</l>
<l n="tr">The liquid empire fell, and trident of the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">His pow'r to hollow caverns is confin'd:</l>
<l n="tr">There let him reign, the jailer of the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">With hoarse commands his breathing subjects call,</l>
<l n="tr">And boast and bluster in his empty hall.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="142" unit="card"/>He spoke; and, while he spoke, he smooth'd the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">Dispell'd the darkness, and restor'd the day.</l>
<l n="tr">Cymothoe, Triton, and the sea-green train</l>
<l n="tr">Of beauteous nymphs, the daughters of the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Clear from the rocks the vessels with their hands:</l>
<l n="tr">The god himself with ready trident stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And opes the deep, and spreads the moving sands;</l>
<l n="tr">Then heaves them off the shoals. Where'er he guides</l>
<l n="tr">His finny coursers and in triumph rides,</l>
<l n="tr">The waves unruffle and the sea subsides.</l>
<l n="tr">As, when in tumults rise  th'  ignoble crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">Mad are their motions, and their tongues are loud;</l>
<l n="tr">And stones and brands in rattling volleys fly,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the rustic arms that fury can supply:</l>
<l n="tr">If then some grave and pious man appear,</l>
<l n="tr">They hush their noise, and lend a list'ning ear;</l>
<l n="tr">He soothes with sober words their angry mood,</l>
<l n="tr">And quenches their innate desire of blood:</l>
<l n="tr">So, when the Father of the Flood appears,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er the seas his sov'reign trident rears,</l>
<l n="tr">Their fury falls: he skims the liquid plains,</l>
<l n="tr">High on his chariot, and, with loosen'd reins,</l>
<l n="tr">Majestic moves along, and awful peace maintains.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="157" unit="card"/>The weary Trojans ply their shatter'd oars</l>
<l n="tr">To nearest land, and make the Libyan shores.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Within a long recess there lies a bay:</l>
<l n="tr">An island shades it from the rolling sea,</l>
<l n="tr">And forms a port secure for ships to ride;</l>
<l n="tr">Broke by the jutting land, on either side,</l>
<l n="tr">In double streams the briny waters glide.</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt two rows of rocks a sylvan scene</l>
<l n="tr">Appears above, and groves for ever green:</l>
<l n="tr">A grot is form'd beneath, with mossy seats,</l>
<l n="tr">To rest the Nereids, and exclude the heats.</l>
<l n="tr">Down thro' the crannies of the living walls</l>
<l n="tr">The crystal streams descend in murm'ring falls:</l>
<l n="tr">No haulsers need to bind the vessels here,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor bearded anchors; for no storms they fear.</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n ships within this happy harbor meet,</l>
<l n="tr">The thin remainders of the scatter'd fleet.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans, worn with toils, and spent with woes,</l>
<l n="tr">Leap on the welcome land, and seek their wish'd repose.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>First, good Achates, with repeated strokes</l>
<l n="tr">Of clashing flints, their hidden fire provokes:</l>
<l n="tr">Short flame succeeds; a bed of wither'd leaves</l>
<l n="tr">The dying sparkles in their fall receives:</l>
<l n="tr">Caught into life, in fiery fumes they rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And, fed with stronger food, invade the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans, dropping wet, or stand around</l>
<l n="tr">The cheerful blaze, or lie along the ground:</l>
<l n="tr">Some dry their corn, infected with the brine,</l>
<l n="tr">Then grind with marbles, and prepare to dine.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="180" unit="card"/>Aeneas climbs the mountain's airy brow,</l>
<l n="tr">And takes a prospect of the seas below,</l>
<l n="tr">If Capys thence, or Antheus he could spy,</l>
<l n="tr">Or see the streamers of Caicus fly.</l>
<l n="tr">No vessels were in view; but, on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Three beamy stags command a lordly train</l>
<l n="tr">Of branching heads: the more ignoble throng</l>
<l n="tr">Attend their stately steps, and slowly graze along.</l>
<l n="tr">He stood; and, while secure they fed below,</l>
<l n="tr">He took the quiver and the trusty bow</l>
<l n="tr">Achates us'd to bear: the leaders first</l>
<l n="tr">He laid along, and then the vulgar pierc'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor ceas'd his arrows, till the shady plain</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n mighty bodies with their blood distain.</l>
<l n="tr">For the sev'n ships he made an equal share,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the port return'd, triumphant from the war.</l>
<l n="tr">The jars of gen'rous wine (Acestes' gift,</l>
<l n="tr">When his Trinacrian shores the navy left)</l>
<l n="tr">He set abroach, and for the feast prepar'd,</l>
<l n="tr">In equal portions with the ven'son shar'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while he dealt it round, the pious chief</l>
<l n="tr">With cheerful words allay'd the common grief:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="198" unit="card"/>“Endure, and conquer! Jove will soon dispose</l>
<l n="tr">To future good our past and present woes.</l>
<l n="tr">With me, the rocks of Scylla you have tried;</l>
<l n="tr"> th'  inhuman Cyclops and his den defied.</l>
<l n="tr">What greater ills hereafter can you bear?</l>
<l n="tr">Resume your courage and dismiss your care,</l>
<l n="tr">An hour will come, with pleasure to relate</l>
<l n="tr">Your sorrows past, as benefits of Fate.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' various hazards and events, we move</l>
<l n="tr">To <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> and the realms foredoom'd by Jove.</l>
<l n="tr">Call'd to the seat (the promise of the skies)</l>
<l n="tr">Where Trojan kingdoms once again may rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Endure the hardships of your present state;</l>
<l n="tr">Live, and reserve yourselves for better fate.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="208" unit="card"/>These words he spoke, but spoke not from his heart;</l>
<l n="tr">His outward smiles conceal'd his inward smart.</l>
<l n="tr">The jolly crew, unmindful of the past,</l>
<l n="tr">The quarry share, their plenteous dinner haste.</l>
<l n="tr">Some strip the skin; some portion out the spoil;</l>
<l n="tr">The limbs, yet trembling, in the caldrons boil;</l>
<l n="tr">Some on the fire the reeking entrails broil.</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch'd on the grassy turf, at ease they dine,</l>
<l n="tr">Restore their strength with meat, and cheer their souls with wine.</l>
<l n="tr">Their hunger thus appeas'd, their care attends</l>
<l n="tr">The doubtful fortune of their absent friends:</l>
<l n="tr">Alternate hopes and fears their minds possess,</l>
<l n="tr">Whether to deem 'em dead, or in distress.</l>
<l n="tr">Above the rest, Aeneas mourns the fate</l>
<l n="tr">Of brave Orontes, and  th'  uncertain state</l>
<l n="tr">Of Gyas, Lycus, and of Amycus.</l>
<l n="tr">The day, but not their sorrows, ended thus.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="223" unit="card"/>When, from aloft, almighty Jove surveys</l>
<l n="tr">Earth, air, and shores, and navigable seas,</l>
<l n="tr">At length on Libyan realms he fix'd his eyes—</l>
<l n="tr">Whom, pond'ring thus on human miseries,</l>
<l n="tr">When Venus saw, she with a lowly look,</l>
<l n="tr">Not free from tears, her heav'nly sire bespoke:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“O King of Gods and Men! whose awful hand</l>
<l n="tr">Disperses thunder on the seas and land,</l>
<l n="tr">Disposing all with absolute command;</l>
<l n="tr">How could my pious son thy pow'r incense?</l>
<l n="tr">Or what, alas! is vanish'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s offense?</l>
<l n="tr">Our hope of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> not only lost,</l>
<l n="tr">On various seas by various tempests toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">But shut from ev'ry shore, and barr'd from ev'ry coast.</l>
<l n="tr">You promis'd once, a progeny divine</l>
<l n="tr">Of Romans, rising from the Trojan line,</l>
<l n="tr">In after times should hold the world in awe,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the land and ocean give the law.</l>
<l n="tr">How is your doom revers'd, which eas'd my care</l>
<l n="tr">When <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> was ruin'd in that cruel war?</l>
<l n="tr">Then fates to fates I could oppose; but now,</l>
<l n="tr">When Fortune still pursues her former blow,</l>
<l n="tr">What can I hope? What worse can still succeed?</l>
<l n="tr">What end of labors has your will decreed?</l>
<l n="tr">Antenor, from the midst of Grecian hosts,</l>
<l n="tr">Could pass secure, and pierce  th'  Illyrian coasts,</l>
<l n="tr">Where, rolling down the steep, Timavus raves</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' nine channels disembogues his waves.</l>
<l n="tr">At length he founded <placeName key="tgn,7003085" authname="tgn,7003085">Padua</placeName>'s happy seat,</l>
<l n="tr">And gave his Trojans a secure retreat;</l>
<l n="tr">There fix'd their arms, and there renew'd their name,</l>
<l n="tr">And there in quiet rules, and crown'd with fame.</l>
<l n="tr">But we, descended from your sacred line,</l>
<l n="tr">Entitled to your heav'n and rites divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Are banish'd earth; and, for the wrath of one,</l>
<l n="tr">Remov'd from <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> and the promis'd throne.</l>
<l n="tr">Are these our scepters? these our due rewards?</l>
<l n="tr">And is it thus that Jove his plighted faith regards?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="254" unit="card"/>To whom the Father of  th'  immortal race,</l>
<l n="tr">Smiling with that serene indulgent face,</l>
<l n="tr">With which he drives the clouds and clears the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">First gave a holy kiss; then thus replies:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Daughter, dismiss thy fears; to thy desire</l>
<l n="tr">The fates of thine are fix'd, and stand entire.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou shalt behold thy wish'd Lavinian walls;</l>
<l n="tr">And, ripe for heav'n, when fate Aeneas calls,</l>
<l n="tr">Then shalt thou bear him up, sublime, to me:</l>
<l n="tr">No councils have revers'd my firm decree.</l>
<l n="tr">And, lest new fears disturb thy happy state,</l>
<l n="tr">Know, I have search'd the mystic rolls of Fate:</l>
<l n="tr">Thy son (nor is  th'  appointed season far)</l>
<l n="tr">In <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> shall wage successful war,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall tame fierce nations in the bloody field,</l>
<l n="tr">And sov'reign laws impose, and cities build,</l>
<l n="tr">Till, after ev'ry foe subdued, the sun</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice thro' the signs his annual race shall run:</l>
<l n="tr">This is his time prefix'd. Ascanius then,</l>
<l n="tr">Now call'd Iulus, shall begin his reign.</l>
<l n="tr">He thirty rolling years the crown shall wear,</l>
<l n="tr">Then from <placeName key="perseus,Lavinium" authname="perseus,Lavinium">Lavinium</placeName> shall the seat transfer,</l>
<l n="tr">And, with hard labor, <placeName key="perseus,Alba Longa" authname="perseus,Alba Longa">Alba Longa</placeName> build.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="272" unit="card"/>The throne with his succession shall be fill'd</l>
<l n="tr">Three hundred circuits more: then shall be seen</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Ilia</persName> the fair, a priestess and a queen,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, full of Mars, in time, with kindly throes,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall at a birth two goodly boys disclose.</l>
<l n="tr">The royal babes a tawny wolf shall drain:</l>
<l n="tr">Then Romulus his grandsire's throne shall gain,</l>
<l n="tr">Of martial tow'rs the founder shall become,</l>
<l n="tr">The people Romans call, the city <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">To them no bounds of empire I assign,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor term of years to their immortal line.</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n haughty Juno, who, with endless broils,</l>
<l n="tr">Earth, seas, and heav'n, and Jove himself turmoils;</l>
<l n="tr">At length aton'd, her friendly pow'r shall join,</l>
<l n="tr">To cherish and advance the Trojan line.</l>
<l n="tr">The subject world shall <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>'s dominion own,</l>
<l n="tr">And, prostrate, shall adore the nation of the gown.</l>
<l n="tr">An age is ripening in revolving fate</l>
<l n="tr">When <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> shall overturn the Grecian state,</l>
<l n="tr">And sweet revenge her conqu'ring sons shall call,</l>
<l n="tr">To crush the people that conspir'd her fall.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Caesar from the Julian stock shall rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose empire ocean, and whose fame the skies</l>
<l n="tr">Alone shall bound; whom, fraught with eastern spoils,</l>
<l n="tr">Our heav'n, the just reward of human toils,</l>
<l n="tr">Securely shall repay with rites divine;</l>
<l n="tr">And incense shall ascend before his sacred shrine.</l>
<l n="tr">Then dire debate and impious war shall cease,</l>
<l n="tr">And the stern age be soften'd into peace:</l>
<l n="tr">Then banish'd Faith shall once again return,</l>
<l n="tr">And Vestal fires in hallow'd temples burn;</l>
<l n="tr">And Remus with Quirinus shall sustain</l>
<l n="tr">The righteous laws, and fraud and force restrain.</l>
<l n="tr">Janus himself before his fane shall wait,</l>
<l n="tr">And keep the dreadful issues of his gate,</l>
<l n="tr">With bolts and iron bars: within remains</l>
<l n="tr">Imprison'd Fury, bound in brazen chains;</l>
<l n="tr">High on a trophy rais'd, of useless arms,</l>
<l n="tr">He sits, and threats the world with vain alarms.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="297" unit="card"/>He said, and sent Cyllenius with command</l>
<l n="tr">To free the ports, and ope the Punic land</l>
<l n="tr">To Trojan guests; lest, ignorant of fate,</l>
<l n="tr">The queen might force them from her town and state.</l>
<l n="tr">Down from the steep of heav'n Cyllenius flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And cleaves with all his wings the yielding skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon on the Libyan shore descends the god,</l>
<l n="tr">Performs his message, and displays his rod:</l>
<l n="tr">The surly murmurs of the people cease;</l>
<l n="tr">And, as the fates requir'd, they give the peace:</l>
<l n="tr">The queen herself suspends the rigid laws,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans pities, and protects their cause.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="305" unit="card"/>Meantime, in shades of night Aeneas lies:</l>
<l n="tr">Care seiz'd his soul, and sleep forsook his eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">But, when the sun restor'd the cheerful day,</l>
<l n="tr">He rose, the coast and country to survey,</l>
<l n="tr">Anxious and eager to discover more.</l>
<l n="tr">It look'd a wild uncultivated shore;</l>
<l n="tr">But, whether humankind, or beasts alone</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd the new-found region, was unknown.</l>
<l n="tr">Beneath a ledge of rocks his fleet he hides:</l>
<l n="tr">Tall trees surround the mountain's shady sides;</l>
<l n="tr">The bending brow above a safe retreat provides.</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd with two pointed darts, he leaves his friends,</l>
<l n="tr">And true Achates on his steps attends.</l>
<l n="tr">Lo! in the deep recesses of the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Before his eyes his goddess mother stood:</l>
<l n="tr">A huntress in her habit and her mien;</l>
<l n="tr">Her dress a maid, her air confess'd a queen.</l>
<l n="tr">Bare were her knees, and knots her garments bind;</l>
<l n="tr">Loose was her hair, and wanton'd in the wind;</l>
<l n="tr">Her hand sustain'd a bow; her quiver hung behind.</l>
<l n="tr">She seem'd a virgin of the Spartan blood:</l>
<l n="tr">With such array Harpalyce bestrode</l>
<l n="tr">Her Thracian courser and outstripp'd the rapid flood.</l>
<l n="tr">“Ho, strangers! have you lately seen,” she said,</l>
<l n="tr">“One of my sisters, like myself array'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Who cross'd the lawn, or in the forest stray'd?</l>
<l n="tr">A painted quiver at her back she bore;</l>
<l n="tr">Varied with spots, a lynx's hide she wore;</l>
<l n="tr">And at full cry pursued the tusky boar.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="325" unit="card"/>Thus Venus: thus her son replied again:</l>
<l n="tr">“None of your sisters have we heard or seen,</l>
<l n="tr">O virgin! or what other name you bear</l>
<l n="tr">Above that style—O more than mortal fair!</l>
<l n="tr">Your voice and mien celestial birth betray!</l>
<l n="tr">If, as you seem, the sister of the day,</l>
<l n="tr">Or one at least of chaste Diana's train,</l>
<l n="tr">Let not an humble suppliant sue in vain;</l>
<l n="tr">But tell a stranger, long in tempests toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">What earth we tread, and who commands the coast?</l>
<l n="tr">Then on your name shall wretched mortals call,</l>
<l n="tr">And offer'd victims at your altars fall.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="335" unit="card"/>“I dare not,” she replied, “assume the name</l>
<l n="tr">Of goddess, or celestial honors claim:</l>
<l n="tr">For Tyrian virgins bows and quivers bear,</l>
<l n="tr">And purple buskins o'er their ankles wear.</l>
<l n="tr">Know, gentle youth, in Libyan lands you are—</l>
<l n="tr">A people rude in peace, and rough in war.</l>
<l n="tr">The rising city, which from far you see,</l>
<l n="tr">Is <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, and a Tyrian colony.</l>
<l n="tr">Phoenician Dido rules the growing state,</l>
<l n="tr">Who fled from <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, to shun her brother's hate.</l>
<l n="tr">Great were her wrongs, her story full of fate;</l>
<l n="tr">Which I will sum in short. Sichaeus, known</l>
<l n="tr">For wealth, and brother to the Punic throne,</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd fair Dido's bed; and either heart</l>
<l n="tr">At once was wounded with an equal dart.</l>
<l n="tr">Her father gave her, yet a spotless maid;</l>
<l n="tr">Pygmalion then the Tyrian scepter sway'd:</l>
<l n="tr">One who condemn'd divine and human laws.</l>
<l n="tr">Then strife ensued, and cursed gold the cause.</l>
<l n="tr">The monarch, blinded with desire of wealth,</l>
<l n="tr">With steel invades his brother's life by stealth;</l>
<l n="tr">Before the sacred altar made him bleed,</l>
<l n="tr">And long from her conceal'd the cruel deed.</l>
<l n="tr">Some tale, some new pretense, he daily coin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To soothe his sister, and delude her mind.</l>
<l n="tr">At length, in dead of night, the ghost appears</l>
<l n="tr">Of her unhappy lord: the specter stares,</l>
<l n="tr">And, with erected eyes, his bloody bosom bares.</l>
<l n="tr">The cruel altars and his fate he tells,</l>
<l n="tr">And the dire secret of his house reveals,</l>
<l n="tr">Then warns the widow, with her household gods,</l>
<l n="tr">To seek a refuge in remote abodes.</l>
<l n="tr">Last, to support her in so long a way,</l>
<l n="tr">He shows her where his hidden treasure lay.</l>
<l n="tr">Admonish'd thus, and seiz'd with mortal fright,</l>
<l n="tr">The queen provides companions of her flight:</l>
<l n="tr">They meet, and all combine to leave the state,</l>
<l n="tr">Who hate the tyrant, or who fear his hate.</l>
<l n="tr">They seize a fleet, which ready rigg'd they find;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor is Pygmalion's treasure left behind.</l>
<l n="tr">The vessels, heavy laden, put to sea</l>
<l n="tr">With prosp'rous winds; a woman leads the way.</l>
<l n="tr">I know not, if by stress of weather driv'n,</l>
<l n="tr">Or was their fatal course dispos'd by Heav'n;</l>
<l n="tr">At last they landed, where from far your eyes</l>
<l n="tr">May view the turrets of new <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> rise;</l>
<l n="tr">There bought a space of ground, which (Byrsa call'd,</l>
<l n="tr">From the bull's hide) they first inclos'd, and wall'd.</l>
<l n="tr">But whence are you? what country claims your birth?</l>
<l n="tr">What seek you, strangers, on our Libyan earth?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To whom, with sorrow streaming from his eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And deeply sighing, thus her son replies:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="372" unit="card"/>“Could you with patience hear, or I relate,</l>
<l n="tr">O nymph, the tedious annals of our fate!</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' such a train of woes if I should run,</l>
<l n="tr">The day would sooner than the tale be done!</l>
<l n="tr">From ancient <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, by force expell'd, we came—</l>
<l n="tr">If you by chance have heard the Trojan name.</l>
<l n="tr">On various seas by various tempests toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">At length we landed on your Libyan coast.</l>
<l n="tr">The good Aeneas am I call'd—a name,</l>
<l n="tr">While Fortune favor'd, not unknown to fame.</l>
<l n="tr">My household gods, companions of my woes,</l>
<l n="tr">With pious care I rescued from our foes.</l>
<l n="tr">To fruitful <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> my course was bent;</l>
<l n="tr">And from the King of Heav'n is my descent.</l>
<l n="tr">With twice ten sail I cross'd the Phrygian sea;</l>
<l n="tr">Fate and my mother goddess led my way.</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce sev'n, the thin remainders of my fleet,</l>
<l n="tr">From storms preserv'd, within your harbor meet.</l>
<l n="tr">Myself distress'd, an exile, and unknown,</l>
<l n="tr">Debarr'd from <placeName key="tgn,1000003" authname="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>, and from <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> thrown,</l>
<l n="tr">In Libyan desarts wander thus alone.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>His tender parent could no longer bear;</l>
<l n="tr">But, interposing, sought to soothe his care.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="387" unit="card"/>“Whoe'er you are—not unbelov'd by Heav'n,</l>
<l n="tr">Since on our friendly shore your ships are driv'n—</l>
<l n="tr">Have courage: to the gods permit the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the queen expose your just request.</l>
<l n="tr">Now take this earnest of success, for more:</l>
<l n="tr">Your scatter'd fleet is join'd upon the shore;</l>
<l n="tr">The winds are chang'd, your friends from danger free;</l>
<l n="tr">Or I renounce my skill in augury.</l>
<l n="tr">Twelve swans behold in beauteous order move,</l>
<l n="tr">And stoop with closing pinions from above;</l>
<l n="tr">Whom late the bird of Jove had driv'n along,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' the clouds pursued the scatt'ring throng:</l>
<l n="tr">Now, all united in a goodly team,</l>
<l n="tr">They skim the ground, and seek the quiet stream.</l>
<l n="tr">As they, with joy returning, clap their wings,</l>
<l n="tr">And ride the circuit of the skies in rings;</l>
<l n="tr">Not otherwise your ships, and ev'ry friend,</l>
<l n="tr">Already hold the port, or with swift sails descend.</l>
<l n="tr">No more advice is needful; but pursue</l>
<l n="tr">The path before you, and the town in view.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="402" unit="card"/>Thus having said, she turn'd, and made appear</l>
<l n="tr">Her neck refulgent, and dishevel'd hair,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, flowing from her shoulders, reach'd the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">And widely spread ambrosial scents around:</l>
<l n="tr">In length of train descends her sweeping gown;</l>
<l n="tr">And, by her graceful walk, the Queen of Love is known.</l>
<l n="tr">The prince pursued the parting deity</l>
<l n="tr">With words like these: “Ah! whither do you fly?</l>
<l n="tr">Unkind and cruel! to deceive your son</l>
<l n="tr">In borrow'd shapes, and his embrace to shun;</l>
<l n="tr">Never to bless my sight, but thus unknown;</l>
<l n="tr">And still to speak in accents not your own.”</l>
<l n="tr">Against the goddess these complaints he made,</l>
<l n="tr">But took the path, and her commands obey'd.</l>
<l n="tr">They march, obscure; for Venus kindly shrouds</l>
<l n="tr">With mists their persons, and involves in clouds,</l>
<l n="tr">That, thus unseen, their passage none might stay,</l>
<l n="tr">Or force to tell the causes of their way.</l>
<l n="tr">This part perform'd, the goddess flies sublime</l>
<l n="tr">To visit <placeName key="tgn,7002373" authname="tgn,7002373">Paphos</placeName> and her native clime;</l>
<l n="tr">Where garlands, ever green and ever fair,</l>
<l n="tr">With vows are offer'd, and with solemn pray'r:</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred altars in her temple smoke;</l>
<l n="tr">A thousand bleeding hearts her pow'r invoke.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="418" unit="card"/>They climb the next ascent, and, looking down,</l>
<l n="tr">Now at a nearer distance view the town.</l>
<l n="tr">The prince with wonder sees the stately tow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">Which late were huts and shepherds' homely bow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">The gates and streets; and hears, from ev'ry part,</l>
<l n="tr">The noise and busy concourse of the mart.</l>
<l n="tr">The toiling Tyrians on each other call</l>
<l n="tr">To ply their labor: some extend the wall;</l>
<l n="tr">Some build the citadel; the brawny throng</l>
<l n="tr">Or dig, or push unwieldly stones along.</l>
<l n="tr">Some for their dwellings choose a spot of ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, first design'd, with ditches they surround.</l>
<l n="tr">Some laws ordain; and some attend the choice</l>
<l n="tr">Of holy senates, and elect by voice.</l>
<l n="tr">Here some design a mole, while others there</l>
<l n="tr">Lay deep foundations for a theater;</l>
<l n="tr">From marble quarries mighty columns hew,</l>
<l n="tr">For ornaments of scenes, and future view.</l>
<l n="tr">Such is their toil, and such their busy pains,</l>
<l n="tr">As exercise the bees in flow'ry plains,</l>
<l n="tr">When winter past, and summer scarce begun,</l>
<l n="tr">Invites them forth to labor in the sun;</l>
<l n="tr">Some lead their youth abroad, while some condense</l>
<l n="tr">Their liquid store, and some in cells dispense;</l>
<l n="tr">Some at the gate stand ready to receive</l>
<l n="tr">The golden burthen, and their friends relieve;</l>
<l n="tr">All with united force, combine to drive</l>
<l n="tr">The lazy drones from the laborious hive:</l>
<l n="tr">With envy stung, they view each other's deeds;</l>
<l n="tr">The fragrant work with diligence proceeds.</l>
<l n="tr">“Thrice happy you, whose walls already rise!”</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas said, and view'd, with lifted eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Their lofty tow'rs; then, entiring at the gate,</l>
<l n="tr">Conceal'd in clouds (prodigious to relate)</l>
<l n="tr">He mix'd, unmark'd, among the busy throng,</l>
<l n="tr">Borne by the tide, and pass'd unseen along.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="441" unit="card"/>Full in the center of the town there stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Thick set with trees, a venerable wood.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrians, landing near this holy ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And digging here, a prosp'rous omen found:</l>
<l n="tr">From under earth a courser's head they drew,</l>
<l n="tr">Their growth and future fortune to foreshew.</l>
<l n="tr">This fated sign their foundress <persName>Juno</persName> gave,</l>
<l n="tr">Of a soil fruitful, and a people brave.</l>
<l n="tr">Sidonian Dido here with solemn state</l>
<l n="tr">Did Juno's temple build, and consecrate,</l>
<l n="tr">Enrich'd with gifts, and with a golden shrine;</l>
<l n="tr">But more the goddess made the place divine.</l>
<l n="tr">On brazen steps the marble threshold rose,</l>
<l n="tr">And brazen plates the cedar beams inclose:</l>
<l n="tr">The rafters are with brazen cov'rings crown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The lofty doors on brazen hinges sound.</l>
<l n="tr">What first Aeneas this place beheld,</l>
<l n="tr">Reviv'd his courage, and his fear expell'd.</l>
<l n="tr">For while, expecting there the queen, he rais'd</l>
<l n="tr">His wond'ring eyes, and round the temple gaz'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Admir'd the fortune of the rising town,</l>
<l n="tr">The striving artists, and their arts' renown;</l>
<l n="tr">He saw, in order painted on the wall,</l>
<l n="tr">Whatever did unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> befall:</l>
<l n="tr">The wars that fame around the world had blown,</l>
<l n="tr">All to the life, and ev'ry leader known.</l>
<l n="tr">There Agamemnon, Priam here, he spies,</l>
<l n="tr">And fierce Achilles, who both kings defies.</l>
<l n="tr">He stopp'd, and weeping said: “O friend! ev'n here</l>
<l n="tr">The monuments of Trojan woes appear!</l>
<l n="tr">Our known disasters fill ev'n foreign lands:</l>
<l n="tr">See there, where old unhappy Priam stands!</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n the mute walls relate the warrior's fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And Trojan griefs the Tyrians' pity claim.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="464" unit="card"/>He said (his tears a ready passage find),</l>
<l n="tr">Devouring what he saw so well design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And with an empty picture fed his mind:</l>
<l n="tr">For there he saw the fainting Grecians yield,</l>
<l n="tr">And here the trembling Trojans quit the field,</l>
<l n="tr">Pursued by fierce Achilles thro' the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">On his high chariot driving o'er the slain.</l>
<l n="tr">The tents of Rhesus next his grief renew,</l>
<l n="tr">By their white sails betray'd to nightly view;</l>
<l n="tr">And wakeful Diomede, whose cruel sword</l>
<l n="tr">The sentries slew, nor spar'd their slumb'ring lord,</l>
<l n="tr">Then took the fiery steeds, ere yet the food</l>
<l n="tr">Of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> they taste, or drink the Xanthian flood.</l>
<l n="tr">Elsewhere he saw where Troilus defied</l>
<l n="tr">Achilles, and unequal combat tried;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, where the boy disarm'd, with loosen'd reins,</l>
<l n="tr">Was by his horses hurried o'er the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">Hung by the neck and hair, and dragg'd around:</l>
<l n="tr">The hostile spear, yet sticking in his wound,</l>
<l n="tr">With tracks of blood inscrib'd the dusty ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Meantime the Trojan dames, oppress'd with woe,</l>
<l n="tr">To <persName>Pallas</persName>' fane in long procession go,</l>
<l n="tr">In hopes to reconcile their heav'nly foe.</l>
<l n="tr">They weep, they beat their breasts, they rend their hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And rich embroider'd vests for presents bear;</l>
<l n="tr">But the stern goddess stands unmov'd with pray'r.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice round the Trojan walls Achilles drew</l>
<l n="tr">The corpse of Hector, whom in fight he slew.</l>
<l n="tr">Here Priam sues; and there, for sums of gold,</l>
<l n="tr">The lifeless body of his son is sold.</l>
<l n="tr">So sad an object, and so well express'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Drew sighs and groans from the griev'd hero's breast,</l>
<l n="tr">To see the figure of his lifeless friend,</l>
<l n="tr">And his old sire his helpless hand extend.</l>
<l n="tr">Himself he saw amidst the Grecian train,</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd in the bloody battle on the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">And swarthy Memnon in his arms he knew,</l>
<l n="tr">His pompous ensigns, and his Indian crew.</l>
<l n="tr">Penthisilea there, with haughty grace,</l>
<l n="tr">Leads to the wars an Amazonian race:</l>
<l n="tr">In their right hands a pointed dart they wield;</l>
<l n="tr">The left, for ward, sustains the lunar shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Athwart her breast a golden belt she throws,</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the press alone provokes a thousand foes,</l>
<l n="tr">And dares her maiden arms to manly force oppose.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="494" unit="card"/>Thus while the Trojan prince employs his eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd on the walls with wonder and surprise,</l>
<l n="tr">The beauteous <persName>Dido</persName>, with a num'rous train</l>
<l n="tr">And pomp of guards, ascends the sacred fane.</l>
<l n="tr">Such on Eurotas' banks, or Cynthus' height,</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Diana</persName> seems; and so she charms the sight,</l>
<l n="tr">When in the dance the graceful goddess leads</l>
<l n="tr">The choir of nymphs, and overtops their heads:</l>
<l n="tr">Known by her quiver, and her lofty mien,</l>
<l n="tr">She walks majestic, and she looks their queen;</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Latona</persName> sees her shine above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">And feeds with secret joy her silent breast.</l>
<l n="tr">Such <persName>Dido</persName> was; with such becoming state,</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the crowd, she walks serenely great.</l>
<l n="tr">Their labor to her future sway she speeds,</l>
<l n="tr">And passing with a gracious glance proceeds;</l>
<l n="tr">Then mounts the throne, high plac'd before the shrine:</l>
<l n="tr">In crowds around, the swarming people join.</l>
<l n="tr">She takes petitions, and dispenses laws,</l>
<l n="tr">Hears and determines ev'ry private cause;</l>
<l n="tr">Their tasks in equal portions she divides,</l>
<l n="tr">And, where unequal, there by lots decides.</l>
<l n="tr">Another way by chance Aeneas bends</l>
<l n="tr">His eyes, and unexpected sees his friends,</l>
<l n="tr">Antheus, Sergestus grave, Cloanthus strong,</l>
<l n="tr">And at their backs a mighty Trojan throng,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom late the tempest on the billows toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And widely scatter'd on another coast.</l>
<l n="tr">The prince, unseen, surpris'd with wonder stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And longs, with joyful haste, to join their hands;</l>
<l n="tr">But, doubtful of the wish'd event, he stays,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the hollow cloud his friends surveys,</l>
<l n="tr">Impatient till they told their present state,</l>
<l n="tr">And where they left their ships, and what their fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And why they came, and what was their request;</l>
<l n="tr">For these were sent, commission'd by the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">To sue for leave to land their sickly men,</l>
<l n="tr">And gain admission to the gracious queen.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="520" unit="card"/>Ent'ring, with cries they fill'd the holy fane;</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus, with lowly voice, Ilioneus began:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“O queen! indulg'd by favor of the gods</l>
<l n="tr">To found an empire in these new abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">To build a town, with statutes to restrain</l>
<l n="tr">The wild inhabitants beneath thy reign,</l>
<l n="tr">We wretched Trojans, toss'd on ev'ry shore,</l>
<l n="tr">From sea to sea, thy clemency implore.</l>
<l n="tr">Forbid the fires our shipping to deface!</l>
<l n="tr">Receive  th'  unhappy fugitives to grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And spare the remnant of a pious race!</l>
<l n="tr">We come not with design of wasteful prey,</l>
<l n="tr">To drive the country, force the swains away:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor such our strength, nor such is our desire;</l>
<l n="tr">The vanquish'd dare not to such thoughts aspire.</l>
<l n="tr">A land there is, Hesperia nam'd of old;</l>
<l n="tr">The soil is fruitful, and the men are bold—</l>
<l n="tr"> th'  Oenotrians held it once—by common fame</l>
<l n="tr">Now call'd <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italia</placeName>, from the leader's name.</l>
<l n="tr">To that sweet region was our voyage bent,</l>
<l n="tr">When winds and ev'ry warring element</l>
<l n="tr">Disturb'd our course, and, far from sight of land,</l>
<l n="tr">Cast our torn vessels on the moving sand:</l>
<l n="tr">The sea came on; the South, with mighty roar,</l>
<l n="tr">Dispers'd and dash'd the rest upon the rocky shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Those few you see escap'd the Storm, and fear,</l>
<l n="tr">Unless you interpose, a shipwreck here.</l>
<l n="tr">What men, what monsters, what inhuman race,</l>
<l n="tr">What laws, what barb'rous customs of the place,</l>
<l n="tr">Shut up a desart shore to drowning men,</l>
<l n="tr">And drive us to the cruel seas again?</l>
<l n="tr">If our hard fortune no compassion draws,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor hospitable rights, nor human laws,</l>
<l n="tr">The gods are just, and will revenge our cause.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="544" unit="card"/>Aeneas was our prince: a juster lord,</l>
<l n="tr">Or nobler warrior, never drew a sword;</l>
<l n="tr">Observant of the right, religious of his word.</l>
<l n="tr">If yet he lives, and draws this vital air,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor we, his friends, of safety shall despair;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor you, great queen, these offices repent,</l>
<l n="tr">Which he will equal, and perhaps augment.</l>
<l n="tr">We want not cities, nor Sicilian coasts,</l>
<l n="tr">Where King Acestes Trojan lineage boasts.</l>
<l n="tr">Permit our ships a shelter on your shores,</l>
<l n="tr">Refitted from your woods with planks and oars,</l>
<l n="tr">That, if our prince be safe, we may renew</l>
<l n="tr">Our destin'd course, and <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> pursue.</l>
<l n="tr">But if, O best of men, the Fates ordain</l>
<l n="tr">That thou art swallow'd in the Libyan main,</l>
<l n="tr">And if our young Iulus be no more,</l>
<l n="tr">Dismiss our navy from your friendly shore,</l>
<l n="tr">That we to good Acestes may return,</l>
<l n="tr">And with our friends our common losses mourn.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus spoke Ilioneus: the Trojan crew</l>
<l n="tr">With cries and clamors his request renew.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="561" unit="card"/>The modest queen a while, with downcast eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Ponder'd the speech; then briefly thus replies:</l>
<l n="tr">“Trojans, dismiss your fears; my cruel fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And doubts attending an unsettled state,</l>
<l n="tr">Force me to guard my coast from foreign foes.</l>
<l n="tr">Who has not heard the story of your woes,</l>
<l n="tr">The name and fortune of your native place,</l>
<l n="tr">The fame and valor of the Phrygian race?</l>
<l n="tr">We Tyrians are not so devoid of sense,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor so remote from Phoebus' influence.</l>
<l n="tr">Whether to Latian shores your course is bent,</l>
<l n="tr">Or, driv'n by tempests from your first intent,</l>
<l n="tr">You seek the good Acestes' government,</l>
<l n="tr">Your men shall be receiv'd, your fleet repair'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And sail, with ships of convoy for your guard:</l>
<l n="tr">Or, would you stay, and join your friendly pow'rs</l>
<l n="tr">To raise and to defend the Tyrian tow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">My wealth, my city, and myself are yours.</l>
<l n="tr">And would to Heav'n, the Storm, you felt, would bring</l>
<l n="tr">On Carthaginian coasts your wand'ring king.</l>
<l n="tr">My people shall, by my command, explore</l>
<l n="tr">The ports and creeks of ev'ry winding shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And towns, and wilds, and shady woods, in quest</l>
<l n="tr">Of so renown'd and so desir'd a guest.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="579" unit="card"/>Rais'd in his mind the Trojan hero stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And long'd to break from out his ambient cloud:</l>
<l n="tr">Achates found it, and thus urg'd his way:</l>
<l n="tr">“From whence, O goddess-born, this long delay?</l>
<l n="tr">What more can you desire, your welcome sure,</l>
<l n="tr">Your fleet in safety, and your friends secure?</l>
<l n="tr">One only wants; and him we saw in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Oppose the Storm, and swallow'd in the main.</l>
<l n="tr">Orontes in his fate our forfeit paid;</l>
<l n="tr">The rest agrees with what your mother said.”</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had he spoken, when the cloud gave way,</l>
<l n="tr">The mists flew upward and dissolv'd in day.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The Trojan chief appear'd in open sight,</l>
<l n="tr">August in visage, and serenely bright.</l>
<l n="tr">His mother goddess, with her hands divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Had form'd his curling locks, and made his temples shine,</l>
<l n="tr">And giv'n his rolling eyes a sparkling grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And breath'd a youthful vigor on his face;</l>
<l n="tr">Like polish'd ivory, beauteous to behold,</l>
<l n="tr">Or Parian marble, when enchas'd in gold:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus radiant from the circling cloud he broke,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus with manly modesty he spoke:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“He whom you seek am I; by tempests toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And sav'd from shipwreck on your Libyan coast;</l>
<l n="tr">Presenting, gracious queen, before your throne,</l>
<l n="tr">A prince that owes his life to you alone.</l>
<l n="tr">Fair majesty, the refuge and redress</l>
<l n="tr">Of those whom fate pursues, and wants oppress,</l>
<l n="tr">You, who your pious offices employ</l>
<l n="tr">To save the relics of abandon'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>;</l>
<l n="tr">Receive the shipwreck'd on your friendly shore,</l>
<l n="tr">With hospitable rites relieve the poor;</l>
<l n="tr">Associate in your town a wand'ring train,</l>
<l n="tr">And strangers in your palace entertain:</l>
<l n="tr">What thanks can wretched fugitives return,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, scatter'd thro' the world, in exile mourn?</l>
<l n="tr">The gods, if gods to goodness are inclin'd;</l>
<l n="tr">If acts of mercy touch their heav'nly mind,</l>
<l n="tr">And, more than all the gods, your gen'rous heart.</l>
<l n="tr">Conscious of worth, requite its own desert!</l>
<l n="tr">In you this age is happy, and this earth,</l>
<l n="tr">And parents more than mortal gave you birth.</l>
<l n="tr">While rolling rivers into seas shall run,</l>
<l n="tr">And round the space of heav'n the radiant sun;</l>
<l n="tr">While trees the mountain tops with shades supply,</l>
<l n="tr">Your honor, name, and praise shall never die.</l>
<l n="tr">Whate'er abode my fortune has assign'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Your image shall be present in my mind.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, he turn'd with pious haste,</l>
<l n="tr">And joyful his expecting friends embrac'd:</l>
<l n="tr">With his right hand Ilioneus was grac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Serestus with his left; then to his breast</l>
<l n="tr">Cloanthus and the noble Gyas press'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And so by turns descended to the rest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="613" unit="card"/>The Tyrian queen stood fix'd upon his face,</l>
<l n="tr">Pleas'd with his motions, ravish'd with his grace;</l>
<l n="tr">Admir'd his fortunes, more admir'd the man;</l>
<l n="tr">Then recollected stood, and thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“What fate, O goddess-born; what angry pow'rs</l>
<l n="tr">Have cast you shipwrack'd on our barren shores?</l>
<l n="tr">Are you the great Aeneas, known to fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Who from celestial seed your lineage claim?</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The same Aeneas whom fair Venus bore</l>
<l n="tr">To fam'd Anchises on  th'  Idaean shore?</l>
<l n="tr">It calls into my mind, tho' then a child,</l>
<l n="tr">When Teucer came, from <placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus" authname="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName> exil'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And sought my father's aid, to be restor'd:</l>
<l n="tr">My father Belus then with fire and sword</l>
<l n="tr">Invaded <placeName key="tgn,1000112" authname="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, made the region bare,</l>
<l n="tr">And, conqu'ring, finish'd the successful war.</l>
<l n="tr">From him the Trojan siege I understood,</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian chiefs, and your illustrious blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Your foe himself the Dardan valor prais'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And his own ancestry from Trojans rais'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Enter, my noble guest, and you shall find,</l>
<l n="tr">If not a costly welcome, yet a kind:</l>
<l n="tr">For I myself, like you, have been distress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Till Heav'n afforded me this place of rest;</l>
<l n="tr">Like you, an alien in a land unknown,</l>
<l n="tr">I learn to pity woes so like my own.”</l>
<l n="tr">She said, and to the palace led her guest;</l>
<l n="tr">Then offer'd incense, and proclaim'd a feast.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor yet less careful for her absent friends,</l>
<l n="tr">Twice ten fat oxen to the ships she sends;</l>
<l n="tr">Besides a hundred boars, a hundred lambs,</l>
<l n="tr">With bleating cries, attend their milky dams;</l>
<l n="tr">And jars of gen'rous wine and spacious bowls</l>
<l n="tr">She gives, to cheer the sailors' drooping souls.</l>
<l n="tr">Now purple hangings clothe the palace walls,</l>
<l n="tr">And sumptuous feasts are made in splendid halls:</l>
<l n="tr">On Tyrian carpets, richly wrought, they dine;</l>
<l n="tr">With loads of massy plate the sideboards shine,</l>
<l n="tr">And antique vases, all of gold emboss'd</l>
<l n="tr">(The gold itself inferior to the cost),</l>
<l n="tr">Of curious work, where on the sides were seen</l>
<l n="tr">The fights and figures of illustrious men,</l>
<l n="tr">From their first founder to the present queen.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="643" unit="card"/>The good Aeneas, paternal care</l>
<l n="tr">Iulus' absence could no longer bear,</l>
<l n="tr">Dispatch'd Achates to the ships in haste,</l>
<l n="tr">To give a glad relation of the past,</l>
<l n="tr">And, fraught with precious gifts, to bring the boy,</l>
<l n="tr">Snatch'd from the ruins of unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>:</l>
<l n="tr">A robe of tissue, stiff with golden wire;</l>
<l n="tr">An upper vest, once Helen's rich attire,</l>
<l n="tr">From <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> by the fam'd adultress brought,</l>
<l n="tr">With golden flow'rs and winding foliage wrought,</l>
<l n="tr">Her mother Leda's present, when she came</l>
<l n="tr">To ruin <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> and set the world on flame;</l>
<l n="tr">The scepter Priam's eldest daughter bore,</l>
<l n="tr">Her orient necklace, and the crown she wore</l>
<l n="tr">Of double texture, glorious to behold,</l>
<l n="tr">One order set with gems, and one with gold.</l>
<l n="tr">Instructed thus, the wise Achates goes,</l>
<l n="tr">And in his diligence his duty shows.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="657" unit="card"/>But Venus, anxious for her son's affairs,</l>
<l n="tr">New counsels tries, and new designs prepares:</l>
<l n="tr">That Cupid should assume the shape and face</l>
<l n="tr">Of sweet Ascanius, and the sprightly grace;</l>
<l n="tr">Should bring the presents, in her nephew's stead,</l>
<l n="tr">And in Eliza's veins the gentle poison shed:</l>
<l n="tr">For much she fear'd the Tyrians, double-tongued,</l>
<l n="tr">And knew the town to Juno's care belong'd.</l>
<l n="tr">These thoughts by night her golden slumbers broke,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus alarm'd, to winged Love she spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“My son, my strength, whose mighty pow'r alone</l>
<l n="tr">Controls the Thund'rer on his awful throne,</l>
<l n="tr">To thee thy much-afflicted mother flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And on thy succor and thy faith relies.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou know'st, my son, how Jove's revengeful wife,</l>
<l n="tr">By force and fraud, attempts thy brother's life;</l>
<l n="tr">And often hast thou mourn'd with me his pains.</l>
<l n="tr">Him Dido now with blandishment detains;</l>
<l n="tr">But I suspect the town where Juno reigns.</l>
<l n="tr">For this 't is needful to prevent her art,</l>
<l n="tr">And fire with love the proud Phoenician's heart:</l>
<l n="tr">A love so violent, so strong, so sure,</l>
<l n="tr">As neither age can change, nor art can cure.</l>
<l n="tr">How this may be perform'd, now take my mind:</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius by his father is design'd</l>
<l n="tr">To come, with presents laden, from the port,</l>
<l n="tr">To gratify the queen, and gain the court.</l>
<l n="tr">I mean to plunge the boy in pleasing sleep,</l>
<l n="tr">And, ravish'd, in Idalian bow'rs to keep,</l>
<l n="tr">Or high <placeName key="tgn,7010869" authname="tgn,7010869">Cythera</placeName>, that the sweet deceit</l>
<l n="tr">May pass unseen, and none prevent the cheat.</l>
<l n="tr">Take thou his form and shape. I beg the grace</l>
<l n="tr">But only for a night's revolving space:</l>
<l n="tr">Thyself a boy, assume a boy's dissembled face;</l>
<l n="tr">That when, amidst the fervor of the feast,</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrian hugs and fonds thee on her breast,</l>
<l n="tr">And with sweet kisses in her arms constrains,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou may'st infuse thy venom in her veins.”</l>
<l n="tr">The God of Love obeys, and sets aside</l>
<l n="tr">His bow and quiver, and his plumy pride;</l>
<l n="tr">He walks Iulus in his mother's sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And in the sweet resemblance takes delight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The goddess then to young Ascanius flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a pleasing slumber seals his eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">Lull'd in her lap, amidst a train of Loves,</l>
<l n="tr">She gently bears him to her blissful groves,</l>
<l n="tr">Then with a wreath of myrtle crowns his head,</l>
<l n="tr">And softly lays him on a flow'ry bed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="695" unit="card"/>Cupid meantime assum'd his form and face,</l>
<l n="tr">Foll'wing Achates with a shorter pace,</l>
<l n="tr">And brought the gifts. The queen already sate</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the Trojan lords, in shining state,</l>
<l n="tr">High on a golden bed: her princely guest</l>
<l n="tr">Was next her side; in order sate the rest.</l>
<l n="tr">Then canisters with bread are heap'd on high;</l>
<l n="tr"> th'  attendants water for their hands supply,</l>
<l n="tr">And, having wash'd, with silken towels dry.</l>
<l n="tr">Next fifty handmaids in long order bore</l>
<l n="tr">The censers, and with fumes the gods adore:</l>
<l n="tr">Then youths, and virgins twice as many, join</l>
<l n="tr">To place the dishes, and to serve the wine.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrian train, admitted to the feast,</l>
<l n="tr">Approach, and on the painted couches rest.</l>
<l n="tr">All on the Trojan gifts with wonder gaze,</l>
<l n="tr">But view the beauteous boy with more amaze,</l>
<l n="tr">His rosy-color'd cheeks, his radiant eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">His motions, voice, and shape, and all the god's disguise;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor pass unprais'd the vest and veil divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Which wand'ring foliage and rich flow'rs entwine.</l>
<l n="tr">But, far above the rest, the royal dame,</l>
<l n="tr">(Already doom'd to love's disastrous flame,)</l>
<l n="tr">With eyes insatiate, and tumultuous joy,</l>
<l n="tr">Beholds the presents, and admires the boy.</l>
<l n="tr">The guileful god about the hero long,</l>
<l n="tr">With children's play, and false embraces, hung;</l>
<l n="tr">Then sought the queen: she took him to her arms</l>
<l n="tr">With greedy pleasure, and devour'd his charms.</l>
<l n="tr">Unhappy Dido little thought what guest,</l>
<l n="tr">How dire a god, she drew so near her breast;</l>
<l n="tr">But he, not mindless of his mother's pray'r,</l>
<l n="tr">Works in the pliant bosom of the fair,</l>
<l n="tr">And molds her heart anew, and blots her former care.</l>
<l n="tr">The dead is to the living love resign'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And all Aeneas enters in her mind.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="723" unit="card"/>Now, when the rage of hunger was appeas'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The meat remov'd, and ev'ry guest was pleas'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The golden bowls with sparkling wine are crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' the palace cheerful cries resound.</l>
<l n="tr">From gilded roofs depending lamps display</l>
<l n="tr">Nocturnal beams, that emulate the day.</l>
<l n="tr">A golden bowl, that shone with gems divine,</l>
<l n="tr">The queen commanded to be crown'd with wine:</l>
<l n="tr">The bowl that Belus us'd, and all the Tyrian line.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, silence thro' the hall proclaim'd, she spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“O hospitable Jove! we thus invoke,</l>
<l n="tr">With solemn rites, thy sacred name and pow'r;</l>
<l n="tr">Bless to both nations this auspicious hour!</l>
<l n="tr">So may the Trojan and the Tyrian line</l>
<l n="tr">In lasting concord from this day combine.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, <persName>Bacchus</persName>, god of joys and friendly cheer,</l>
<l n="tr">And gracious <persName>Juno</persName>, both be present here!</l>
<l n="tr">And you, my lords of <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, your vows address</l>
<l n="tr">To Heav'n with mine, to ratify the peace.”</l>
<l n="tr">The goblet then she took, with nectar crown'd</l>
<l n="tr">(Sprinkling the first libations on the ground,)</l>
<l n="tr">And rais'd it to her mouth with sober grace;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, sipping, offer'd to the next in place.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was Bitias whom she call'd, a thirsty soul;</l>
<l n="tr">He took challenge, and embrac'd the bowl,</l>
<l n="tr">With pleasure swill'd the gold, nor ceas'd to draw,</l>
<l n="tr">Till he the bottom of the brimmer saw.</l>
<l n="tr">The goblet goes around: Iopas brought</l>
<l n="tr">His golden lyre, and sung what ancient Atlas taught:</l>
<l n="tr">The various labors of the wand'ring moon,</l>
<l n="tr">And whence proceed  th'  eclipses of the sun;</l>
<l n="tr"> th'  original of men and beasts; and whence</l>
<l n="tr">The rains arise, and fires their warmth dispense,</l>
<l n="tr">And fix'd and erring stars dispose their influence;</l>
<l n="tr">What shakes the solid earth; what cause delays</l>
<l n="tr">The summer nights and shortens winter days.</l>
<l n="tr">With peals of shouts the Tyrians praise the song:</l>
<l n="tr">Those peals are echo'd by the Trojan throng.</l>
<l n="tr"> th'  unhappy queen with talk prolong'd the night,</l>
<l n="tr">And drank large draughts of love with vast delight;</l>
<l n="tr">Of Priam much enquir'd, of <persName>Hector</persName> more;</l>
<l n="tr">Then ask'd what arms the swarthy Memnon wore,</l>
<l n="tr">What troops he landed on the Trojan shore;</l>
<l n="tr">The steeds of Diomede varied the discourse,</l>
<l n="tr">And fierce Achilles, with his matchless force;</l>
<l n="tr">At length, as fate and her ill stars requir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To hear the series of the war desir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">“Relate at large, my godlike guest,” she said,</l>
<l n="tr">“The Grecian stratagems, the town betray'd:</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal issue of so long a war,</l>
<l n="tr">Your flight, your wand'rings, and your woes, declare;</l>
<l n="tr">For, since on ev'ry sea, on ev'ry coast,</l>
<l n="tr">Your men have been distress'd, your navy toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n times the sun has either tropic view'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The winter banish'd, and the spring renew'd.”</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>