<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="10" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">The gates of heav'n unfold: Jove summons all</l>
<l n="tr">The gods to council in the common hall.</l>
<l n="tr">Sublimely seated, he surveys from far</l>
<l n="tr">The fields, the camp, the fortune of the war,</l>
<l n="tr">And all  th'  inferior world. From first to last,</l>
<l n="tr">The sov'reign senate in degrees are plac'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus  th'  almighty sire began: “Ye gods,</l>
<l n="tr">Natives or denizens of blest abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">From whence these murmurs, and this change of mind,</l>
<l n="tr">This backward fate from what was first design'd?</l>
<l n="tr">Why this protracted war, when my commands</l>
<l n="tr">Pronounc'd a peace, and gave the Latian lands?</l>
<l n="tr">What fear or hope on either part divides</l>
<l n="tr">Our heav'ns, and arms our powers on diff'rent sides?</l>
<l n="tr">A lawful time of war at length will come,</l>
<l n="tr">(Nor need your haste anticipate the doom),</l>
<l n="tr">When <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> shall contend the world with <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall force the rigid rocks and Alpine chains,</l>
<l n="tr">And, like a flood, come pouring on the plains.</l>
<l n="tr">Then is your time for faction and debate,</l>
<l n="tr">For partial favor, and permitted hate.</l>
<l n="tr">Let now your immature dissension cease;</l>
<l n="tr">Sit quiet, and compose your souls to peace.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="16" unit="card"/>Thus Jupiter in few unfolds the charge;</l>
<l n="tr">But lovely Venus thus replies at large:</l>
<l n="tr">“O pow'r immense, eternal energy,</l>
<l n="tr">(For to what else protection can we fly?)</l>
<l n="tr">Seest thou the proud Rutulians, how they dare</l>
<l n="tr">In fields, unpunish'd, and insult my care?</l>
<l n="tr">How lofty Turnus vaunts amidst his train,</l>
<l n="tr">In shining arms, triumphant on the plain?</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n in their lines and trenches they contend,</l>
<l n="tr">And scarce their walls the Trojan troops defend:</l>
<l n="tr">The town is fill'd with slaughter, and o'erfloats,</l>
<l n="tr">With a red deluge, their increasing moats.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, ignorant, and far from thence,</l>
<l n="tr">Has left a camp expos'd, without defense.</l>
<l n="tr">This endless outrage shall they still sustain?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> renew'd be forc'd and fir'd again?</l>
<l n="tr">A second siege my banish'd issue fears,</l>
<l n="tr">And a new Diomede in arms appears.</l>
<l n="tr">One more audacious mortal will be found;</l>
<l n="tr">And I, thy daughter, wait another wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, if with fates averse, without thy leave,</l>
<l n="tr">The Latian lands my progeny receive,</l>
<l n="tr">Bear they the pains of violated law,</l>
<l n="tr">And thy protection from their aid withdraw.</l>
<l n="tr">But, if the gods their sure success foretell;</l>
<l n="tr">If those of heav'n consent with those of hell,</l>
<l n="tr">To promise <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; who dare debate</l>
<l n="tr">The pow'r of Jove, or fix another fate?</l>
<l n="tr">What should I tell of tempests on the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Of Aeolus usurping Neptune's reign?</l>
<l n="tr">Of Iris sent, with Bacchanalian heat</l>
<l n="tr">T' inspire the matrons, and destroy the fleet?</l>
<l n="tr">Now Juno to the Stygian sky descends,</l>
<l n="tr">Solicits hell for aid, and arms the fiends.</l>
<l n="tr">That new example wanted yet above:</l>
<l n="tr">An act that well became the wife of Jove!</l>
<l n="tr">Alecto, rais'd by her, with rage inflames</l>
<l n="tr">The peaceful bosoms of the Latian dames.</l>
<l n="tr">Imperial sway no more exalts my mind;</l>
<l n="tr">(Such hopes I had indeed, while Heav'n was kind;)</l>
<l n="tr">Now let my happier foes possess my place,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Jove prefers before the Trojan race;</l>
<l n="tr">And conquer they, whom you with conquest grace.</l>
<l n="tr">Since you can spare, from all your wide command,</l>
<l n="tr">No spot of earth, no hospitable land,</l>
<l n="tr">Which may my wand'ring fugitives receive;</l>
<l n="tr">(Since haughty Juno will not give you leave;)</l>
<l n="tr">Then, father, (if I still may use that name,)</l>
<l n="tr">By ruin'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, yet smoking from the flame,</l>
<l n="tr">I beg you, let Ascanius, by my care,</l>
<l n="tr">Be freed from danger, and dismiss'd the war:</l>
<l n="tr">Inglorious let him live, without a crown.</l>
<l n="tr">The father may be cast on coasts unknown,</l>
<l n="tr">Struggling with fate; but let me save the son.</l>
<l n="tr">Mine is <placeName key="tgn,7010869" authname="tgn,7010869">Cythera</placeName>, mine the Cyprian tow'rs:</l>
<l n="tr">In those recesses, and those sacred bow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">Obscurely let him rest; his right resign</l>
<l n="tr">To promis'd empire, and his Julian line.</l>
<l n="tr">Then <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> may  th'  Ausonian towns destroy,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor fear the race of a rejected boy.</l>
<l n="tr">What profits it my son to scape the fire,</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd with his gods, and loaded with his sire;</l>
<l n="tr">To pass the perils of the seas and wind;</l>
<l n="tr">Evade the Greeks, and leave the war behind;</l>
<l n="tr">To reach  th'  Italian shores; if, after all,</l>
<l n="tr">Our second <placeName key="perseus,Pergamon" authname="perseus,Pergamon">Pergamus</placeName> is doom'd to fall?</l>
<l n="tr">Much better had he curb'd his high desires,</l>
<l n="tr">And hover'd o'er his ill-extinguish'd fires.</l>
<l n="tr">To Simois' banks the fugitives restore,</l>
<l n="tr">And give them back to war, and all the woes before.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="62" unit="card"/>Deep indignation swell'd <placeName key="tgn,6005278" authname="tgn,6005278">Saturnia</placeName>'s heart:</l>
<l n="tr">“And must I own,” she said, “my secret smarT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">What with more decence were in silence kept,</l>
<l n="tr">And, but for this unjust reproach, had slept?</l>
<l n="tr">Did god or man your fav'rite son advise,</l>
<l n="tr">With war unhop'd the Latians to surprise?</l>
<l n="tr">By fate, you boast, and by the gods' decree,</l>
<l n="tr">He left his native land for <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>!</l>
<l n="tr">Confess the truth; by mad Cassandra, more</l>
<l n="tr">Than Heav'n inspir'd, he sought a foreign shore!</l>
<l n="tr">Did I persuade to trust his second <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">To the raw conduct of a beardless boy,</l>
<l n="tr">With walls unfinish'd, which himself forsakes,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' the waves a wand'ring voyage takes?</l>
<l n="tr">When have I urg'd him meanly to demand</l>
<l n="tr">The Tuscan aid, and arm a quiet land?</l>
<l n="tr">Did I or Iris give this mad advice,</l>
<l n="tr">Or made the fool himself the fatal choice?</l>
<l n="tr">You think it hard, the Latians should destroy</l>
<l n="tr">With swords your Trojans, and with fires your <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>!</l>
<l n="tr">Hard and unjust indeed, for men to draw</l>
<l n="tr">Their native air, nor take a foreign law!</l>
<l n="tr">That Turnus is permitted still to live,</l>
<l n="tr">To whom his birth a god and goddess give!</l>
<l n="tr">But yet is just and lawful for your line</l>
<l n="tr">To drive their fields, and force with fraud to join;</l>
<l n="tr">Realms, not your own, among your clans divide,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the bridegroom tear the promis'd bride;</l>
<l n="tr">Petition, while you public arms prepare;</l>
<l n="tr">Pretend a peace, and yet provoke a war!</l>
<l n="tr">'T was giv'n to you, your darling son to shroud,</l>
<l n="tr">To draw the dastard from the fighting crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, for a man, obtend an empty cloud.</l>
<l n="tr">From flaming fleets you turn'd the fire away,</l>
<l n="tr">And chang'd the ships to daughters of the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">But is my crime—the Queen of Heav'n offends,</l>
<l n="tr">If she presume to save her suff'ring friends!</l>
<l n="tr">Your son, not knowing what his foes decree,</l>
<l n="tr">You say, is absent: absent let him be.</l>
<l n="tr">Yours is <placeName key="tgn,7010869" authname="tgn,7010869">Cythera</placeName>, yours the Cyprian tow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">The soft recesses, and the sacred bow'rs.</l>
<l n="tr">Why do you then these needless arms prepare,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus provoke a people prone to war?</l>
<l n="tr">Did I with fire the Trojan town deface,</l>
<l n="tr">Or hinder from return your exil'd race?</l>
<l n="tr">Was I the cause of mischief, or the man</l>
<l n="tr">Whose lawless lust the fatal war began?</l>
<l n="tr">Think on whose faith  th'  adult'rous youth relied;</l>
<l n="tr">Who promis'd, who procur'd, the Spartan bride?</l>
<l n="tr">When all  th'  united states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> combin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To purge the world of the perfidious kind,</l>
<l n="tr">Then was your time to fear the Trojan fate:</l>
<l n="tr">Your quarrels and complaints are now too late.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="96" unit="card"/>Thus Juno. Murmurs rise, with mix'd applause,</l>
<l n="tr">Just as they favor or dislike the cause.</l>
<l n="tr">So winds, when yet unfledg'd in woods they lie,</l>
<l n="tr">In whispers first their tender voices try,</l>
<l n="tr">Then issue on the main with bellowing rage,</l>
<l n="tr">And storms to trembling mariners presage.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus to both replied  th'  imperial god,</l>
<l n="tr">Who shakes heav'n's axles with his awful nod.</l>
<l n="tr">(When he begins, the silent senate stand</l>
<l n="tr">With rev'rence, list'ning to the dread command:</l>
<l n="tr">The clouds dispel; the winds their breath restrain;</l>
<l n="tr">And the hush'd waves lie flatted on the main.)</l>
<l n="tr">“Celestials, your attentive ears incline!</l>
<l n="tr">Since,” said the god, “the Trojans must not join</l>
<l n="tr">In wish'd alliance with the Latian line;</l>
<l n="tr">Since endless jarrings and immortal hate</l>
<l n="tr">Tend but to discompose our happy state;</l>
<l n="tr">The war henceforward be resign'd to fate:</l>
<l n="tr">Each to his proper fortune stand or fall;</l>
<l n="tr">Equal and unconcern'd I look on all.</l>
<l n="tr">Rutulians, Trojans, are the same to me;</l>
<l n="tr">And both shall draw the lots their fates decree.</l>
<l n="tr">Let these assault, if Fortune be their friend;</l>
<l n="tr">And, if she favors those, let those defend:</l>
<l n="tr">The Fates will find their way.” The Thund'rer said,</l>
<l n="tr">And shook the sacred honors of his head,</l>
<l n="tr">Attesting Styx,  th'  inviolable flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And the black regions of his brother god.</l>
<l n="tr">Trembled the poles of heav'n, and earth confess'd the nod.</l>
<l n="tr">This end the sessions had: the senate rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And to his palace wait their sov'reign thro' the skies.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="118" unit="card"/>Meantime, intent upon their siege, the foes</l>
<l n="tr">Within their walls the Trojan host inclose:</l>
<l n="tr">They wound, they kill, they watch at ev'ry gate;</l>
<l n="tr">Renew the fires, and urge their happy fate.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Th' Aeneans wish in vain their wanted chief,</l>
<l n="tr">Hopeless of flight, more hopeless of relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Thin on the tow'rs they stand; and ev'n those few</l>
<l n="tr">A feeble, fainting, and dejected crew.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet in the face of danger some there stood:</l>
<l n="tr">The two bold brothers of Sarpedon's blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Asius and Acmon; both  th'  Assaraci;</l>
<l n="tr">Young Haemon, and tho' young, resolv'd to die.</l>
<l n="tr">With these were Clarus and Thymoetes join'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Tibris and Castor, both of Lycian kind.</l>
<l n="tr">From Acmon's hands a rolling stone there came,</l>
<l n="tr">So large, it half deserv'd a mountain's name:</l>
<l n="tr">Strong-sinew'd was the youth, and big of bone;</l>
<l n="tr">His brother Mnestheus could not more have done,</l>
<l n="tr">Or the great father of  th'  intrepid son.</l>
<l n="tr">Some firebrands throw, some flights of arrows send;</l>
<l n="tr">And some with darts, and some with stones defend.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Amid the press appears the beauteous boy,</l>
<l n="tr">The care of Venus, and the hope of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">His lovely face unarm'd, his head was bare;</l>
<l n="tr">In ringlets o'er his shoulders hung his hair.</l>
<l n="tr">His forehead circled with a diadem;</l>
<l n="tr">Distinguish'd from the crowd, he shines a gem,</l>
<l n="tr">Enchas'd in gold, or polish'd iv'ry set,</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the meaner foil of sable jet.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nor Ismarus was wanting to the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Directing pointed arrows from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">And death with poison arm'd—in <placeName key="tgn,7016631" authname="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName> born,</l>
<l n="tr">Where plenteous harvests the fat fields adorn;</l>
<l n="tr">Where proud Pactolus floats the fruitful lands,</l>
<l n="tr">And leaves a rich manure of golden sands.</l>
<l n="tr">There Capys, author of the Capuan name,</l>
<l n="tr">And there was Mnestheus too, increas'd in fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Since Turnus from the camp he cast with shame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="146" unit="card"/>Thus mortal war was wag'd on either side.</l>
<l n="tr">Meantime the hero cuts the nightly tide:</l>
<l n="tr">For, anxious, from Evander when he went,</l>
<l n="tr">He sought the Tyrrhene camp, and Tarchon's tent;</l>
<l n="tr">Expos'd the cause of coming to the chief;</l>
<l n="tr">His name and country told, and ask'd relief;</l>
<l n="tr">Propos'd the terms; his own small strength declar'd;</l>
<l n="tr">What vengeance proud Mezentius had prepar'd:</l>
<l n="tr">What Turnus, bold and violent, design'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Then shew'd the slipp'ry state of humankind,</l>
<l n="tr">And fickle fortune; warn'd him to beware,</l>
<l n="tr">And to his wholesome counsel added pray'r.</l>
<l n="tr">Tarchon, without delay, the treaty signs,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the Trojan troops the Tuscan joins.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>They soon set sail; nor now the fates withstand;</l>
<l n="tr">Their forces trusted with a foreign hand.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas leads; upon his stern appear</l>
<l n="tr">Two lions carv'd, which rising Ida bear—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Ida, to wand'ring Trojans ever dear.</l>
<l n="tr">Under their grateful shade Aeneas sate,</l>
<l n="tr">Revolving war's events, and various fate.</l>
<l n="tr">His left young Pallas kept, fix'd to his side,</l>
<l n="tr">And oft of winds enquir'd, and of the tide;</l>
<l n="tr">Oft of the stars, and of their wat'ry way;</l>
<l n="tr">And what he suffer'd both by land and sea.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="163" unit="card"/>Now, sacred sisters, open all your spring!</l>
<l n="tr">The Tuscan leaders, and their army sing,</l>
<l n="tr">Which follow'd great Aeneas to the war:</l>
<l n="tr">Their arms, their numbers, and their names declare.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="166" unit="card"/>A thousand youths brave Massicus obey,</l>
<l n="tr">Borne in the Tiger thro' the foaming sea;</l>
<l n="tr">From Asium brought, and <placeName key="perseus,Cosa" authname="perseus,Cosa">Cosa</placeName>, by his care:</l>
<l n="tr">For arms, light quivers, bows and shafts, they bear.</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Abas next: his men bright armor wore;</l>
<l n="tr">His stern Apollo's golden statue bore.</l>
<l n="tr">Six hundred <placeName key="perseus,Populonia" authname="perseus,Populonia">Populonia</placeName> sent along,</l>
<l n="tr">All skill'd in martial exercise, and strong.</l>
<l n="tr">Three hundred more for battle <placeName key="tgn,7006197" authname="tgn,7006197">Ilva</placeName> joins,</l>
<l n="tr">An isle renown'd for steel, and unexhausted mines.</l>
<l n="tr">Asylas on his prow the third appears,</l>
<l n="tr">Who heav'n interprets, and the wand'ring stars;</l>
<l n="tr">From offer'd entrails prodigies expounds,</l>
<l n="tr">And peals of thunder, with presaging sounds.</l>
<l n="tr">A thousand spears in warlike order stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Sent by the Pisans under his command.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Fair Astur follows in the wat'ry field,</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of his manag'd horse and painted shield.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Gravisca" authname="perseus,Gravisca">Gravisca</placeName>, noisome from the neighb'ring fen,</l>
<l n="tr">And his own <placeName key="perseus,Caere" authname="perseus,Caere">Caere</placeName>, sent three hundred men;</l>
<l n="tr">With those which Minio's fields and <placeName key="tgn,7008308" authname="tgn,7008308">Pyrgi</placeName> gave,</l>
<l n="tr">All bred in arms, unanimous, and brave.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="185" unit="card"/>Thou, Muse, the name of Cinyras renew,</l>
<l n="tr">And brave Cupavo follow'd but by few;</l>
<l n="tr">Whose helm confess'd the lineage of the man,</l>
<l n="tr">And bore, with wings display'd, a silver swan.</l>
<l n="tr">Love was the fault of his fam'd ancestry,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose forms and fortunes in his ensigns fly.</l>
<l n="tr">For Cycnus lov'd unhappy Phaeton,</l>
<l n="tr">And sung his loss in poplar groves, alone,</l>
<l n="tr">Beneath the sister shades, to soothe his grief.</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'n heard his song, and hasten'd his relief,</l>
<l n="tr">And chang'd to snowy plumes his hoary hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And wing'd his flight, to chant aloft in air.</l>
<l n="tr">His son Cupavo brush'd the briny flood:</l>
<l n="tr">Upon his stern a brawny Centaur stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Who heav'd a rock, and, threat'ning still to throw,</l>
<l n="tr">With lifted hands alarm'd the seas below:</l>
<l n="tr">They seem'd to fear the formidable sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And roll'd their billows on, to speed his flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="198" unit="card"/>Ocnus was next, who led his native train</l>
<l n="tr">Of hardy warriors thro' the wat'ry plain:</l>
<l n="tr">The son of Manto by the Tuscan stream,</l>
<l n="tr">From whence the Mantuan town derives the name—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">An ancient city, but of mix'd descent:</l>
<l n="tr">Three sev'ral tribes compose the government;</l>
<l n="tr">Four towns are under each; but all obey</l>
<l n="tr">The Mantuan laws, and own the Tuscan sway.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hate to Mezentius arm'd five hundred more,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Mincius from his sire Benacus bore:</l>
<l n="tr">Mincius, with wreaths of reeds his forehead cover'd o'er.</l>
<l n="tr">These grave Auletes leads: a hundred sweep</l>
<l n="tr">With stretching oars at once the glassy deep.</l>
<l n="tr">Him and his martial train the Triton bears;</l>
<l n="tr">High on his poop the sea-green god appears:</l>
<l n="tr">Frowning he seems his crooked shell to sound,</l>
<l n="tr">And at the blast the billows dance around.</l>
<l n="tr">A hairy man above the waist he shows;</l>
<l n="tr">A porpoise tail beneath his belly grows;</l>
<l n="tr">And ends a fish: his breast the waves divides,</l>
<l n="tr">And froth and foam augment the murm'ring tides.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Full thirty ships transport the chosen train</l>
<l n="tr">For <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s relief, and scour the briny main.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="215" unit="card"/>Now was the world forsaken by the sun,</l>
<l n="tr">And Phoebe half her nightly race had run.</l>
<l n="tr">The careful chief, who never clos'd his eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Himself the rudder holds, the sails supplies.</l>
<l n="tr">A choir of Nereids meet him on the flood,</l>
<l n="tr">Once his own galleys, hewn from Ida's wood;</l>
<l n="tr">But now, as many nymphs, the sea they sweep,</l>
<l n="tr">As rode, before, tall vessels on the deep.</l>
<l n="tr">They know him from afar; and in a ring</l>
<l n="tr">Inclose the ship that bore the Trojan king.</l>
<l n="tr">Cymodoce, whose voice excell'd the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Above the waves advanc'd her snowy breast;</l>
<l n="tr">Her right hand stops the stern; her left divides</l>
<l n="tr">The curling ocean, and corrects the tides.</l>
<l n="tr">She spoke for all the choir, and thus began</l>
<l n="tr">With pleasing words to warn  th'  unknowing man:</l>
<l n="tr">“Sleeps our lov'd lord? O goddess-born, awake!</l>
<l n="tr">Spread ev'ry sail, pursue your wat'ry track,</l>
<l n="tr">And haste your course. Your navy once were we,</l>
<l n="tr">From Ida's height descending to the sea;</l>
<l n="tr">Till Turnus, as at anchor fix'd we stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Presum'd to violate our holy wood.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, loos'd from shore, we fled his fires profane</l>
<l n="tr">(Unwillingly we broke our master's chain),</l>
<l n="tr">And since have sought you thro' the Tuscan main.</l>
<l n="tr">The mighty Mother chang'd our forms to these,</l>
<l n="tr">And gave us life immortal in the seas.</l>
<l n="tr">But young Ascanius, in his camp distress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">By your insulting foes is hardly press'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Arcadian horsemen, and Etrurian host,</l>
<l n="tr">Advance in order on the Latian coast:</l>
<l n="tr">To cut their way the Daunian chief designs,</l>
<l n="tr">Before their troops can reach the Trojan lines.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, when the rosy morn restores the light,</l>
<l n="tr">First arm thy soldiers for  th'  ensuing fight:</l>
<l n="tr">Thyself the fated sword of Vulcan wield,</l>
<l n="tr">And bear aloft  th'  impenetrable shield.</l>
<l n="tr">To-morrow's sun, unless my skill be vain,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall see huge heaps of foes in battle slain.”</l>
<l n="tr">Parting, she spoke; and with immortal force</l>
<l n="tr">Push'd on the vessel in her wat'ry course;</l>
<l n="tr">For well she knew the way. Impell'd behind,</l>
<l n="tr">The ship flew forward, and outstripp'd the wind.</l>
<l n="tr">The rest make up. Unknowing of the cause,</l>
<l n="tr">The chief admires their speed, and happy omens draws.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus he pray'd, and fix'd on heav'n his eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">“Hear thou, great Mother of the deities.</l>
<l n="tr">With turrets crown'd! (on Ida's holy hill</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce tigers, rein'd and curb'd, obey thy will.)</l>
<l n="tr">Firm thy own omens; lead us on to fight;</l>
<l n="tr">And let thy Phrygians conquer in thy right.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He said no more. And now renewing day</l>
<l n="tr">Had chas'd the shadows of the night away.</l>
<l n="tr">He charg'd the soldiers, with preventing care,</l>
<l n="tr">Their flags to follow, and their arms prepare;</l>
<l n="tr">Warn'd of  th'  ensuing fight, and bade 'em hope the war.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="260" unit="card"/>Now, from his lofty poop, he view'd below</l>
<l n="tr">His camp incompass'd, and  th'  inclosing foe.</l>
<l n="tr">His blazing shield, imbrac'd, he held on high;</l>
<l n="tr">The camp receive the sign, and with loud shouts reply.</l>
<l n="tr">Hope arms their courage: from their tow'rs they throw</l>
<l n="tr">Their darts with double force, and drive the foe.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, at the signal giv'n, the cranes arise</l>
<l n="tr">Before the stormy south, and blacken all the skies.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>King Turnus wonder'd at the fight renew'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Till, looking back, the Trojan fleet he view'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The seas with swelling canvas cover'd o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">And the swift ships descending on the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">The Latians saw from far, with dazzled eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">The radiant crest that seem'd in flames to rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And dart diffusive fires around the field,</l>
<l n="tr">And the keen glitt'ring the golden shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus threat'ning comets, when by night they rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Shoot sanguine streams, and sadden all the skies:</l>
<l n="tr">So Sirius, flashing forth sinister lights,</l>
<l n="tr">Pale humankind with plagues and with dry famine fright:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="276" unit="card"/>Yet Turnus with undaunted mind is bent</l>
<l n="tr">To man the shores, and hinder their descent,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus awakes the courage of his friends:</l>
<l n="tr">“What you so long have wish'd, kind Fortune sends;</l>
<l n="tr">In ardent arms to meet  th'  invading foe:</l>
<l n="tr">You find, and find him at advantage now.</l>
<l n="tr">Yours is the day: you need but only dare;</l>
<l n="tr">Your swords will make you masters of the war.</l>
<l n="tr">Your sires, your sons, your houses, and your lands,</l>
<l n="tr">And dearest wifes, are all within your hands.</l>
<l n="tr">Be mindful of the race from whence you came,</l>
<l n="tr">And emulate in arms your fathers' fame.</l>
<l n="tr">Now take the time, while stagg'ring yet they stand</l>
<l n="tr">With feet unfirm, and prepossess the strand:</l>
<l n="tr">Fortune befriends the bold.” Nor more he said,</l>
<l n="tr">But balanc'd whom to leave, and whom to lead;</l>
<l n="tr">Then these elects, the landing to prevent;</l>
<l n="tr">And those he leaves, to keep the city pent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="287" unit="card"/>Meantime the Trojan sends his troops ashore:</l>
<l n="tr">Some are by boats expos'd, by bridges more.</l>
<l n="tr">With lab'ring oars they bear along the strand,</l>
<l n="tr">Where the tide languishes, and leap aland.</l>
<l n="tr">Tarchon observes the coast with careful eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And, where no ford he finds, no water fries,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor billows with unequal murmurs roar,</l>
<l n="tr">But smoothly slide along, and swell the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">That course he steer'd, and thus he gave command:</l>
<l n="tr">“Here ply your oars, and at all hazard land:</l>
<l n="tr">Force on the vessel, that her keel may wound</l>
<l n="tr">This hated soil, and furrow hostile ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Let me securely land—I ask no more;</l>
<l n="tr">Then sink my ships, or shatter on the shore.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This fiery speech inflames his fearful friends:</l>
<l n="tr">They tug at ev'ry oar, and ev'ry stretcher bends;</l>
<l n="tr">They run their ships aground; the vessels knock,</l>
<l n="tr">(Thus forc'd ashore,) and tremble with the shock.</l>
<l n="tr">Tarchon's alone was lost, that stranded stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Stuck on a bank, and beaten by the flood:</l>
<l n="tr">She breaks her back; the loosen'd sides give way,</l>
<l n="tr">And plunge the Tuscan soldiers in the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Their broken oars and floating planks withstand</l>
<l n="tr">Their passage, while they labor to the land,</l>
<l n="tr">And ebbing tides bear back upon  th'  uncertain sand.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="308" unit="card"/>Now Turnus leads his troops without delay,</l>
<l n="tr">Advancing to the margin of the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">The trumpets sound: Aeneas first assail'd</l>
<l n="tr">The clowns new-rais'd and raw, and soon prevail'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Great Theron fell, an omen of the fight;</l>
<l n="tr">Great Theron, large of limbs, of giant height.</l>
<l n="tr">He first in open field defied the prince:</l>
<l n="tr">But armor scal'd with gold was no defense</l>
<l n="tr">Against the fated sword, which open'd wide</l>
<l n="tr">His plated shield, and pierc'd his naked side.</l>
<l n="tr">Next, Lichas fell, who, not like others born,</l>
<l n="tr">Was from his wretched mother ripp'd and torn;</l>
<l n="tr">Sacred, O Phoebus, from his birth to thee;</l>
<l n="tr">For his beginning life from biting steel was free.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from him was Gyas laid along,</l>
<l n="tr">Of monstrous bulk; with Cisseus fierce and strong:</l>
<l n="tr">Vain bulk and strength! for, when the chief assail'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor valor nor Herculean arms avail'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor their fam'd father, wont in war to go</l>
<l n="tr">With great Alcides, while he toil'd below.</l>
<l n="tr">The noisy Pharos next receiv'd his death:</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas writh'd his dart, and stopp'd his bawling breath.</l>
<l n="tr">Then wretched Cydon had receiv'd his doom,</l>
<l n="tr">Who courted Clytius in his beardless bloom,</l>
<l n="tr">And sought with lust obscene polluted joys:</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan sword had curd his love of boys,</l>
<l n="tr">Had not his sev'n bold brethren stopp'd the course</l>
<l n="tr">Of the fierce champions, with united force.</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n darts were thrown at once; and some rebound</l>
<l n="tr">From his bright shield, some on his helmet sound:</l>
<l n="tr">The rest had reach'd him; but his mother's care</l>
<l n="tr">Prevented those, and turn'd aside in air.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The prince then call'd Achates, to supply</l>
<l n="tr">The spears that knew the way to victory—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">“Those fatal weapons, which, inur'd to blood,</l>
<l n="tr">In Grecian bodies under <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> stood:</l>
<l n="tr">Not one of those my hand shall toss in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Against our foes, on this contended plain.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; then seiz'd a mighty spear, and threw;</l>
<l n="tr">Which, wing'd with fate, thro' Maeon's buckler flew,</l>
<l n="tr">Pierc'd all the brazen plates, and reach'd his heart:</l>
<l n="tr">He stagger'd with intolerable smart.</l>
<l n="tr">Alcanor saw; and reach'd, but reach'd in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">His helping hand, his brother to sustain.</l>
<l n="tr">A second spear, which kept the former course,</l>
<l n="tr">From the same hand, and sent with equal force,</l>
<l n="tr">His right arm pierc'd, and holding on, bereft</l>
<l n="tr">His use of both, and pinion'd down his left.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Numitor from his dead brother drew</l>
<l n="tr">Th' ill-omen'd spear, and at the Trojan threw:</l>
<l n="tr">Preventing fate directs the lance awry,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, glancing, only mark'd Achates' thigh.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="345" unit="card"/>In pride of youth the Sabine Clausus came,</l>
<l n="tr">And, from afar, at Dryops took his aim.</l>
<l n="tr">The spear flew hissing thro' the middle space,</l>
<l n="tr">And pierc'd his throat, directed at his face;</l>
<l n="tr">It stopp'd at once the passage of his wind,</l>
<l n="tr">And the free soul to flitting air resign'd:</l>
<l n="tr">His forehead was the first that struck the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Lifeblood and life rush'd mingled thro' the wound.</l>
<l n="tr">He slew three brothers of the Borean race,</l>
<l n="tr">And three, whom Ismarus, their native place,</l>
<l n="tr">Had sent to war, but all the sons of <placeName key="tgn,7002756" authname="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">Halesus, next, the bold Aurunci leads:</l>
<l n="tr">The son of <persName>Neptune</persName> to his aid succeeds,</l>
<l n="tr">Conspicuous on his horse. On either hand,</l>
<l n="tr">These fight to keep, and those to win, the land.</l>
<l n="tr">With mutual blood  th'  Ausonian soil is dyed,</l>
<l n="tr">While on its borders each their claim decide.</l>
<l n="tr">As wintry winds, contending in the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">With equal force of lungs their titles try:</l>
<l n="tr">They rage, they roar; the doubtful rack of heav'n</l>
<l n="tr">Stands without motion, and the tide undriv'n:</l>
<l n="tr">Each bent to conquer, neither side to yield,</l>
<l n="tr">They long suspend the fortune of the field.</l>
<l n="tr">Both armies thus perform what courage can;</l>
<l n="tr">Foot set to foot, and mingled man to man.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="362" unit="card"/>But, in another part,  th'  Arcadian horse</l>
<l n="tr">With ill success ingage the Latin force:</l>
<l n="tr">For, where  th'  impetuous torrent, rushing down,</l>
<l n="tr">Huge craggy stones and rooted trees had thrown,</l>
<l n="tr">They left their coursers, and, unus'd to fight</l>
<l n="tr">On foot, were scatter'd in a shameful flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Pallas</persName>, who with disdain and grief had view'd</l>
<l n="tr">His foes pursuing, and his friends pursued,</l>
<l n="tr">Us'd threat'nings mix'd with pray'rs, his last resource,</l>
<l n="tr">With these to move their minds, with those to fire their force</l>
<l n="tr">“Which way, companions? whether would you run?</l>
<l n="tr">By you yourselves, and mighty battles won,</l>
<l n="tr">By my great sire, by his establish'd name,</l>
<l n="tr">And early promise of my future fame;</l>
<l n="tr">By my youth, emulous of equal right</l>
<l n="tr">To share his honors—shun ignoble flight!</l>
<l n="tr">Trust not your feet: your hands must hew way</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' yon black body, and that thick array:</l>
<l n="tr">'T is thro' that forward path that we must come;</l>
<l n="tr">There lies our way, and that our passage home.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor pow'rs above, nor destinies below</l>
<l n="tr">Oppress our arms: with equal strength we go,</l>
<l n="tr">With mortal hands to meet a mortal foe.</l>
<l n="tr">See on what foot we stand: a scanty shore,</l>
<l n="tr">The sea behind, our enemies before;</l>
<l n="tr">No passage left, unless we swim the main;</l>
<l n="tr">Or, forcing these, the Trojan trenches gain.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, he strode with eager haste along,</l>
<l n="tr">And bore amidst the thickest of the throng.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="380" unit="card"/>Lagus, the first he met, with fate to foe,</l>
<l n="tr">Had heav'd a stone of mighty weight, to throw:</l>
<l n="tr">Stooping, the spear descended on his chine,</l>
<l n="tr">Just where the bone distinguished either loin:</l>
<l n="tr">It stuck so fast, so deeply buried lay,</l>
<l n="tr">That scarce the victor forc'd the steel away.</l>
<l n="tr">Hisbon came on: but, while he mov'd too slow</l>
<l n="tr">To wish'd revenge, the prince prevents his blow;</l>
<l n="tr">For, warding his at once, at once he press'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And plung'd the fatal weapon in his breast.</l>
<l n="tr">Then lewd Anchemolus he laid in dust,</l>
<l n="tr">Who stain'd his stepdam's bed with impious lust.</l>
<l n="tr">And, after him, the Daucian twins were slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Laris and Thymbrus, on the Latian plain;</l>
<l n="tr">So wondrous like in feature, shape, and size,</l>
<l n="tr">As caus'd an error in their parents' eyes—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Grateful mistake! but soon the sword decides</l>
<l n="tr">The nice distinction, and their fate divides:</l>
<l n="tr">For Thymbrus' head was lopp'd; and Laris' hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Dismember'd, sought its owner on the strand:</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling fingers yet the fauchion strain,</l>
<l n="tr">And threaten still  th'  intended stroke in vain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, to renew the charge,  th'  Arcadians came:</l>
<l n="tr">Sight of such acts, and sense of honest shame,</l>
<l n="tr">And grief, with anger mix'd, their minds inflame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="399" unit="card"/>Then, with a casual blow was Rhoeteus slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Who chanc'd, as Pallas threw, to cross the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">The flying spear was after Ilus sent;</l>
<l n="tr">But Rhoeteus happen'd on a death unmeant:</l>
<l n="tr">From Teuthras and from Tyres while he fled,</l>
<l n="tr">The lance, athwart his body, laid him dead:</l>
<l n="tr">Roll'd from his chariot with a mortal wound,</l>
<l n="tr">And intercepted fate, he spurn'd the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">As when, in summer, welcome winds arise,</l>
<l n="tr">The watchful shepherd to the forest flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And fires the midmost plants; contagion spreads,</l>
<l n="tr">And catching flames infect the neighb'ring heads;</l>
<l n="tr">Around the forest flies the furious blast,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the leafy nation sinks at last,</l>
<l n="tr">And <persName>Vulcan</persName> rides in triumph o'er the waste;</l>
<l n="tr">The pastor, pleas'd with his dire victory,</l>
<l n="tr">Beholds the satiate flames in sheets ascend the sky:</l>
<l n="tr">So <persName>Pallas</persName>' troops their scatter'd strength unite,</l>
<l n="tr">And, pouring on their foes, their prince delight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Halesus came, fierce with desire of blood;</l>
<l n="tr">But first collected in his arms he stood:</l>
<l n="tr">Advancing then, he plied the spear so well,</l>
<l n="tr">Ladon, Demodocus, and Pheres fell.</l>
<l n="tr">Around his head he toss'd his glitt'ring brand,</l>
<l n="tr">And from Strymonius hew'd his better hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Held up to guard his throat; then hurl'd a stone</l>
<l n="tr">At Thoas' ample front, and pierc'd the bone:</l>
<l n="tr">It struck beneath the space of either eye;</l>
<l n="tr">And blood, and mingled brains, together fly.</l>
<l n="tr">Deep skill'd in future fates, Halesus' sire</l>
<l n="tr">Did with the youth to lonely groves retire:</l>
<l n="tr">But, when the father's mortal race was run,</l>
<l n="tr">Dire destiny laid hold upon the son,</l>
<l n="tr">And haul'd him to the war, to find, beneath</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Evandrian spear, a memorable death.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Pallas</persName>  th'  encounter seeks, but, ere he throws,</l>
<l n="tr">To Tuscan Tiber thus address'd his vows:</l>
<l n="tr">“O sacred stream, direct my flying dart,</l>
<l n="tr">And give to pass the proud Halesus' heart!</l>
<l n="tr">His arms and spoils thy holy oak shall bear.”</l>
<l n="tr">Pleas'd with the bribe, the god receiv'd his pray'r:</l>
<l n="tr">For, while his shield protects a friend distress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The dart came driving on, and pierc'd his breast.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="426" unit="card"/>But Lausus, no small portion of the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Permits not panic fear to reign too far,</l>
<l n="tr">Caus'd by the death of so renown'd a knight;</l>
<l n="tr">But by his own example cheers the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Abas first he slew; Abas, the stay</l>
<l n="tr">Of Trojan hopes, and hindrance of the day.</l>
<l n="tr">The Phrygian troops escap'd the Greeks in vain:</l>
<l n="tr">They, and their mix'd allies, now load the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">To the rude shock of war both armies came;</l>
<l n="tr">Their leaders equal, and their strength the same.</l>
<l n="tr">The rear so press'd the front, they could not wield</l>
<l n="tr">Their angry weapons, to dispute the field.</l>
<l n="tr">Here <persName>Pallas</persName> urges on, and Lausus there:</l>
<l n="tr">Of equal youth and beauty both appear,</l>
<l n="tr">But both by fate forbid to breathe their native air.</l>
<l n="tr">Their congress in the field great Jove withstands:</l>
<l n="tr">Both doom'd to fall, but fall by greater hands.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="439" unit="card"/>Meantime Juturna warns the Daunian chief</l>
<l n="tr">Of Lausus' danger, urging swift relief.</l>
<l n="tr">With his driv'n chariot he divides the crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, making to his friends, thus calls aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“Let none presume his needless aid to join;</l>
<l n="tr">Retire, and clear the field; the fight is mine:</l>
<l n="tr">To this right hand is <persName>Pallas</persName> only due;</l>
<l n="tr">O were his father here, my just revenge to view!”</l>
<l n="tr">From the forbidden space his men retir'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Pallas</persName> their awe, and his stern words, admir'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Survey'd him o'er and o'er with wond'ring sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Struck with his haughty mien, and tow'ring height.</l>
<l n="tr">Then to the king: “Your empty vaunts forbear;</l>
<l n="tr">Success I hope, and fate I cannot fear;</l>
<l n="tr">Alive or dead, I shall deserve a name;</l>
<l n="tr">Jove is impartial, and to both the same.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and to the void advanc'd his pace:</l>
<l n="tr">Pale horror sate on each Arcadian face.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Turnus, from his chariot leaping light,</l>
<l n="tr">Address'd himself on foot to single fight.</l>
<l n="tr">And, as a lion—when he spies from far</l>
<l n="tr">A bull that seems to meditate the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Bending his neck, and spurning back the sand—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Runs roaring downward from his hilly stand:</l>
<l n="tr">Imagine eager Turnus not more slow,</l>
<l n="tr">To rush from high on his unequal foe.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Young <persName>Pallas</persName>, when he saw the chief advance</l>
<l n="tr">Within due distance of his flying lance,</l>
<l n="tr">Prepares to charge him first, resolv'd to try</l>
<l n="tr">If fortune would his want of force supply;</l>
<l n="tr">And thus to Heav'n and <persName>Hercules</persName> address'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“Alcides, once on earth <persName>Evander</persName>'s guest,</l>
<l n="tr">His son adjures you by those holy rites,</l>
<l n="tr">That hospitable board, those genial nights;</l>
<l n="tr">Assist my great attempt to gain this prize,</l>
<l n="tr">And let proud Turnus view, with dying eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">His ravish'd spoils.” 'T was heard, the vain request;</l>
<l n="tr">Alcides mourn'd, and stifled sighs within his breast.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Jove, to soothe his sorrow, thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Short bounds of life are set to mortal man.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is virtue's work alone to stretch the narrow span.</l>
<l n="tr">So many sons of gods, in bloody fight,</l>
<l n="tr">Around the walls of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, have lost the light:</l>
<l n="tr">My own Sarpedon fell beneath his foe;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor I, his mighty sire, could ward the blow.</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n Turnus shortly shall resign his breath,</l>
<l n="tr">And stands already on the verge of death.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, the god permits the fatal fight,</l>
<l n="tr">But from the Latian fields averts his sight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now with full force his spear young <persName>Pallas</persName> threw,</l>
<l n="tr">And, having thrown, his shining fauchion drew</l>
<l n="tr">The steel just graz'd along the shoulder joint,</l>
<l n="tr">And mark'd it slightly with the glancing point.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="479" unit="card"/>Fierce Turnus first to nearer distance drew,</l>
<l n="tr">And pois'd his pointed spear, before he threw:</l>
<l n="tr">Then, as the winged weapon whizz'd along,</l>
<l n="tr">“See now,” said he, “whose arm is better strung.”</l>
<l n="tr">The spear kept on the fatal course, unstay'd</l>
<l n="tr">By plates of ir'n, which o'er the shield were laid:</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' folded brass and tough bull hides it pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">His corslet pierc'd, and reach'd his heart at last.</l>
<l n="tr">In vain the youth tugs at the broken wood;</l>
<l n="tr">The soul comes issuing with the vital blood:</l>
<l n="tr">He falls; his arms upon his body sound;</l>
<l n="tr">And with his bloody teeth he bites the ground.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Turnus bestrode the corpse: “Arcadians, hear,”</l>
<l n="tr">Said he; “my message to your master bear:</l>
<l n="tr">Such as the sire deserv'd, the son I send;</l>
<l n="tr">It costs him dear to be the Phrygians' friend.</l>
<l n="tr">The lifeless body, tell him, I bestow,</l>
<l n="tr">Unask'd, to rest his wand'ring ghost below.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and trampled down with all the force</l>
<l n="tr">Of his left foot, and spurn'd the wretched corse;</l>
<l n="tr">Then snatch'd the shining belt, with gold inlaid;</l>
<l n="tr">The belt Eurytion's artful hands had made,</l>
<l n="tr">Where fifty fatal brides, express'd to sight,</l>
<l n="tr">All in the compass of one mournful night,</l>
<l n="tr">Depriv'd their bridegrooms of returning light.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In an ill hour insulting Turnus tore</l>
<l n="tr">Those golden spoils, and in a worse he wore.</l>
<l n="tr">O mortals, blind in fate, who never know</l>
<l n="tr">To bear high fortune, or endure the low!</l>
<l n="tr">The time shall come, when Turnus, but in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall wish untouch'd the trophies of the slain;</l>
<l n="tr">Shall wish the fatal belt were far away,</l>
<l n="tr">And curse the dire remembrance of the day.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The sad Arcadians, from  th'  unhappy field,</l>
<l n="tr">Bear back the breathless body on a shield.</l>
<l n="tr">O grace and grief of war! at once restor'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With praises, to thy sire, at once deplor'd!</l>
<l n="tr">One day first sent thee to the fighting field,</l>
<l n="tr">Beheld whole heaps of foes in battle kill'd;</l>
<l n="tr">One day beheld thee dead, and borne upon thy shield.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="510" unit="card"/>This dismal news, not from uncertain fame,</l>
<l n="tr">But sad spectators, to the hero came:</l>
<l n="tr">His friends upon the brink of ruin stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Unless reliev'd by his victorious hand.</l>
<l n="tr">He whirls his sword around, without delay,</l>
<l n="tr">And hews thro' adverse foes an ample way,</l>
<l n="tr">To find fierce Turnus, of his conquest proud:</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Evander</persName>, <persName>Pallas</persName>, all that friendship ow'd</l>
<l n="tr">To large deserts, are present to his eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">His plighted hand, and hospitable ties.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Four sons of Sulmo, four whom Ufens bred,</l>
<l n="tr">He took in fight, and living victims led,</l>
<l n="tr">To please the ghost of <persName>Pallas</persName>, and expire,</l>
<l n="tr">In sacrifice, before his fun'ral fire.</l>
<l n="tr">At Magus next he threw: he stoop'd below</l>
<l n="tr">The flying spear, and shunn'd the promis'd blow;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, creeping, clasp'd the hero's knees, and pray'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“By young Iulus, by thy father's shade,</l>
<l n="tr">O spare my life, and send me back to see</l>
<l n="tr">My longing sire, and tender progeny!</l>
<l n="tr">A lofty house I have, and wealth untold,</l>
<l n="tr">In silver ingots, and in bars of gold:</l>
<l n="tr">All these, and sums besides, which see no day,</l>
<l n="tr">The ransom of this one poor life shall pay.</l>
<l n="tr">If I survive, will <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> the less prevail?</l>
<l n="tr">A single soul's too light to turn the scale.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said. The hero sternly thus replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“Thy bars and ingots, and the sums beside,</l>
<l n="tr">Leave for thy children's lot. Thy Turnus broke</l>
<l n="tr">All rules of war by one relentless stroke,</l>
<l n="tr">When <persName>Pallas</persName> fell: so deems, nor deems alone</l>
<l n="tr">My father's shadow, but my living son.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, of kind remorse bereft,</l>
<l n="tr">He seiz'd his helm, and dragg'd him with his left;</l>
<l n="tr">Then with his right hand, while his neck he wreath'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Up to the hilts his shining fauchion sheath'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Apollo's priest, Emonides, was near;</l>
<l n="tr">His holy fillets on his front appear;</l>
<l n="tr">Glitt'ring in arms, he shone amidst the crowd;</l>
<l n="tr">Much of his god, more of his purple, proud.</l>
<l n="tr">Him the fierce Trojan follow'd thro' the field:</l>
<l n="tr">The holy coward fell; and, forc'd to yield,</l>
<l n="tr">The prince stood o'er the priest, and, at one blow,</l>
<l n="tr">Sent him an off'ring to the shades below.</l>
<l n="tr">His arms Seresthus on his shoulders bears,</l>
<l n="tr">Design'd a trophy to the God of Wars.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="543" unit="card"/>Vulcanian Caeculus renews the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">And Umbro, born upon the mountains' height.</l>
<l n="tr">The champion cheers his troops T' encounter those,</l>
<l n="tr">And seeks revenge himself on other foes.</l>
<l n="tr">At <persName>Anxur</persName>'s shield he drove; and, at the blow,</l>
<l n="tr">Both shield and arm to ground together go.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Anxur</persName> had boasted much of magic charms,</l>
<l n="tr">And thought he wore impenetrable arms,</l>
<l n="tr">So made by mutter'd spells; and, from the spheres,</l>
<l n="tr">Had life secur'd, in vain, for length of years.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Tarquitus the field triumph trod;</l>
<l n="tr">A nymph his mother, his sire a god.</l>
<l n="tr">Exulting in bright arms, he braves the prince:</l>
<l n="tr">With his protended lance he makes defense;</l>
<l n="tr">Bears back his feeble foe; then, pressing on,</l>
<l n="tr">Arrests his better hand, and drags him down;</l>
<l n="tr">Stands o'er the prostrate wretch, and, as he lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Vain tales inventing, and prepar'd to pray,</l>
<l n="tr">Mows off his head: the trunk a moment stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Then sunk, and roll'd along the sand in blood.</l>
<l n="tr">The vengeful victor thus upbraids the slain:</l>
<l n="tr">“Lie there, proud man, unpitied, on the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Lie there, inglorious, and without a tomb,</l>
<l n="tr">Far from thy mother and thy native home,</l>
<l n="tr">Exposed to savage beasts, and birds of prey,</l>
<l n="tr">Or thrown for food to monsters of the sea.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On Lycas and Antaeus next he ran,</l>
<l n="tr">Two chiefs of Turnus, and who led his van.</l>
<l n="tr">They fled for fear; with these, he chas'd along</l>
<l n="tr">Camers the yellow-lock'd, and Numa strong;</l>
<l n="tr">Both great in arms, and both were fair and young.</l>
<l n="tr">Camers was son to Volscens lately slain,</l>
<l n="tr">In wealth surpassing all the Latian train,</l>
<l n="tr">And in Amycla fix'd his silent easy reign.</l>
<l n="tr">And, as Aegaeon, when with heav'n he strove,</l>
<l n="tr">Stood opposite in arms to mighty Jove;</l>
<l n="tr">Mov'd all his hundred hands, provok'd the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Defied the forky lightning from afar;</l>
<l n="tr">At fifty mouths his flaming breath expires,</l>
<l n="tr">And flash for flash returns, and fires for fires;</l>
<l n="tr">In his right hand as many swords he wields,</l>
<l n="tr">And takes the thunder on as many shields:</l>
<l n="tr">With strength like his, the Trojan hero stood;</l>
<l n="tr">And soon the fields with falling corps were strow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">When once his fauchion found the taste of blood.</l>
<l n="tr">With fury scarce to be conceiv'd, he flew</l>
<l n="tr">Against Niphaeus, whom four coursers drew.</l>
<l n="tr">They, when they see the fiery chief advance,</l>
<l n="tr">And pushing at their chests his pointed lance,</l>
<l n="tr">Wheel'd with so swift a motion, mad with fear,</l>
<l n="tr">They threw their master headlong from the chair.</l>
<l n="tr">They stare, they start, nor stop their course, before</l>
<l n="tr">They bear the bounding chariot to the shore.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="575" unit="card"/>Now Lucagus and <persName>Liger</persName> scour the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">With two white steeds; but <persName>Liger</persName> holds the reins,</l>
<l n="tr">And Lucagus the lofty seat maintains:</l>
<l n="tr">Bold brethren both. The former wav'd in air</l>
<l n="tr">His flaming sword: Aeneas couch'd his spear,</l>
<l n="tr">Unus'd to threats, and more unus'd to fear.</l>
<l n="tr">Then <persName>Liger</persName> thus: “Thy confidence is vain</l>
<l n="tr">To scape from hence, as from the Trojan plain:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor these the steeds which Diomede bestrode,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor this the chariot where Achilles rode;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor Venus' veil is here, near Neptune's shield;</l>
<l n="tr">Thy fatal hour is come, and this the field.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus <persName>Liger</persName> vainly vaunts: the Trojan</l>
<l n="tr">Return'd his answer with his flying spear.</l>
<l n="tr">As Lucagus, to lash his horses, bends,</l>
<l n="tr">Prone to the wheels, and his left foot protends,</l>
<l n="tr">Prepar'd for fight; the fatal dart arrives,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' the borders of his buckler drives;</l>
<l n="tr">Pass'd thro' and pierc'd his groin: the deadly wound,</l>
<l n="tr">Cast from his chariot, roll'd him on the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Whom thus the chief upbraids with scornful spite:</l>
<l n="tr">“Blame not the slowness of your steeds in flight;</l>
<l n="tr">Vain shadows did not force their swift retreat;</l>
<l n="tr">But you yourself forsake your empty seat.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and seiz'd at once the loosen'd rein;</l>
<l n="tr">For <persName>Liger</persName> lay already on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">By the same shock: then, stretching out his hands,</l>
<l n="tr">The recreant thus his wretched life demands:</l>
<l n="tr">“Now, by thyself, O more than mortal man!</l>
<l n="tr">By her and him from whom thy breath began,</l>
<l n="tr">Who form'd thee thus divine, I beg thee, spare</l>
<l n="tr">This forfeit life, and hear thy suppliant's pray'r.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus much he spoke, and more he would have said;</l>
<l n="tr">But the stern hero turn'd aside his head,</l>
<l n="tr">And cut him short: “I hear another man;</l>
<l n="tr">You talk'd not thus before the fight began.</l>
<l n="tr">Now take your turn; and, as a brother should,</l>
<l n="tr">Attend your brother to the Stygian flood.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then thro' his breast his fatal sword he sent,</l>
<l n="tr">And the soul issued at the gaping vent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As storms the skies, and torrents tear the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Thus rag'd the prince, and scatter'd deaths around.</l>
<l n="tr">At length Ascanius and the Trojan train</l>
<l n="tr">Broke from the camp, so long besieg'd in vain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="606" unit="card"/>Meantime the King of Gods and Mortal Man</l>
<l n="tr">Held conference with his queen, and thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“My sister goddess, and well-pleasing wife,</l>
<l n="tr">Still think you Venus' aid supports the strife—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Sustains her Trojans—or themselves, alone,</l>
<l n="tr">With inborn valor force their fortune on?</l>
<l n="tr">How fierce in fight, with courage undecay'd!</l>
<l n="tr">Judge if such warriors want immortal aid.”</l>
<l n="tr">To whom the goddess with the charming eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Soft in her tone, submissively replies:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why, O my sov'reign lord, whose frown I fear,</l>
<l n="tr">And cannot, unconcern'd, your anger bear;</l>
<l n="tr">Why urge you thus my grief? when, if I still</l>
<l n="tr">(As once I was) were mistress of your will,</l>
<l n="tr">From your almighty pow'r your pleasing wife</l>
<l n="tr">Might gain the grace of length'ning Turnus' life,</l>
<l n="tr">Securely snatch him from the fatal fight,</l>
<l n="tr">And give him to his aged father's sight.</l>
<l n="tr">Now let him perish, since you hold it good,</l>
<l n="tr">And glut the Trojans with his pious blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet from our lineage he derives his name,</l>
<l n="tr">And, in the fourth degree, from god Pilumnus came;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet he devoutly pays you rites divine,</l>
<l n="tr">And offers daily incense at your shrine.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then shortly thus the sov'reign god replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“Since in my pow'r and goodness you confide,</l>
<l n="tr">If for a little space, a lengthen'd span,</l>
<l n="tr">You beg reprieve for this expiring man,</l>
<l n="tr">I grant you leave to take your Turnus hence</l>
<l n="tr">From instant fate, and can so far dispense.</l>
<l n="tr">But, if some secret meaning lies beneath,</l>
<l n="tr">To save the short-liv'd youth from destin'd death,</l>
<l n="tr">Or if a farther thought you entertain,</l>
<l n="tr">To change the fates; you feed your hopes in vain.”</l>
<l n="tr">To whom the goddess thus, with weeping eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">“And what if that request, your tongue denies,</l>
<l n="tr">Your heart should grant; and not a short reprieve,</l>
<l n="tr">But length of certain life, to Turnus give?</l>
<l n="tr">Now speedy death attends the guiltless youth,</l>
<l n="tr">If my presaging soul divines with truth;</l>
<l n="tr">Which, O! I wish, might err thro' causeless fears,</l>
<l n="tr">And you (for you have pow'r) prolong his years!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="633" unit="card"/>Thus having said, involv'd in clouds, she flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And drives a storm before her thro' the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Swift she descends, alighting on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Where the fierce foes a dubious fight maintain.</l>
<l n="tr">Of air condens'd a specter soon she made;</l>
<l n="tr">And, what Aeneas was, such seem'd the shade.</l>
<l n="tr">Adorn'd with Dardan arms, the phantom bore</l>
<l n="tr">His head aloft; a plumy crest he wore;</l>
<l n="tr">This hand appear'd a shining sword to wield,.</l>
<l n="tr">And that sustain'd an imitated shield.</l>
<l n="tr">With manly mien he stalk'd along the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor wanted voice belied, nor vaunting sound.</l>
<l n="tr">(Thus haunting ghosts appear to waking sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Or dreadful visions in our dreams by night.)</l>
<l n="tr">The specter seems the Daunian chief to dare,</l>
<l n="tr">And flourishes his empty sword in air.</l>
<l n="tr">At this, advancing, Turnus hurl'd his spear:</l>
<l n="tr">The phantom wheel'd, and seem'd to fly for fear.</l>
<l n="tr">Deluded Turnus thought the Trojan fled,</l>
<l n="tr">And with vain hopes his haughty fancy fed.</l>
<l n="tr">“Whither, O coward?” (thus he calls aloud,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor found he spoke to wind, and chas'd a cloud,)</l>
<l n="tr">“Why thus forsake your bride! Receive from me</l>
<l n="tr">The fated land you sought so long by sea.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and, brandishing at once his blade,</l>
<l n="tr">With eager pace pursued the flying shade.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="653" unit="card"/>By chance a ship was fasten'd to the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Which from old <placeName key="perseus,Clusium" authname="perseus,Clusium">Clusium</placeName> King Osinius bore:</l>
<l n="tr">The plank was ready laid for safe ascent;</l>
<l n="tr">For shelter there the trembling shadow bent,</l>
<l n="tr">And skipp't and skulk'd, and under hatches went.</l>
<l n="tr">Exulting Turnus, with regardless haste,</l>
<l n="tr">Ascends the plank, and to the galley pass'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had he reach'd the prow: <placeName key="tgn,6005278" authname="tgn,6005278">Saturnia</placeName>'s hand</l>
<l n="tr">The haulsers cuts, and shoots the ship from land.</l>
<l n="tr">With wind in poop, the vessel plows the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">And measures back with speed her former way.</l>
<l n="tr">Meantime Aeneas seeks his absent foe,</l>
<l n="tr">And sends his slaughter'd troops to shades below.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The guileful phantom now forsook the shroud,</l>
<l n="tr">And flew sublime, and vanish'd in a cloud.</l>
<l n="tr">Too late young Turnus the delusion found,</l>
<l n="tr">Far on the sea, still making from the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, thankless for a life redeem'd by shame,</l>
<l n="tr">With sense of honor stung, and forfeit fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Fearful besides of what in fight had pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">His hands and haggard eyes to heav'n he cast;</l>
<l n="tr">“O Jove!” he cried, “for what offense have</l>
<l n="tr">Deserv'd to bear this endless infamy?</l>
<l n="tr">Whence am I forc'd, and whether am I borne?</l>
<l n="tr">How, and with what reproach, shall I return?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall ever I behold the Latian plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Or see Laurentum's lofty tow'rs again?</l>
<l n="tr">What will they say of their deserting chief</l>
<l n="tr">The war was mine: I fly from their relief;</l>
<l n="tr">I led to slaughter, and in slaughter leave;</l>
<l n="tr">And ev'n from hence their dying groans receive.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, overmatch'd in fight, in heaps they lie;</l>
<l n="tr">There, scatter'd o'er the fields, ignobly fly.</l>
<l n="tr">Gape wide, O earth, and draw me down alive!</l>
<l n="tr">Or, O ye pitying winds, a wretch relieve!</l>
<l n="tr">On sands or shelves the splitting vessel drive;</l>
<l n="tr">Or set me shipwrack'd on some desart shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Where no Rutulian eyes may see me more,</l>
<l n="tr">Unknown to friends, or foes, or conscious Fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Lest she should follow, and my flight proclaim.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus Turnus rav'd, and various fates revolv'd:</l>
<l n="tr">The choice was doubtful, but the death resolv'd.</l>
<l n="tr">And now the sword, and now the sea took place,</l>
<l n="tr">That to revenge, and this to purge disgrace.</l>
<l n="tr">Sometimes he thought to swim the stormy main,</l>
<l n="tr">By stretch of arms the distant shore to gain.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice he the sword assay'd, and thrice the flood;</l>
<l n="tr">But Juno, mov'd with pity, both withstood.</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice repress'd his rage; strong gales supplied,</l>
<l n="tr">And push'd the vessel o'er the swelling tide.</l>
<l n="tr">At length she lands him on his native shores,</l>
<l n="tr">And to his father's longing arms restores.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="689" unit="card"/>Meantime, by Jove's impulse, Mezentius arm'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Succeeding Turnus, with his ardor warm'd</l>
<l n="tr">His fainting friends, reproach'd their shameful flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Repell'd the victors, and renew'd the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Against their king the Tuscan troops conspire;</l>
<l n="tr">Such is their hate, and such their fierce desire</l>
<l n="tr">Of wish'd revenge: on him, and him alone,</l>
<l n="tr">All hands employ'd, and all their darts are thrown.</l>
<l n="tr">He, like a solid rock by seas inclos'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To raging winds and roaring waves oppos'd,</l>
<l n="tr">From his proud summit looking down, disdains</l>
<l n="tr">Their empty menace, and unmov'd remains.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Beneath his feet fell haughty <placeName key="tgn,7002660" authname="tgn,7002660">Hebrus</placeName> dead,</l>
<l n="tr">Then Latagus, and Palmus as he fled.</l>
<l n="tr">At Latagus a weighty stone he flung:</l>
<l n="tr">His face was flatted, and his helmet rung.</l>
<l n="tr">But Palmus from behind receives his wound;</l>
<l n="tr">Hamstring'd he falls, and grovels on the ground:</l>
<l n="tr">His crest and armor, from his body torn,</l>
<l n="tr">Thy shoulders, Lausus, and thy head adorn.</l>
<l n="tr">Evas and Mimas, both of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, he slew.</l>
<l n="tr">Mimas his birth from fair Theano drew,</l>
<l n="tr">Born on that fatal night, when, big with fire,</l>
<l n="tr">The queen produc'd young <persName>Paris</persName> to his sire:</l>
<l n="tr">But <persName>Paris</persName> in the Phrygian fields was slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Unthinking Mimas on the Latian plain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And, as a savage boar, on mountains bred,</l>
<l n="tr">With forest mast and fatt'ning marshes fed,</l>
<l n="tr">When once he sees himself in toils inclos'd,</l>
<l n="tr">By huntsmen and their eager hounds oppos'd—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">He whets his tusks, and turns, and dares the war;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' invaders dart their jav'lins from afar:</l>
<l n="tr">All keep aloof, and safely shout around;</l>
<l n="tr">But none presumes to give a nearer wound:</l>
<l n="tr">He frets and froths, erects his bristled hide,</l>
<l n="tr">And shakes a grove of lances from his side:</l>
<l n="tr">Not otherwise the troops, with hate inspir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And just revenge against the tyrant fir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Their darts with clamor at a distance drive,</l>
<l n="tr">And only keep the languish'd war alive.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="719" unit="card"/>From Coritus came Acron to the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">Who left his spouse betroth'd, and unconsummate night.</l>
<l n="tr">Mezentius sees him thro' the squadrons ride,</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of the purple favors of his bride.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, as a hungry lion, who beholds</l>
<l n="tr">A gamesome goat, who frisks about the folds,</l>
<l n="tr">Or beamy stag, that grazes on the plain—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">He runs, he roars, he shakes his rising mane,</l>
<l n="tr">He grins, and opens wide his greedy jaws;</l>
<l n="tr">The prey lies panting underneath his paws:</l>
<l n="tr">He fills his famish'd maw; his mouth runs o'er</l>
<l n="tr">With unchew'd morsels, while he churns the gore:</l>
<l n="tr">So proud Mezentius rushes on his foes,</l>
<l n="tr">And first unhappy Acron overthrows:</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch'd at his length, he spurns the swarthy ground;</l>
<l n="tr">The lance, besmear'd with blood, lies broken in the wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Then with disdain the haughty victor view'd</l>
<l n="tr">Orodes flying, nor the wretch pursued,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thought the dastard's back deserv'd a wound,</l>
<l n="tr">But, running, gain'd  th'  advantage of the ground:</l>
<l n="tr">Then turning short, he met him face to face,</l>
<l n="tr">To give his victor the better grace.</l>
<l n="tr">Orodes falls, equal fight oppress'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Mezentius fix'd his foot upon his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">And rested lance; and thus aloud he cries:</l>
<l n="tr">“Lo! here the champion of my rebels lies!”</l>
<l n="tr">The fields around with Io Paean! ring;</l>
<l n="tr">And peals of shouts applaud the conqu'ring king.</l>
<l n="tr">At this the vanquish'd, with his dying breath,</l>
<l n="tr">Thus faintly spoke, and prophesied in death:</l>
<l n="tr">“Nor thou, proud man, unpunish'd shalt remain:</l>
<l n="tr">Like death attends thee on this fatal plain.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then, sourly smiling, thus the king replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“For what belongs to me, let Jove provide;</l>
<l n="tr">But die thou first, whatever chance ensue.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and from the wound the weapon drew.</l>
<l n="tr">A hov'ring mist came swimming o'er his sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And seal'd his eyes in everlasting night.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="747" unit="card"/>By Caedicus, Alcathous was slain;</l>
<l n="tr">Sacrator laid <persName>Hydaspes</persName> on the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Orses the strong to greater strength must yield;</l>
<l n="tr">He, with Parthenius, were by Rapo kill'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Then brave Messapus Ericetes slew,</l>
<l n="tr">Who from Lycaon's blood his lineage drew.</l>
<l n="tr">But from his headstrong horse his fate he found,</l>
<l n="tr">Who threw his master, as he made a bound:</l>
<l n="tr">The chief, alighting, stuck him to the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Then Clonius, hand to hand, on foot assails:</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan sinks, and Neptune's son prevails.</l>
<l n="tr">Agis the Lycian, stepping forth with pride,</l>
<l n="tr">To single fight the boldest foe defied;</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Tuscan Valerus by force o'ercame,</l>
<l n="tr">And not belied his mighty father's fame.</l>
<l n="tr">Salius to death the great Antronius sent:</l>
<l n="tr">But the same fate the victor underwent,</l>
<l n="tr">Slain by Nealces' hand, well-skill'd to throw</l>
<l n="tr">The flying dart, and draw the far-deceiving bow.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="755" unit="card"/>Thus equal deaths are dealt with equal chance;</l>
<l n="tr">By turns they quit their ground, by turns advance:</l>
<l n="tr">Victors and vanquish'd, in the various field,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor wholly overcome, nor wholly yield.</l>
<l n="tr">The gods from heav'n survey the fatal strife,</l>
<l n="tr">And mourn the miseries of human life.</l>
<l n="tr">Above the rest, two goddesses appear</l>
<l n="tr">Concern'd for each: here Venus, Juno there.</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the crowd, infernal Ate shakes</l>
<l n="tr">Her scourge aloft, and crest of hissing snakes.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Once more the proud Mezentius, with disdain,</l>
<l n="tr">Brandish'd his spear, and rush'd into the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Where tow'ring in the midmost rank she stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Like tall Orion stalking o'er the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">(When with his brawny breast he cuts the waves,</l>
<l n="tr">His shoulders scarce the topmost billow laves),</l>
<l n="tr">Or like a mountain ash, whose roots are spread,</l>
<l n="tr">Deep fix'd in earth; in clouds he hides his head.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="769" unit="card"/>The Trojan prince beheld him from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">And dauntless undertook the doubtful war.</l>
<l n="tr">Collected in his strength, and like a rock,</l>
<l n="tr">Pois'd on his base, Mezentius stood the shock.</l>
<l n="tr">He stood, and, measuring first with careful eyes</l>
<l n="tr">The space his spear could reach, aloud he cries:</l>
<l n="tr">“My strong right hand, and sword, assist my stroke!</l>
<l n="tr">(Those only gods Mezentius will invoke.)</l>
<l n="tr">His armor, from the Trojan pirate torn,</l>
<l n="tr">By my triumphant Lausus shall be worn.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and with his utmost force he threw</l>
<l n="tr">The massy spear, which, hissing as it flew,</l>
<l n="tr">Reach'd the celestial shield, that stopp'd the course;</l>
<l n="tr">But, glancing thence, the yet unbroken force</l>
<l n="tr">Took a new bent obliquely, and betwixt</l>
<l n="tr">The side and bowels fam'd Anthores fix'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Anthores had from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> travel'd far,</l>
<l n="tr">Alcides' friend, and brother of the war;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, tir'd with toils, fair <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> he chose,</l>
<l n="tr">And in Evander's palace sought repose.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, falling by another's wound, his eyes</l>
<l n="tr">He cast to heav'n, on <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> thinks, and dies.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The pious Trojan then his jav'lin sent;</l>
<l n="tr">The shield gave way; thro' treble plates it went</l>
<l n="tr">Of solid brass, of linen trebly roll'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And three bull hides which round the buckler fold.</l>
<l n="tr">All these it pass'd, resistless in the course,</l>
<l n="tr">Transpierc'd his thigh, and spent its dying force.</l>
<l n="tr">The gaping wound gush'd out a crimson flood.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan, glad with sight of hostile blood,</l>
<l n="tr">His faunchion drew, to closer fight address'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And with new force his fainting foe oppress'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>His father's peril Lausus view'd with grief;</l>
<l n="tr">He sigh'd, he wept, he ran to his relief.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="791" unit="card"/>And here, heroic youth, 't is here I must</l>
<l n="tr">To thy immortal memory be just,</l>
<l n="tr">And sing an act so noble and so new,</l>
<l n="tr">Posterity will scarce believe 't is true.</l>
<l n="tr">Pain'd with his wound, and useless for the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">The father sought to save himself by flight:</l>
<l n="tr">Incumber'd, slow he dragg'd the spear along,</l>
<l n="tr">Which pierc'd his thigh, and in his buckler hung.</l>
<l n="tr">The pious youth, resolv'd on death, below</l>
<l n="tr">The lifted sword springs forth to face the foe;</l>
<l n="tr">Protects his parent, and prevents the blow.</l>
<l n="tr">Shouts of applause ran ringing thro' the field,</l>
<l n="tr">To see the son the vanquish'd father shield.</l>
<l n="tr">All, fir'd with gen'rous indignation, strive,</l>
<l n="tr">And with a storm of darts to distance drive</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan chief, who, held at bay from far,</l>
<l n="tr">On his Vulcanian orb sustain'd the war.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As, when thick hail comes rattling in the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">The plowman, passenger, and lab'ring hind</l>
<l n="tr">For shelter to the neighb'ring covert fly,</l>
<l n="tr">Or hous'd, or safe in hollow caverns lie;</l>
<l n="tr">But, that o'erblown, when heav'n above 'em smiles,</l>
<l n="tr">Return to travel, and renew their toils:</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas thus, o'erwhelmed on ev'ry side,</l>
<l n="tr">The storm of darts, undaunted, did abide;</l>
<l n="tr">And thus to Lausus loud with friendly threat'ning cried:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why wilt thou rush to certain death, and rage</l>
<l n="tr">In rash attempts, beyond thy tender age,</l>
<l n="tr">Betray'd by pious love?” Nor, thus forborne,</l>
<l n="tr">The youth desists, but with insulting scorn</l>
<l n="tr">Provokes the ling'ring prince, whose patience, tir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Gave place; and all his breast with fury fir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">For now the Fates prepar'd their sharpen'd shears;</l>
<l n="tr">And lifted high the flaming sword appears,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, full descending with a frightful sway,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' shield and corslet forc'd  th'  impetuous way,</l>
<l n="tr">And buried deep in his fair bosom lay.</l>
<l n="tr">The purple streams thro' the thin armor strove,</l>
<l n="tr">And drench'd  th'  imbroider'd coat his mother wove;</l>
<l n="tr">And life at length forsook his heaving heart,</l>
<l n="tr">Loth from so sweet a mansion to depart.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But when, with blood and paleness all o'erspread,</l>
<l n="tr">The pious prince beheld young Lausus dead,</l>
<l n="tr">He griev'd; he wept; the sight an image brought</l>
<l n="tr">Of his own filial love, a sadly pleasing thought:</l>
<l n="tr">Then stretch'd his hand to hold him up, and said:</l>
<l n="tr">“Poor hapless youth! what praises can be paid</l>
<l n="tr">To love so great, to such transcendent store</l>
<l n="tr">Of early worth, and sure presage of more?</l>
<l n="tr">Accept whate'er Aeneas can afford;</l>
<l n="tr">Untouch'd thy arms, untaken be thy sword;</l>
<l n="tr">And all that pleas'd thee living, still remain</l>
<l n="tr">Inviolate, and sacred to the slain.</l>
<l n="tr">Thy body on thy parents I bestow,</l>
<l n="tr">To rest thy soul, at least, if shadows know,</l>
<l n="tr">Or have a sense of human things below.</l>
<l n="tr">There to thy fellow ghosts with glory tell:</l>
<l n="tr">‘'T was by the great Aeneas hand I fell.’”</l>
<l n="tr">With this, his distant friends he beckons near,</l>
<l n="tr">Provokes their duty, and prevents their fear:</l>
<l n="tr">Himself assists to lift him from the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">With clotted locks, and blood that well'd from out the wound.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="833" unit="card"/>Meantime, his father, now no father, stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And wash'd his wounds by <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s yellow flood:</l>
<l n="tr">Oppress'd with anguish, panting, and o'erspent,</l>
<l n="tr">His fainting limbs against an oak he leant.</l>
<l n="tr">A bough his brazen helmet did sustain;</l>
<l n="tr">His heavier arms lay scatter'd on the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">A chosen train of youth around him stand;</l>
<l n="tr">His drooping head was rested on his hand:</l>
<l n="tr">His grisly beard his pensive bosom sought;</l>
<l n="tr">And all on Lausus ran his restless thought.</l>
<l n="tr">Careful, concern'd his danger to prevent,</l>
<l n="tr">He much enquir'd, and many a message sent</l>
<l n="tr">To warn him from the field—alas! in vain!</l>
<l n="tr">Behold, his mournful followers bear him slain!</l>
<l n="tr">O'er his broad shield still gush'd the yawning wound,</l>
<l n="tr">And drew a bloody trail along the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Far off he heard their cries, far off divin'd</l>
<l n="tr">The dire event, with a foreboding mind.</l>
<l n="tr">With dust he sprinkled first his hoary head;</l>
<l n="tr">Then both his lifted hands to heav'n he spread;</l>
<l n="tr">Last, the dear corpse embracing, thus he said:</l>
<l n="tr">“What joys, alas! could this frail being give,</l>
<l n="tr">That I have been so covetous to live?</l>
<l n="tr">To see my son, and such a son, resign</l>
<l n="tr">His life, a ransom for preserving mine!</l>
<l n="tr">And am I then preserv'd, and art thou lost?</l>
<l n="tr">How much too dear has that redemption cost!</l>
<l n="tr">'T is now my bitter banishment I feel:</l>
<l n="tr">This is a wound too deep for time to heal.</l>
<l n="tr">My guilt thy growing virtues did defame;</l>
<l n="tr">My blackness blotted thy unblemish'd name.</l>
<l n="tr">Chas'd from a throne, abandon'd, and exil'd</l>
<l n="tr">For foul misdeeds, were punishments too mild:</l>
<l n="tr">I ow'd my people these, and, from their hate,</l>
<l n="tr">With less resentment could have borne my fate.</l>
<l n="tr">And yet I live, and yet sustain the sight</l>
<l n="tr">Of hated men, and of more hated light:</l>
<l n="tr">But will not long.” With that he rais'd from ground</l>
<l n="tr">His fainting limbs, that stagger'd with his wound;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, with a mind resolv'd, and unappall'd</l>
<l n="tr">With pains or perils, for his courser call'd</l>
<l n="tr">Well-mouth'd, well-manag'd, whom himself did dress</l>
<l n="tr">With daily care, and mounted with success;</l>
<l n="tr">His aid in arms, his ornament in peace.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Soothing his courage with a gentle stroke,</l>
<l n="tr">The steed seem'd sensible, while thus he spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“O Rhoebus, we have liv'd too long for me—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">If life and long were terms that could agree!</l>
<l n="tr">This day thou either shalt bring back the head</l>
<l n="tr">And bloody trophies of the Trojan dead;</l>
<l n="tr">This day thou either shalt revenge my woe,</l>
<l n="tr">For murther'd Lausus, on his cruel foe;</l>
<l n="tr">Or, if inexorable fate deny</l>
<l n="tr">Our conquest, with thy conquer'd master die:</l>
<l n="tr">For, after such a lord, rest secure,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou wilt no foreign reins, or Trojan load endure.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and straight  th'  officious courser kneels,</l>
<l n="tr">To take his wonted weight. His hands he fills</l>
<l n="tr">With pointed jav'lins; on his head he lac'd</l>
<l n="tr">His glitt'ring helm, which terribly was grac'd</l>
<l n="tr">With waving horsehair, nodding from afar;</l>
<l n="tr">Then spurr'd his thund'ring steed amidst the war.</l>
<l n="tr">Love, anguish, wrath, and grief, to madness wrought,</l>
<l n="tr">Despair, and secret shame, and conscious thought</l>
<l n="tr">Of inborn worth, his lab'ring soul oppress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Roll'd in his eyes, and rag'd within his breast.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="873" unit="card"/>Then loud he call'd Aeneas thrice by name:</l>
<l n="tr">The loud repeated voice to glad Aeneas came.</l>
<l n="tr">“Great Jove,” he said, “and the far-shooting god,</l>
<l n="tr">Inspire thy mind to make thy challenge good!”</l>
<l n="tr">He spoke no more; but hasten'd, void of fear,</l>
<l n="tr">And threaten'd with his long protended spear.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To whom Mezentius thus: “Thy vaunts are vain.</l>
<l n="tr">My Lausus lies extended on the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">He's lost! thy conquest is already won;</l>
<l n="tr">The wretched sire is murther'd in the son.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor fate I fear, but all the gods defy.</l>
<l n="tr">Forbear thy threats: my bus'ness is to die;</l>
<l n="tr">But first receive this parting legacy.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and straight a whirling dart he sent;</l>
<l n="tr">Another after, and another went.</l>
<l n="tr">Round in a spacious ring he rides the field,</l>
<l n="tr">And vainly plies  th'  impenetrable shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice rode he round; and thrice Aeneas wheel'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Turn'd as he turn'd: the golden orb withstood</l>
<l n="tr">The strokes, and bore about an iron wood.</l>
<l n="tr">Impatient of delay, and weary grown,</l>
<l n="tr">Still to defend, and to defend alone,</l>
<l n="tr">To wrench the darts which in his buckler light,</l>
<l n="tr">Urg'd and o'er-labor'd in unequal fight;</l>
<l n="tr">At length resolv'd, he throws with all his force</l>
<l n="tr">Full at the temples of the warrior horse.</l>
<l n="tr">Just where the stroke was aim'd,  th'  unerring spear</l>
<l n="tr">Made way, and stood transfix'd thro' either ear.</l>
<l n="tr">Seiz'd with unwonted pain, surpris'd with fright,</l>
<l n="tr">The wounded steed curvets, and, rais'd upright,</l>
<l n="tr">Lights on his feet before; his hoofs behind</l>
<l n="tr">Spring up in air aloft, and lash the wind.</l>
<l n="tr">Down comes the rider headlong from his height:</l>
<l n="tr">His horse came after with unwieldy weight,</l>
<l n="tr">And, flound'ring forward, pitching on his head,</l>
<l n="tr">His lord's incumber'd shoulder overlaid.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>From either host, the mingled shouts and cries</l>
<l n="tr">Of Trojans and Rutulians rend the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, hast'ning, wav'd his fatal sword</l>
<l n="tr">High o'er his head, with this reproachful word:</l>
<l n="tr">“Now; where are now thy vaunts, the fierce disdain</l>
<l n="tr">Of proud Mezentius, and the lofty strain?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Struggling, and wildly staring on the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">With scarce recover'd sight he thus replies:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why these insulting words, this waste of breath,</l>
<l n="tr">To souls undaunted, and secure of death?</l>
<l n="tr">'T is no dishonor for the brave to die,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor came I here with hope victory;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor ask I life, nor fought with that design:</l>
<l n="tr">As I had us'd my fortune, use thou thine.</l>
<l n="tr">My dying son contracted no such band;</l>
<l n="tr">The gift is hateful from his murd'rer's hand.</l>
<l n="tr">For this, this only favor let me sue,</l>
<l n="tr">If pity can to conquer'd foes be due:</l>
<l n="tr">Refuse it not; but let my body have</l>
<l n="tr">The last retreat of humankind, a grave.</l>
<l n="tr">Too well I know  th'  insulting people's hate;</l>
<l n="tr">Protect me from their vengeance after fate:</l>
<l n="tr">This refuge for my poor remains provide,</l>
<l n="tr">And lay my much-lov'd Lausus by my side.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and to the sword his throat applied.</l>
<l n="tr">The crimson stream distain'd his arms around,</l>
<l n="tr">And the disdainful soul came rushing thro' the wound.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>