<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="11" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">Scarce had the rosy Morning rais'd her head</l>
<l n="tr">Above the waves, and left her wat'ry bed;</l>
<l n="tr">The pious chief, whom double cares attend</l>
<l n="tr">For his unburied soldiers and his friend,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet first to Heav'n perform'd a victor's vows:</l>
<l n="tr">He bar'd an ancient oak of all her boughs;</l>
<l n="tr">Then on a rising ground the trunk he plac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Which with the spoils of his dead foe he grac'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The coat of arms by proud Mezentius worn,</l>
<l n="tr">Now on a naked snag in triumph borne,</l>
<l n="tr">Was hung on high, and glitter'd from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">A trophy sacred to the God of War.</l>
<l n="tr">Above his arms, fix'd on the leafless wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Appear'd his plumy crest, besmear'd with blood:</l>
<l n="tr">His brazen buckler on the left was seen;</l>
<l n="tr">Truncheons of shiver'd lances hung between;</l>
<l n="tr">And on the right was placed his corslet, bor'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And to the neck was tied his unavailing sword.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A crowd of chiefs inclose the godlike man,</l>
<l n="tr">Who thus, conspicuous in the midst, began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Our toils, my friends, are crown'd with sure success;</l>
<l n="tr">The greater part perform'd, achieve the less.</l>
<l n="tr">Now follow cheerful to the trembling town;</l>
<l n="tr">Press but an entrance, and presume it won.</l>
<l n="tr">Fear is no more, for fierce Mezentius lies,</l>
<l n="tr">As the first fruits of war, a sacrifice.</l>
<l n="tr">Turnus shall fall extended on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">And, in this omen, is already slain.</l>
<l n="tr">Prepar'd in arms, pursue your happy chance;</l>
<l n="tr">That none unwarn'd may plead his ignorance,</l>
<l n="tr">And I, at Heav'n's appointed hour, may find</l>
<l n="tr">Your warlike ensigns waving in the wind.</l>
<l n="tr">Meantime the rites and fun'ral pomps prepare,</l>
<l n="tr">Due to your dead companions of the war:</l>
<l n="tr">The last respect the living can bestow,</l>
<l n="tr">To shield their shadows from contempt below.</l>
<l n="tr">That conquer'd earth be theirs, for which they fought,</l>
<l n="tr">And which for us with their own blood they bought;</l>
<l n="tr">But first the corpse of our unhappy friend</l>
<l n="tr">To the sad city of Evander send,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, not inglorious, in his age's bloom,</l>
<l n="tr">Was hurried hence by too severe a doom.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="29" unit="card"/>Thus, weeping while he spoke, he took his way,</l>
<l n="tr">Where, new in death, lamented <persName>Pallas</persName> lay.</l>
<l n="tr">Acoetes watch'd the corpse; whose youth deserv'd</l>
<l n="tr">The father's trust; and now the son he serv'd</l>
<l n="tr">With equal faith, but less auspicious care.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' attendants of the slain his sorrow share.</l>
<l n="tr">A troop of Trojans mix'd with these appear,</l>
<l n="tr">And mourning matrons with dishevel'd hair.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon as the prince appears, they raise a cry;</l>
<l n="tr">All beat their breasts, and echoes rend the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">They rear his drooping forehead from the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">But, when Aeneas view'd the grisly wound</l>
<l n="tr">Which <persName>Pallas</persName> in his manly bosom bore,</l>
<l n="tr">And the fair flesh distain'd with purple gore;</l>
<l n="tr">First, melting into tears, the pious man</l>
<l n="tr">Deplor'd so sad a sight, then thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Unhappy youth! when Fortune gave the rest</l>
<l n="tr">Of my full wishes, she refus'd the best!</l>
<l n="tr">She came; but brought not thee along, to bless</l>
<l n="tr">My longing eyes, and share in my success:</l>
<l n="tr">She grudg'd thy safe return, the triumphs due</l>
<l n="tr">To prosp'rous valor, in the public view.</l>
<l n="tr">Not thus I promis'd, when thy father lent</l>
<l n="tr">Thy needless succor with a sad consent;</l>
<l n="tr">Embrac'd me, parting for  th'  Etrurian land,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent me to possess a large command.</l>
<l n="tr">He warn'd, and from his own experience told,</l>
<l n="tr">Our foes were warlike, disciplin'd, and bold.</l>
<l n="tr">And now perhaps, in hopes of thy return,</l>
<l n="tr">Rich odors on his loaded altars burn,</l>
<l n="tr">While we, with vain officious pomp, prepare</l>
<l n="tr">To send him back his portion of the war,</l>
<l n="tr">A bloody breathless body, which can owe</l>
<l n="tr">No farther debt, but to the pow'rs below.</l>
<l n="tr">The wretched father, ere his race is run,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall view the fun'ral honors of his son.</l>
<l n="tr">These are my triumphs of the Latian war,</l>
<l n="tr">Fruits of my plighted faith and boasted care!</l>
<l n="tr">And yet, unhappy sire, thou shalt not see</l>
<l n="tr">A son whose death disgrac'd his ancestry;</l>
<l n="tr">Thou shalt not blush, old man, however griev'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Thy Pallas no dishonest wound receiv'd.</l>
<l n="tr">He died no death to make thee wish, too late,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou hadst not liv'd to see his shameful fate:</l>
<l n="tr">But what a champion has  th'  Ausonian coast,</l>
<l n="tr">And what a friend hast thou, Ascanius, lost!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="59" unit="card"/>Thus having mourn'd, he gave the word around,</l>
<l n="tr">To raise the breathless body from the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">And chose a thousand horse, the flow'r of all</l>
<l n="tr">His warlike troops, to wait the funeral,</l>
<l n="tr">To bear him back and share <persName>Evander</persName>'s grief:</l>
<l n="tr">A well-becoming, but a weak relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Of oaken twigs they twist an easy bier,</l>
<l n="tr">Then on their shoulders the sad burden rear.</l>
<l n="tr">The body on this rural hearse is borne:</l>
<l n="tr">Strew'd leaves and funeral greens the bier adorn.</l>
<l n="tr">All pale he lies, and looks a lovely flow'r,</l>
<l n="tr">New cropp'd by virgin hands, to dress the bow'r:</l>
<l n="tr">Unfaded yet, but yet unfed below,</l>
<l n="tr">No more to mother earth or the green stern shall owe.</l>
<l n="tr">Then two fair vests, of wondrous work and cost,</l>
<l n="tr">Of purple woven, and with gold emboss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">For ornament the Trojan hero brought,</l>
<l n="tr">Which with her hands Sidonian Dido wrought.</l>
<l n="tr">One vest array'd the corpse; and one they spread</l>
<l n="tr">O'er his clos'd eyes, and wrapp'd around his head,</l>
<l n="tr">That, when the yellow hair in flame should fall,</l>
<l n="tr">The catching fire might burn the golden caul.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, the spoils of foes in battle slain,</l>
<l n="tr">When he descended on the Latian plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Arms, trappings, horses, by the hearse are led</l>
<l n="tr">In long array—th' achievements of the dead.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, pinion'd with their hands behind, appear</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unhappy captives, marching in the rear,</l>
<l n="tr">Appointed off'rings in the victor's name,</l>
<l n="tr">To sprinkle with their blood the fun'ral flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Inferior trophies by the chiefs are borne;</l>
<l n="tr">Gauntlets and helms their loaded hands adorn;</l>
<l n="tr">And fair inscriptions fix'd, and titles read</l>
<l n="tr">Of Latian leaders conquer'd by the dead.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Acoetes on his pupil's corpse attends,</l>
<l n="tr">With feeble steps, supported by his friends.</l>
<l n="tr">Pausing at ev'ry pace, in sorrow drown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt their arms he sinks upon the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Where grov'ling while he lies in deep despair,</l>
<l n="tr">He beats his breast, and rends his hoary hair.</l>
<l n="tr">The champion's chariot next is seen to roll,</l>
<l n="tr">Besmear'd with hostile blood, and honorably foul.</l>
<l n="tr">To close the pomp, Aethon, the steed of state,</l>
<l n="tr">Is led, the fun'rals of his lord to wait.</l>
<l n="tr">Stripp'd of his trappings, with a sullen pace</l>
<l n="tr">He walks; and the big tears run rolling down his face.</l>
<l n="tr">The lance of <persName>Pallas</persName>, and the crimson crest,</l>
<l n="tr">Are borne behind: the victor seiz'd the rest.</l>
<l n="tr">The march begins: the trumpets hoarsely sound;</l>
<l n="tr">The pikes and lances trail along the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while the Trojan and Arcadian horse</l>
<l n="tr">To Pallantean tow'rs direct their course,</l>
<l n="tr">In long procession rank'd, the pious chief</l>
<l n="tr">Stopp'd in the rear, and gave a vent to grief:</l>
<l n="tr">“The public care,” he said, “which war attends,</l>
<l n="tr">Diverts our present woes, at least suspends.</l>
<l n="tr">Peace with the manes of great <persName>Pallas</persName> dwell!</l>
<l n="tr">Hail, holy relics! and a last farewell!”</l>
<l n="tr">He said no more, but, inly thro' he mourn'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Restrained his tears, and to the camp return'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="100" unit="card"/>Now suppliants, from Laurentum sent, demand</l>
<l n="tr">A truce, with olive branches in their hand;</l>
<l n="tr">Obtest his clemency, and from the plain</l>
<l n="tr">Beg leave to draw the bodies of their slain.</l>
<l n="tr">They plead, that none those common rites deny</l>
<l n="tr">To conquer'd foes that in fair battle die.</l>
<l n="tr">All cause of hate was ended in their death;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor could he war with bodies void of breath.</l>
<l n="tr">A king, they hop'd, would hear a king's request,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose son he once was call'd, and once his guest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Their suit, which was too just to be denied,</l>
<l n="tr">The hero grants, and farther thus replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“O Latian princes, how severe a fate</l>
<l n="tr">In causeless quarrels has involv'd your state,</l>
<l n="tr">And arm'd against an unoffending man,</l>
<l n="tr">Who sought your friendship ere the war began!</l>
<l n="tr">You beg a truce, which I would gladly give,</l>
<l n="tr">Not only for the slain, but those who live.</l>
<l n="tr">I came not hither but by Heav'n's command,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent by fate to share the Latian land.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor wage I wars unjust: your king denied</l>
<l n="tr">My proffer'd friendship, and my promis'd bride;</l>
<l n="tr">Left me for Turnus. Turnus then should try</l>
<l n="tr">His cause in arms, to conquer or to die.</l>
<l n="tr">My right and his are in dispute: the slain</l>
<l n="tr">Fell without fault, our quarrel to maintain.</l>
<l n="tr">In equal arms let us alone contend;</l>
<l n="tr">And let him vanquish, whom his fates befriend.</l>
<l n="tr">This is the way (so tell him) to possess</l>
<l n="tr">The royal virgin, and restore the peace.</l>
<l n="tr">Bear this message back, with ample leave,</l>
<l n="tr">That your slain friends may fun'ral rites receive.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus having said—th' embassadors, amaz'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Stood mute a while, and on each other gaz'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="122" unit="card"/>Drances, their chief, who harbor'd in his breast</l>
<l n="tr">Long hate to Turnus, as his foe profess'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Broke silence first, and to the godlike man,</l>
<l n="tr">With graceful action bowing, thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Auspicious prince, in arms a mighty name,</l>
<l n="tr">But yet whose actions far transcend your fame;</l>
<l n="tr">Would I your justice or your force express,</l>
<l n="tr">Thought can but equal; and all words are less.</l>
<l n="tr">Your answer we shall thankfully relate,</l>
<l n="tr">And favors granted to the Latian state.</l>
<l n="tr">If wish'd success our labor shall attend,</l>
<l n="tr">Think peace concluded, and the king your friend:</l>
<l n="tr">Let Turnus leave the realm to your command,</l>
<l n="tr">And seek alliance in some other land:</l>
<l n="tr">Build you the city which your fates assign;</l>
<l n="tr">We shall be proud in the great work to join.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus Drances; and his words so well persuade</l>
<l n="tr">The rest impower'd, that soon a truce is made.</l>
<l n="tr">Twelve days the term allow'd: and, during those,</l>
<l n="tr">Latians and Trojans, now no longer foes,</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd in the woods, for fun'ral piles prepare</l>
<l n="tr">To fell the timber, and forget the war.</l>
<l n="tr">Loud axes thro' the groaning groves resound;</l>
<l n="tr">Oak, mountain ash, and poplar spread the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">First fall from high; and some the trunks receive</l>
<l n="tr">In loaden wains; with wedges some they cleave.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="139" unit="card"/>And now the fatal news by Fame is blown</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the short circuit of  th' Arcadian town,</l>
<l n="tr">Of <persName>Pallas</persName> slain—by Fame, which just before</l>
<l n="tr">His triumphs on distended pinions bore.</l>
<l n="tr">Rushing from out the gate, the people stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Each with a fun'ral flambeau in his hand.</l>
<l n="tr">Wildly they stare, distracted with amaze:</l>
<l n="tr">The fields are lighten'd with a fiery blaze,</l>
<l n="tr">That cast a sullen splendor on their friends,</l>
<l n="tr">The marching troop which their dead prince attends.</l>
<l n="tr">Both parties meet: they raise a doleful cry;</l>
<l n="tr">The matrons from the walls with shrieks reply,</l>
<l n="tr">And their mix'd mourning rends the vaulted sky.</l>
<l n="tr">The town is fill'd with tumult and with tears,</l>
<l n="tr">Till the loud clamors reach <persName>Evander</persName>'s ears:</l>
<l n="tr">Forgetful of his state, he runs along,</l>
<l n="tr">With a disorder'd pace, and cleaves the throng;</l>
<l n="tr">Falls on the corpse; and groaning there he lies,</l>
<l n="tr">With silent grief, that speaks but at his eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">Short sighs and sobs succeed; till sorrow breaks</l>
<l n="tr">A passage, and at once he weeps and speaks:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“O <persName>Pallas</persName>! thou hast fail'd thy plighted word,</l>
<l n="tr">To fight with caution, not to tempt the sword!</l>
<l n="tr">I warn'd thee, but in vain; for well I knew</l>
<l n="tr">What perils youthful ardor would pursue,</l>
<l n="tr">That boiling blood would carry thee too far,</l>
<l n="tr">Young as thou wert in dangers, raw to war!</l>
<l n="tr">O curst essay of arms, disastrous doom,</l>
<l n="tr">Prelude of bloody fields, and fights to come!</l>
<l n="tr">Hard elements of unauspicious war,</l>
<l n="tr">Vain vows to Heav'n, and unavailing care!</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice happy thou, dear partner of my bed,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose holy soul the stroke of Fortune fled,</l>
<l n="tr">Praescious of ills, and leaving me behind,</l>
<l n="tr">To drink the dregs of life by fate assign'd!</l>
<l n="tr">Beyond the goal of nature I have gone:</l>
<l n="tr">My <persName>Pallas</persName> late set out, but reach'd too soon.</l>
<l n="tr">If, for my league against  th'  Ausonian state,</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst their weapons I had found my fate,</l>
<l n="tr">(Deserv'd from them,) then I had been return'd</l>
<l n="tr">A breathless victor, and my son had mourn'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet will I not my Trojan friend upbraid,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor grudge  th'  alliance I so gladly made.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was not his fault, my <persName>Pallas</persName> fell so young,</l>
<l n="tr">But my own crime, for having liv'd too long.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, since the gods had destin'd him to die,</l>
<l n="tr">At least he led the way to victory:</l>
<l n="tr">First for his friends he won the fatal shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent whole herds of slaughter'd foes before;</l>
<l n="tr">A death too great, too glorious to deplore.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor will I add new honors to thy grave,</l>
<l n="tr">Content with those the Trojan hero gave:</l>
<l n="tr">That funeral pomp thy Phrygian friends design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">In which the Tuscan chiefs and army join'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Great spoils and trophies, gain'd by thee, they bear:</l>
<l n="tr">Then let thy own achievements be thy share.</l>
<l n="tr">Even thou, O Turnus, hadst a trophy stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose mighty trunk had better grac'd the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">If <persName>Pallas</persName> had arriv'd, with equal length</l>
<l n="tr">Of years, to match thy bulk with equal strength.</l>
<l n="tr">But why, unhappy man, dost thou detain</l>
<l n="tr">These troops, to view the tears thou shedd'st in vain?</l>
<l n="tr">Go, friends, this message to your lord relate:</l>
<l n="tr">Tell him, that, if I bear my bitter fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And, after <persName>Pallas</persName>' death, live ling'ring on,</l>
<l n="tr">'T is to behold his vengeance for my son.</l>
<l n="tr">I stay for Turnus, whose devoted head</l>
<l n="tr">Is owing to the living and the dead.</l>
<l n="tr">My son and I expect it from his hand;</l>
<l n="tr">'T is all that he can give, or we demand.</l>
<l n="tr">Joy is no more; but I would gladly go,</l>
<l n="tr">To greet my <persName>Pallas</persName> with such news below.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="182" unit="card"/>The morn had now dispell'd the shades of night,</l>
<l n="tr">Restoring toils, when she restor'd the light.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan king and Tuscan chief command</l>
<l n="tr">To raise the piles along the winding strand.</l>
<l n="tr">Their friends convey the dead fun'ral fires;</l>
<l n="tr">Black smold'ring smoke from the green wood expires;</l>
<l n="tr">The light of heav'n is chok'd, and the new day retires.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thrice around the kindled piles they go</l>
<l n="tr">(For ancient custom had ordain'd it so)</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice horse and foot about the fires are led;</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice, with loud laments, they hail the dead.</l>
<l n="tr">Tears, trickling down their breasts, bedew the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And drums and trumpets mix their mournful sound.</l>
<l n="tr">Amid the blaze, their pious brethren throw</l>
<l n="tr">The spoils, in battle taken from the foe:</l>
<l n="tr">Helms, bits emboss'd, and swords of shining steel;</l>
<l n="tr">One casts a target, one a chariot wheel;</l>
<l n="tr">Some to their fellows their own arms restore:</l>
<l n="tr">The fauchions which in luckless fight they bore,</l>
<l n="tr">Their bucklers pierc'd, their darts bestow'd in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">And shiver'd lances gather'd from the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Whole herds of offer'd bulls, about the fire,</l>
<l n="tr">And bristled boars, and woolly sheep expire.</l>
<l n="tr">Around the piles a careful troop attends,</l>
<l n="tr">To watch the wasting flames, and weep their burning friends;</l>
<l n="tr">Ling'ring along the shore, till dewy night</l>
<l n="tr">New decks the face of heav'n with starry light.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="203" unit="card"/>The conquer'd Latians, with like pious care,</l>
<l n="tr">Piles without number for their dead prepare.</l>
<l n="tr">Part in the places where they fell are laid;</l>
<l n="tr">And part are to the neighb'ring fields convey'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The corps of kings, and captains of renown,</l>
<l n="tr">Borne off in state, are buried in the town;</l>
<l n="tr">The rest, unhonor'd, and without a name,</l>
<l n="tr">Are cast a common heap to feed the flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Trojans and Latians vie with like desires</l>
<l n="tr">To make the field of battle shine with fires,</l>
<l n="tr">And the promiscuous blaze to heav'n aspires.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now had the morning thrice renew'd the light,</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice dispell'd the shadows of the night,</l>
<l n="tr">When those who round the wasted fires remain,</l>
<l n="tr">Perform the last sad office to the slain.</l>
<l n="tr">They rake the yet warm ashes from below;</l>
<l n="tr">These, and the bones unburn'd, in earth bestow;</l>
<l n="tr">These relics with their country rites they grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And raise a mount of turf to mark the place.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But, in the palace of the king, appears</l>
<l n="tr">A scene more solemn, and a pomp of tears.</l>
<l n="tr">Maids, matrons, widows, mix their common moans;</l>
<l n="tr">Orphans their sires, and sires lament their sons.</l>
<l n="tr">All in that universal sorrow share,</l>
<l n="tr">And curse the cause of this unhappy war:</l>
<l n="tr">A broken league, a bride unjustly sought,</l>
<l n="tr">A crown usurp'd, which with their blood is bought!</l>
<l n="tr">These are the crimes with which they load the name</l>
<l n="tr">Of Turnus, and on him alone exclaim:</l>
<l n="tr">“Let him who lords it o'er  th'  Ausonian land</l>
<l n="tr">Engage the Trojan hero hand to hand:</l>
<l n="tr">His is the gain; our lot is but to serve;</l>
<l n="tr">'T is just, the sway he seeks, he should deserve.”</l>
<l n="tr">This Drances aggravates; and adds, with spite:</l>
<l n="tr">“His foe expects, and dares him to the fight.”</l>
<l n="tr">Nor Turnus wants a party, to support</l>
<l n="tr">His cause and credit in the Latian court.</l>
<l n="tr">His former acts secure his present fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And the queen shades him with her mighty name.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="225" unit="card"/>While thus their factious minds with fury burn,</l>
<l n="tr">The legates from  th'  Aetolian prince return:</l>
<l n="tr">Sad news they bring, that, after all the cost</l>
<l n="tr">And care employ'd, their embassy is lost;</l>
<l n="tr">That Diomedes refus'd his aid in war,</l>
<l n="tr">Unmov'd with presents, and as deaf to pray'r.</l>
<l n="tr">Some new alliance must elsewhere be sought,</l>
<l n="tr">Or peace with <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> on hard conditions bought.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Latinus, sunk in sorrow, finds too late,</l>
<l n="tr">A foreign son is pointed out by fate;</l>
<l n="tr">And, till Aeneas shall <persName>Lavinia</persName> wed,</l>
<l n="tr">The wrath of Heav'n is hov'ring o'er his head.</l>
<l n="tr">The gods, he saw, espous'd the juster side,</l>
<l n="tr">When late their titles in the field were tried:</l>
<l n="tr">Witness the fresh laments, and fun'ral tears undried.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, full of anxious thought, he summons all</l>
<l n="tr">The Latian senate to the council hall.</l>
<l n="tr">The princes come, commanded by their head,</l>
<l n="tr">And crowd the paths that to the palace lead.</l>
<l n="tr">Supreme in pow'r, and reverenc'd for his years,</l>
<l n="tr">He takes the throne, and in the midst appears.</l>
<l n="tr">Majestically sad, he sits in state,</l>
<l n="tr">And bids his envoys their success relate.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When Venulus began, the murmuring sound</l>
<l n="tr">Was hush'd, and sacred silence reign'd around.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="243" unit="card"/>“We have,” said he, “perform'd your high command,</l>
<l n="tr">And pass'd with peril a long tract of land:</l>
<l n="tr">We reach'd the place desir'd; with wonder fill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian tents and rising tow'rs beheld.</l>
<l n="tr">Great Diomede has compass'd round with walls</l>
<l n="tr">The city, which Argyripa he calls,</l>
<l n="tr">From his own <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> nam'd. We touch'd, with joy,</l>
<l n="tr">The royal hand that raz'd unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">When introduc'd, our presents first we bring,</l>
<l n="tr">Then crave an instant audience from the king.</l>
<l n="tr">His leave obtain'd, our native soil we name,</l>
<l n="tr">And tell  th'  important cause for which we came.</l>
<l n="tr">Attentively he heard us, while we spoke;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, with soft accents, and a pleasing look,</l>
<l n="tr">Made this return: ‘Ausonian race, of old</l>
<l n="tr">Renown'd for peace, and for an age of gold,</l>
<l n="tr">What madness has your alter'd minds possess'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To change for war hereditary rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Solicit arms unknown, and tempt the sword,</l>
<l n="tr">A needless ill your ancestors abhorr'd?</l>
<l n="tr">We—for myself I speak, and all the name</l>
<l n="tr">Of Grecians, who to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s destruction came,</l>
<l n="tr">Omitting those who were in battle slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Or borne by rolling Simois to the main—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Not one but suffer'd, and too dearly bought</l>
<l n="tr">The prize of honor which in arms he sought;</l>
<l n="tr">Some doom'd to death, and some in exile driv'n.</l>
<l n="tr">Outcasts, abandon'd by the care of Heav'n;</l>
<l n="tr">So worn, so wretched, so despis'd a crew,</l>
<l n="tr">As ev'n old Priam might with pity view.</l>
<l n="tr">Witness the vessels by <persName>Minerva</persName> toss'd</l>
<l n="tr">In storms; the vengeful Capharean coast;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Euboean rocks! the prince, whose brother led</l>
<l n="tr">Our armies to revenge his injur'd bed,</l>
<l n="tr">In <placeName key="tgn,7016833" authname="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> lost! <persName>Ulysses</persName> with his men</l>
<l n="tr">Have seen Charybdis and the Cyclops' den.</l>
<l n="tr">Why should I name Idomeneus, in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Restor'd to scepters, and expell'd again?</l>
<l n="tr">Or young Achilles, by his rival slain?</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n he, the King of Men, the foremost name</l>
<l n="tr">Of all the Greeks, and most renown'd by fame,</l>
<l n="tr">The proud revenger of another's wife,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet by his own adult'ress lost his life;</l>
<l n="tr">Fell at his threshold; and the spoils of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">The foul polluters of his bed enjoy.</l>
<l n="tr">The gods have envied me the sweets of life,</l>
<l n="tr">My much lov'd country, and my more lov'd wife:</l>
<l n="tr">Banish'd from both, I mourn; while in the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Transform'd to birds, my lost companions fly:</l>
<l n="tr">Hov'ring about the coasts, they make their moan,</l>
<l n="tr">And cuff the cliffs with pinions not their own.</l>
<l n="tr">What squalid specters, in the dead of night,</l>
<l n="tr">Break my short sleep, and skim before my sight!</l>
<l n="tr">I might have promis'd to myself those harms,</l>
<l n="tr">Mad as I was, when I, with mortal arms,</l>
<l n="tr">Presum'd against immortal pow'rs to move,</l>
<l n="tr">And violate with wounds the Queen of Love.</l>
<l n="tr">Such arms this hand shall never more employ;</l>
<l n="tr">No hate remains with me to ruin'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">I war not with its dust; nor am I glad</l>
<l n="tr">To think of past events, or good or bad.</l>
<l n="tr">Your presents I return: whate'er you bring</l>
<l n="tr">To buy my friendship, send the Trojan king.</l>
<l n="tr">We met in fight; I know him, to my cost:</l>
<l n="tr">With what a whirling force his lance he toss'd!</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'ns! what a spring was in his arm, to throw!</l>
<l n="tr">How high he held his shield, and rose at ev'ry blow!</l>
<l n="tr">Had <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> produc'd two more his match in might,</l>
<l n="tr">They would have chang'd the fortune of the fight:</l>
<l n="tr">Th' invasion of the Greeks had been return'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Our empire wasted, and our cities burn'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The long defense the Trojan people made,</l>
<l n="tr">The war protracted, and the siege delay'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Were due to Hector's and this hero's hand:</l>
<l n="tr">Both brave alike, and equal in command;</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, not inferior in the field,</l>
<l n="tr">In pious reverence to the gods excell'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Make peace, ye Latians, and avoid with care</l>
<l n="tr">Th' impending dangers of a fatal war.’</l>
<l n="tr">He said no more; but, with this cold excuse,</l>
<l n="tr">Refus'd  th'  alliance, and advis'd a truce.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="296" unit="card"/>Thus Venulus concluded his report.</l>
<l n="tr">A jarring murmur fill'd the factious court:</l>
<l n="tr">As, when a torrent rolls with rapid force,</l>
<l n="tr">And dashes o'er the stones that stop the course,</l>
<l n="tr">The flood, constrain'd within a scanty space,</l>
<l n="tr">Roars horrible along  th'  uneasy race;</l>
<l n="tr">White foam in gath'ring eddies floats around;</l>
<l n="tr">The rocky shores rebellow to the sound.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The murmur ceas'd: then from his lofty throne</l>
<l n="tr">The king invok'd the gods, and thus begun:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="302" unit="card"/>“I wish, ye Latins, what we now debate</l>
<l n="tr">Had been resolv'd before it was too late.</l>
<l n="tr">Much better had it been for you and me,</l>
<l n="tr">Unforc'd by this our last necessity,</l>
<l n="tr">To have been earlier wise, than now to call</l>
<l n="tr">A council, when the foe surrounds the wall.</l>
<l n="tr">O citizens, we wage unequal war,</l>
<l n="tr">With men not only Heav'n's peculiar care,</l>
<l n="tr">But Heav'n's own race; unconquer'd in the field,</l>
<l n="tr">Or, conquer'd, yet unknowing how to yield.</l>
<l n="tr">What hopes you had in Diomedes, lay down:</l>
<l n="tr">Our hopes must center on ourselves alone.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet those how feeble, and, indeed, how vain,</l>
<l n="tr">You see too well; nor need my words explain.</l>
<l n="tr">Vanquish'd without resource; laid flat by fate;</l>
<l n="tr">Factions within, a foe without the gate!</l>
<l n="tr">Not but I grant that all perform'd their parts</l>
<l n="tr">With manly force, and with undaunted hearts:</l>
<l n="tr">With our united strength the war we wag'd;</l>
<l n="tr">With equal numbers, equal arms, engag'd.</l>
<l n="tr">You see  th'  event.—Now hear what I propose,</l>
<l n="tr">To save our friends, and satisfy our foes.</l>
<l n="tr">A tract of land the Latins have possess'd</l>
<l n="tr">Along the <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>, stretching to the west,</l>
<l n="tr">Which now Rutulians and Auruncans till,</l>
<l n="tr">And their mix'd cattle graze the fruitful hill.</l>
<l n="tr">Those mountains fill'd with firs, that lower land,</l>
<l n="tr">If you consent, the Trojan shall command,</l>
<l n="tr">Call'd into part of what is ours; and there,</l>
<l n="tr">On terms agreed, the common country share.</l>
<l n="tr">There let'em build and settle, if they please;</l>
<l n="tr">Unless they choose once more to cross the seas,</l>
<l n="tr">In search of seats remote from <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">And from unwelcome inmates set us free.</l>
<l n="tr">Then twice ten galleys let us build with speed,</l>
<l n="tr">Or twice as many more, if more they need.</l>
<l n="tr">Materials are at hand; a well-grown wood</l>
<l n="tr">Runs equal with the margin of the flood:</l>
<l n="tr">Let them the number and the form assign;</l>
<l n="tr">The care and cost of all the stores be mine.</l>
<l n="tr">To treat the peace, a hundred senators</l>
<l n="tr">Shall be commission'd hence with ample pow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">With olive the presents they shall bear,</l>
<l n="tr">A purple robe, a royal iv'ry chair,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the marks of sway that Latian monarchs wear,</l>
<l n="tr">And sums of gold. Among yourselves debate</l>
<l n="tr">This great affair, and save the sinking state.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="336" unit="card"/>Then Drances took the word, who grudg'd, long since,</l>
<l n="tr">The rising glories of the Daunian prince.</l>
<l n="tr">Factious and rich, bold at the council board,</l>
<l n="tr">But cautious in the field, he shunn'd the sword;</l>
<l n="tr">A close caballer, and tongue-valiant lord.</l>
<l n="tr">Noble his mother was, and near the throne;</l>
<l n="tr">But, what his father's parentage, unknown.</l>
<l n="tr">He rose, and took  th'  advantage of the times,</l>
<l n="tr">To load young Turnus with invidious crimes.</l>
<l n="tr">“Such truths, O king,” said he, “your words contain,</l>
<l n="tr">As strike the sense, and all replies are vain;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor are your loyal subjects now to seek</l>
<l n="tr">What common needs require, but fear to speak.</l>
<l n="tr">Let him give leave of speech, that haughty man,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose pride this unauspicious war began;</l>
<l n="tr">For whose ambition (let me dare to say,</l>
<l n="tr">Fear set apart, tho' death is in my way)</l>
<l n="tr">The plains of <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> run with blood around.</l>
<l n="tr">So many valiant heroes bite the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Dejected grief in ev'ry face appears;</l>
<l n="tr">A town in mourning, and a land in tears;</l>
<l n="tr">While he,  th'  undoubted author of our harms,</l>
<l n="tr">The man who menaces the gods with arms,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, after all his boasts, forsook the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">And sought his safety in ignoble flight.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, best of kings, since you propose to send</l>
<l n="tr">Such bounteous presents to your Trojan friend;</l>
<l n="tr">Add yet a greater at our joint request,</l>
<l n="tr">One which he values more than all the rest:</l>
<l n="tr">Give him the fair <persName>Lavinia</persName> for his bride;</l>
<l n="tr">With that alliance let the league be tied,</l>
<l n="tr">And for the bleeding land a lasting peace provide.</l>
<l n="tr">Let insolence no longer awe the throne;</l>
<l n="tr">But, with a father's right, bestow your own.</l>
<l n="tr">For this maligner of the general good,</l>
<l n="tr">If still we fear his force, he must be woo'd;</l>
<l n="tr">His haughty godhead we with pray'rs implore,</l>
<l n="tr">Your scepter to release, and our just rights restore.</l>
<l n="tr">O cursed cause of all our ills, must we</l>
<l n="tr">Wage wars unjust, and fall in fight, for thee!</l>
<l n="tr">What right hast thou to rule the Latian state,</l>
<l n="tr">And send us out to meet our certain fate?</l>
<l n="tr">'T is a destructive war: from Turnus' hand</l>
<l n="tr">Our peace and public safety we demand.</l>
<l n="tr">Let the fair bride to the brave chief remain;</l>
<l n="tr">If not, the peace, without the pledge, is vain.</l>
<l n="tr">Turnus, I know you think me not your friend,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor will I much with your belief contend:</l>
<l n="tr">I beg your greatness not to give the law</l>
<l n="tr">In others' realms, but, beaten, to withdraw.</l>
<l n="tr">Pity your own, or pity our estate;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor twist our fortunes with your sinking fate.</l>
<l n="tr">Your interest is, the war should never cease;</l>
<l n="tr">But we have felt enough to wish the peace:</l>
<l n="tr">A land exhausted to the last remains,</l>
<l n="tr">Depopulated towns, and driven plains.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, if desire of fame, and thirst of pow'r,</l>
<l n="tr">A beauteous princess, with a crown in dow'r,</l>
<l n="tr">So fire your mind, in arms assert your right,</l>
<l n="tr">And meet your foe, who dares you to the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Mankind, it seems, is made for you alone;</l>
<l n="tr">We, but the slaves who mount you to the throne:</l>
<l n="tr">A base ignoble crowd, without a name,</l>
<l n="tr">Unwept, unworthy, of the fun'ral flame,</l>
<l n="tr">By duty bound to forfeit each his life,</l>
<l n="tr">That Turnus may possess a royal wife.</l>
<l n="tr">Permit not, mighty man, so mean a crew</l>
<l n="tr">Should share such triumphs, and detain from you</l>
<l n="tr">The post of honor, your undoubted due.</l>
<l n="tr">Rather alone your matchless force employ,</l>
<l n="tr">To merit what alone you must enjoy.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="376" unit="card"/>These words, so full of malice mix'd with art,</l>
<l n="tr">Inflam'd with rage the youthful hero's heart.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, groaning from the bottom of his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">He heav'd for wind, and thus his wrath express'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“You, Drances, never want a stream of words,</l>
<l n="tr">Then, when the public need requires our swords.</l>
<l n="tr">First in the council hall to steer the state,</l>
<l n="tr">And ever foremost in a tongue-debate,</l>
<l n="tr">While our strong walls secure us from the foe,</l>
<l n="tr">Ere yet with blood our ditches overflow:</l>
<l n="tr">But let the potent orator declaim,</l>
<l n="tr">And with the brand of coward blot my name;</l>
<l n="tr">Free leave is giv'n him, when his fatal hand</l>
<l n="tr">Has cover'd with more corps the sanguine strand,</l>
<l n="tr">And high as mine his tow'ring trophies stand.</l>
<l n="tr">If any doubt remains, who dares the most,</l>
<l n="tr">Let us decide it at the Trojan's cost,</l>
<l n="tr">And issue both abreast, where honor calls—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Foes are not far to seek without the walls—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Unless his noisy tongue can only fight,</l>
<l n="tr">And feet were giv'n him but to speed his flight.</l>
<l n="tr">I beaten from the field? I forc'd away?</l>
<l n="tr">Who, but so known a dastard, dares to say?</l>
<l n="tr">Had he but ev'n beheld the fight, his eyes</l>
<l n="tr">Had witness'd for me what his tongue denies:</l>
<l n="tr">What heaps of Trojans by this hand were slain,</l>
<l n="tr">And how the bloody <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> swell'd the main.</l>
<l n="tr">All saw, but he,  th' Arcadian troops retire</l>
<l n="tr">In scatter'd squadrons, and their prince expire.</l>
<l n="tr">The giant brothers, in their camp, have found,</l>
<l n="tr">I was not forc'd with ease to quit my ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Not such the Trojans tried me, when, inclos'd,</l>
<l n="tr">I singly their united arms oppos'd:</l>
<l n="tr">First forc'd an entrance thro' their thick array;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, glutted with their slaughter, freed my way.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="399" unit="card"/>'T is a destructive war? So let it be,</l>
<l n="tr">But to the Phrygian pirate, and to thee!</l>
<l n="tr">Meantime proceed to fill the people's ears</l>
<l n="tr">With false reports, their minds with panic fears:</l>
<l n="tr">Extol the strength of a twice-conquer'd race;</l>
<l n="tr">Our foes encourage, and our friends debase.</l>
<l n="tr">Believe thy fables, and the Trojan town</l>
<l n="tr">Triumphant stands; the Grecians are o'erthrown;</l>
<l n="tr">Suppliant at <persName>Hector</persName>'s feet Achilles lies,</l>
<l n="tr">And Diomede from fierce Aeneas flies.</l>
<l n="tr">Say rapid Aufidus with awful dread</l>
<l n="tr">Runs backward from the sea, and hides his head,</l>
<l n="tr">When the great Trojan on his bank appears;</l>
<l n="tr">For that's as true as thy dissembled fears</l>
<l n="tr">Of my revenge. Dismiss that vanity:</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, Drances, art below a death from me.</l>
<l n="tr">Let that vile soul in that vile body rest;</l>
<l n="tr">The lodging is well worthy of the guest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, royal father, to the present state</l>
<l n="tr">Of our affairs, and of this high debate:</l>
<l n="tr">If in your arms thus early you diffide,</l>
<l n="tr">And think your fortune is already tried;</l>
<l n="tr">If one defeat has brought us down so low,</l>
<l n="tr">As never more in fields to meet the foe;</l>
<l n="tr">Then I conclude for peace: 't is time to treat,</l>
<l n="tr">And lie like vassals at the victor's feet.</l>
<l n="tr">But, O! if any ancient blood remains,</l>
<l n="tr">One drop of all our fathers, in our veins,</l>
<l n="tr">That man would I prefer before the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Who dar'd his death with an undaunted breast;</l>
<l n="tr">Who comely fell, by no dishonest wound,</l>
<l n="tr">To shun that sight, and, dying, gnaw'd the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">But, if we still have fresh recruits in store,</l>
<l n="tr">If our confederates can afford us more;</l>
<l n="tr">If the contended field we bravely fought,</l>
<l n="tr">And not a bloodless victory was bought;</l>
<l n="tr">Their losses equal'd ours; and, for their slain,</l>
<l n="tr">With equal fires they fill'd the shining plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Why thus, unforc'd, should we so tamely yield,</l>
<l n="tr">And, ere the trumpet sounds, resign the field?</l>
<l n="tr">Good unexpected, evils unforeseen,</l>
<l n="tr">Appear by turns, as fortune shifts the scene:</l>
<l n="tr">Some, rais'd aloft, come tumbling down amain;</l>
<l n="tr">Then fall so hard, they bound and rise again.</l>
<l n="tr">If Diomede refuse his aid to lend,</l>
<l n="tr">The great Messapus yet remains our friend:</l>
<l n="tr">Tolumnius, who foretells events, is ours;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Italian chiefs and princes join their pow'rs:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor least in number, nor in name the last,</l>
<l n="tr">Your own brave subjects have your cause embrac'd</l>
<l n="tr">Above the rest, the Volscian Amazon</l>
<l n="tr">Contains an army in herself alone,</l>
<l n="tr">And heads a squadron, terrible to sight,</l>
<l n="tr">With glitt'ring shields, in brazen armor bright.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, if the foe a single fight demand,</l>
<l n="tr">And I alone the public peace withstand;</l>
<l n="tr">If you consent, he shall not be refus'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor find a hand to victory unus'd.</l>
<l n="tr">This new Achilles, let him take the field,</l>
<l n="tr">With fated armor, and Vulcanian shield!</l>
<l n="tr">For you, my royal father, and my fame,</l>
<l n="tr">I, Turnus, not the least of all my name,</l>
<l n="tr">Devote my soul. He calls me hand to hand,</l>
<l n="tr">And I alone will answer his demand.</l>
<l n="tr">Drances shall rest secure, and neither share</l>
<l n="tr">The danger, nor divide the prize of war.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="445" unit="card"/>While they debate, nor these nor those will yield,</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas draws his forces to the field,</l>
<l n="tr">And moves his camp. The scouts with flying speed</l>
<l n="tr">Return, and thro' the frighted city spread</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unpleasing news, the Trojans are descried,</l>
<l n="tr">In battle marching by the river side,</l>
<l n="tr">And bending to the town. They take  th'  alarm:</l>
<l n="tr">Some tremble, some are bold; all in confusion arm.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' impetuous youth press forward to the field;</l>
<l n="tr">They clash the sword, and clatter on the shield:</l>
<l n="tr">The fearful matrons raise a screaming cry;</l>
<l n="tr">Old feeble men with fainter groans reply;</l>
<l n="tr">A jarring sound results, and mingles in the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Like that of swans remurm'ring to the floods,</l>
<l n="tr">Or birds of diff'ring kinds in hollow woods.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Turnus  th'  occasion takes, and cries aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“Talk on, ye quaint haranguers of the crowd:</l>
<l n="tr">Declaim in praise of peace, when danger calls,</l>
<l n="tr">And the fierce foes in arms approach the walls.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and, turning short, with speedy pace,</l>
<l n="tr">Casts back a scornful glance, and quits the place:</l>
<l n="tr">“Thou, Volusus, the Volscian troops command</l>
<l n="tr">To mount; and lead thyself our Ardean band.</l>
<l n="tr">Messapus and Catillus, post your force</l>
<l n="tr">Along the fields, to charge the Trojan horse.</l>
<l n="tr">Some guard the passes, others man the wall;</l>
<l n="tr">Drawn up in arms, the rest attend my call.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="468" unit="card"/>They swarm from ev'ry quarter of the town,</l>
<l n="tr">And with disorder'd haste the rampires crown.</l>
<l n="tr">Good old Latinus, when he saw, too late,</l>
<l n="tr">The gath'ring storm just breaking on the state,</l>
<l n="tr">Dismiss'd the council till a fitter time,</l>
<l n="tr">And own'd his easy temper as his crime,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, forc'd against his reason, had complied</l>
<l n="tr">To break the treaty for the promis'd bride.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Some help to sink new trenches; others aid</l>
<l n="tr">To ram the stones, or raise the palisade.</l>
<l n="tr">Hoarse trumpets sound  th'  alarm; around the walls</l>
<l n="tr">Runs a distracted crew, whom their last labor calls.</l>
<l n="tr">A sad procession in the streets is seen,</l>
<l n="tr">Of matrons, that attend the mother queen:</l>
<l n="tr">High in her chair she sits, and, at her side,</l>
<l n="tr">With downcast eyes, appears the fatal bride.</l>
<l n="tr">They mount the cliff, where <persName>Pallas</persName>' temple stands;</l>
<l n="tr">Pray'rs in their mouths, and presents in their hands,</l>
<l n="tr">With censers first they fume the sacred shrine,</l>
<l n="tr">Then in this common supplication join:</l>
<l n="tr">“O patroness of arms, unspotted maid,</l>
<l n="tr">Propitious hear, and lend thy Latins aid!</l>
<l n="tr">Break short the pirate's lance; pronounce his fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And lay the Phrygian low before the gate.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now Turnus arms for fight. His back and breast</l>
<l n="tr">Well-temper'd steel and scaly brass invest:</l>
<l n="tr">The cuishes which his brawny thighs infold</l>
<l n="tr">Are mingled metal damask'd o'er with gold.</l>
<l n="tr">His faithful fauchion sits upon his side;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor casque, nor crest, his manly features hide:</l>
<l n="tr">But, bare to view, amid surrounding friends,</l>
<l n="tr">With godlike grace, he from the tow'r descends.</l>
<l n="tr">Exulting in his strength, he seems to dare</l>
<l n="tr">His absent rival, and to promise war.</l>
<l n="tr">Freed from his keepers, thus, with broken reins,</l>
<l n="tr">The wanton courser prances o'er the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">Or in the pride of youth o'erleaps the mounds,</l>
<l n="tr">And snuffs the females in forbidden grounds.</l>
<l n="tr">Or seeks his wat'ring in the well-known flood,</l>
<l n="tr">To quench his thirst, and cool his fiery blood:</l>
<l n="tr">He swims luxuriant in the liquid plain,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er his shoulder flows his waving mane:</l>
<l n="tr">He neighs, he snorts, he bears his head on high;</l>
<l n="tr">Before his ample chest the frothy waters fly.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="498" unit="card"/>Soon as the prince appears without the gate,</l>
<l n="tr">The Volscians, with their virgin leader, wait</l>
<l n="tr">His last commands. Then, with a graceful mien,</l>
<l n="tr">Lights from her lofty steed the warrior queen:</l>
<l n="tr">Her squadron imitates, and each descends;</l>
<l n="tr">Whose common suit <persName>Camilla</persName> thus commends:</l>
<l n="tr">“If sense of honor, if a soul secure</l>
<l n="tr">Of inborn worth, that can all tests endure,</l>
<l n="tr">Can promise aught, or on itself rely</l>
<l n="tr">Greatly to dare, to conquer or to die;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, I alone, sustain'd by these, will meet</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrrhene troops, and promise their defeat.</l>
<l n="tr">Ours be the danger, ours the sole renown:</l>
<l n="tr">You, gen'ral, stay behind, and guard the town:”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Turnus a while stood mute, with glad surprise,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the fierce virago fix'd his eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus return'd: “O grace of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">With what becoming thanks can I reply?</l>
<l n="tr">Not only words lie lab'ring in my breast,</l>
<l n="tr">But thought itself is by thy praise oppress'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet rob me not of all; but let me join</l>
<l n="tr">My toils, my hazard, and my fame, with thine.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan, not in stratagem unskill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Sends his light horse before to scour the field:</l>
<l n="tr">Himself, thro' steep ascents and thorny brakes,</l>
<l n="tr">A larger compass to the city takes.</l>
<l n="tr">This news my scouts confirm, and I prepare</l>
<l n="tr">To foil his cunning, and his force to dare;</l>
<l n="tr">With chosen foot his passage to forelay,</l>
<l n="tr">And place an ambush in the winding way.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, with thy Volscians, face the Tuscan horse;</l>
<l n="tr">The brave Messapus shall thy troops inforce</l>
<l n="tr">With those of Tibur, and the Latian band,</l>
<l n="tr">Subjected all to thy supreme command.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, he warns Messapus to the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Then ev'ry chief exhorts with equal care.</l>
<l n="tr">All thus encourag'd, his own troops he joins,</l>
<l n="tr">And hastes to prosecute his deep designs.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="522" unit="card"/>Inclos'd with hills, a winding valley lies,</l>
<l n="tr">By nature form'd for fraud, and fitted for surprise.</l>
<l n="tr">A narrow track, by human steps untrode,</l>
<l n="tr">Leads, thro' perplexing thorns, to this obscure abode.</l>
<l n="tr">High o'er the vale a steepy mountain stands,</l>
<l n="tr">Whence the surveying sight the nether ground commands.</l>
<l n="tr">The top is level, an offensive seat</l>
<l n="tr">Of war; and from the war a safe retreat:</l>
<l n="tr">For, on the right and left, is room to press</l>
<l n="tr">The foes at hand, or from afar distress;</l>
<l n="tr">To drive 'em headlong downward, and to pour</l>
<l n="tr">On their descending backs a stony show'r.</l>
<l n="tr">Thither young Turnus took the well-known way,</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd the pass, and in blind ambush lay.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="532" unit="card"/>Meantime Latonian Phoebe, from the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">Beheld  th'  approaching war with hateful eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And call'd the light-foot Opis to her aid,</l>
<l n="tr">Her most belov'd and ever-trusty maid;</l>
<l n="tr">Then with a sigh began: “Camilla goes</l>
<l n="tr">To meet her death amidst her fatal foes:</l>
<l n="tr">The nymphs I lov'd of all my mortal train,</l>
<l n="tr">Invested with Diana's arms, in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor is my kindness for the virgin new:</l>
<l n="tr">'T was born with her; and with her years it grew.</l>
<l n="tr">Her father Metabus, when forc'd away</l>
<l n="tr">From old Privernum, for tyrannic sway,</l>
<l n="tr">Snatch'd up, and sav'd from his prevailing foes,</l>
<l n="tr">This tender babe, companion of his woes.</l>
<l n="tr">Casmilla was her mother; but he drown'd</l>
<l n="tr">One hissing letter in a softer sound,</l>
<l n="tr">And call'd Camilla. thro' the woods he flies;</l>
<l n="tr">Wrapp'd in his robe the royal infant lies.</l>
<l n="tr">His foes in sight, he mends his weary pace;</l>
<l n="tr">With shout and clamors they pursue the chase.</l>
<l n="tr">The banks of Amasene at length he gains:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The raging flood his farther flight restrains,</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd o'er the borders with unusual rains.</l>
<l n="tr">Prepar'd to plunge into the stream, he fears,</l>
<l n="tr">Not for himself, but for the charge he bears.</l>
<l n="tr">Anxious, he stops a while, and thinks in haste;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, desp'rate in distress, resolves at last.</l>
<l n="tr">A knotty lance of well-boil'd oak he bore;</l>
<l n="tr">The middle part with cork he cover'd o'er:</l>
<l n="tr">He clos'd the child within the hollow space;</l>
<l n="tr">With twigs of bending osier bound the case;</l>
<l n="tr">Then pois'd the spear, heavy with human weight,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus invok'd my favor for the freight:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="557" unit="card"/>‘Accept, great goddess of the woods,’ he said,</l>
<l n="tr">‘Sent by her sire, this dedicated maid!</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' air she flies a suppliant to thy shrine;</l>
<l n="tr">And the first weapons that she knows, are thine.’</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and with full force the spear he threw:</l>
<l n="tr">Above the sounding waves Camilla flew.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, press'd by foes, he stemm'd the stormy tide,</l>
<l n="tr">And gain'd, by stress of arms, the farther side.</l>
<l n="tr">His fasten'd spear he pull'd from out the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And, victor of his vows, his infant nymph unbound;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor, after that, in towns which walls inclose,</l>
<l n="tr">Would trust his hunted life amidst his foes;</l>
<l n="tr">But, rough, in open air he chose to lie;</l>
<l n="tr">Earth was his couch, his cov'ring was the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">On hills unshorn, or in a desart den,</l>
<l n="tr">He shunn'd the dire society of men.</l>
<l n="tr">A shepherd's solitary life he led;</l>
<l n="tr">His daughter with the milk of mares he fed.</l>
<l n="tr">The dugs of bears, and ev'ry salvage beast,</l>
<l n="tr">He drew, and thro' her lips the liquor press'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The little Amazon could scarcely go:</l>
<l n="tr">He loads her with a quiver and a bow;</l>
<l n="tr">And, that she might her stagg'ring steps command,</l>
<l n="tr">He with a slender jav'lin fills her hand.</l>
<l n="tr">Her flowing hair no golden fillet bound;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor swept her trailing robe the dusty ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Instead of these, a tiger's hide o'erspread</l>
<l n="tr">Her back and shoulders, fasten'd to her head.</l>
<l n="tr">The flying dart she first attempts to fling,</l>
<l n="tr">And round her tender temples toss'd the sling;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, as her strength with years increas'd, began</l>
<l n="tr">To pierce aloft in air the soaring swan,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the clouds to fetch the heron and the crane.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tuscan matrons with each other vied,</l>
<l n="tr">To bless their rival sons with such a bride;</l>
<l n="tr">But she disdains their love, to share with me</l>
<l n="tr">The sylvan shades and vow'd virginity.</l>
<l n="tr">And, O! I wish, contented with my cares</l>
<l n="tr">Of salvage spoils, she had not sought the wars!</l>
<l n="tr">Then had she been of my celestial train,</l>
<l n="tr">And shunn'd the fate that dooms her to be slain.</l>
<l n="tr">But since, opposing Heav'n's decree, she goes</l>
<l n="tr">To find her death among forbidden foes,</l>
<l n="tr">Haste with these arms, and take thy steepy flight.</l>
<l n="tr">Where, with the gods, averse, the Latins fight.</l>
<l n="tr">This bow to thee, this quiver I bequeath,</l>
<l n="tr">This chosen arrow, to revenge her death:</l>
<l n="tr">By whate'er hand <persName>Camilla</persName> shall be slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Or of the Trojan or Italian train,</l>
<l n="tr">Let him not pass unpunish'd from the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, in a hollow cloud, myself will aid</l>
<l n="tr">To bear the breathless body of my maid:</l>
<l n="tr">Unspoil'd shall be her arms, and unprofan'd</l>
<l n="tr">Her holy limbs with any human hand,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a marble tomb laid in her native land.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said. The faithful nymph descends from high</l>
<l n="tr">With rapid flight, and cuts the sounding sky:</l>
<l n="tr">Black clouds and stormy winds around her body fly.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="597" unit="card"/>By this, the Trojan and the Tuscan horse,</l>
<l n="tr">Drawn up in squadrons, with united force,</l>
<l n="tr">Approach the walls: the sprightly coursers bound,</l>
<l n="tr">Press forward on their bits, and shift their ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Shields, arms, and spears flash horribly from far;</l>
<l n="tr">And the fields glitter with a waving war.</l>
<l n="tr">Oppos'd to these, come on with furious force</l>
<l n="tr">Messapus, Coras, and the Latian horse;</l>
<l n="tr">These in the body plac'd, on either hand</l>
<l n="tr">Sustain'd and clos'd by fair <persName>Camilla</persName>'s band.</l>
<l n="tr">Advancing in a line, they couch their spears;</l>
<l n="tr">And less and less the middle space appears.</l>
<l n="tr">Thick smoke obscures the field; and scarce are seen</l>
<l n="tr">The neighing coursers, and the shouting men.</l>
<l n="tr">In distance of their darts they stop their course;</l>
<l n="tr">Then man to man they rush, and horse to horse.</l>
<l n="tr">The face of heav'n their flying jav'lins hide,</l>
<l n="tr">And deaths unseen are dealt on either side.</l>
<l n="tr">Tyrrhenus, and Aconteus, void of fear,</l>
<l n="tr">By mettled coursers borne in full career,</l>
<l n="tr">Meet first oppos'd; and, with a mighty shock,</l>
<l n="tr">Their horses' heads against each other knock.</l>
<l n="tr">Far from his steed is fierce Aconteus cast,</l>
<l n="tr">As with an engine's force, or lightning's blast:</l>
<l n="tr">He rolls along in blood, and breathes his last.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="618" unit="card"/>The Latin squadrons take a sudden fright,</l>
<l n="tr">And sling their shields behind, to save their backs in flight</l>
<l n="tr">Spurring at speed to their own walls they drew;</l>
<l n="tr">Close in the rear the Tuscan troops pursue,</l>
<l n="tr">And urge their flight: Asylas leads the chase;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, seiz'd, with shame, they wheel about and face,</l>
<l n="tr">Receive their foes, and raise a threat'ning cry.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tuscans take their turn to fear and fly.</l>
<l n="tr">So swelling surges, with a thund'ring roar,</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n on each other's backs, insult the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Bound o'er the rocks, incroach upon the land,</l>
<l n="tr">And far upon the beach eject the sand;</l>
<l n="tr">Then backward, with a swing, they take their way,</l>
<l n="tr">Repuls'd from upper ground, and seek their mother sea;</l>
<l n="tr">With equal hurry quit  th'  invaded shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And swallow back the sand and stones they spew'd before.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Twice were the Tuscans masters of the field,</l>
<l n="tr">Twice by the Latins, in their turn, repell'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Asham'd at length, to the third charge they ran;</l>
<l n="tr">Both hosts resolv'd, and mingled man to man.</l>
<l n="tr">Now dying groans are heard; the fields are strow'd</l>
<l n="tr">With falling bodies, and are drunk with blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Arms, horses, men, on heaps together lie:</l>
<l n="tr">Confus'd the fight, and more confus'd the cry.</l>
<l n="tr">Orsilochus, who durst not press too near</l>
<l n="tr">Strong Remulus, at distance drove his spear,</l>
<l n="tr">And stuck the steel beneath his horse's ear.</l>
<l n="tr">The fiery steed, impatient of the wound,</l>
<l n="tr">Curvets, and, springing upward with a bound,</l>
<l n="tr">His helpless lord cast backward on the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Catillus pierc'd Iolas first; then drew</l>
<l n="tr">His reeking lance, and at Herminius threw,</l>
<l n="tr">The mighty champion of the Tuscan crew.</l>
<l n="tr">His neck and throat unarm'd, his head was bare,</l>
<l n="tr">But shaded with a length of yellow hair:</l>
<l n="tr">Secure, he fought, expos'd on ev'ry part,</l>
<l n="tr">A spacious mark for swords, and for the flying dart.</l>
<l n="tr">Across the shoulders came the feather'd wound;</l>
<l n="tr">Transfix'd he fell, and doubled to the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">The sands with streaming blood are sanguine dyed,</l>
<l n="tr">And death with honor sought on either side.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="648" unit="card"/>Resistless thro' the war <persName>Camilla</persName> rode,</l>
<l n="tr">In danger unappall'd, and pleas'd with blood.</l>
<l n="tr">One side was bare for her exerted breast;</l>
<l n="tr">One shoulder with her painted quiver press'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Now from afar her fatal jav'lins play;</l>
<l n="tr">Now with her ax's edge she hews her way:</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Diana</persName>'s arms upon her shoulder sound;</l>
<l n="tr">And when, too closely press'd, she quits the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">From her bent bow she sends a backward wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Her maids, in martial pomp, on either side,</l>
<l n="tr">Larina, <persName>Tulla</persName>, fierce Tarpeia, ride:</l>
<l n="tr">Italians all; in peace, their queen's delight;</l>
<l n="tr">In war, the bold companions of the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">So march'd the Tracian Amazons of old,</l>
<l n="tr">When Thermodon with bloody billows roll'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Such troops as these in shining arms were seen,</l>
<l n="tr">When Theseus met in fight their maiden queen:</l>
<l n="tr">Such to the field Penthisilea led,</l>
<l n="tr">From the fierce virgin when the Grecians fled;</l>
<l n="tr">With such, return'd triumphant from the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Her maids with cries attend the lofty car;</l>
<l n="tr">They clash with manly force their moony shields;</l>
<l n="tr">With female shouts resound the Phrygian fields.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="664" unit="card"/>Who foremost, and who last, heroic maid,</l>
<l n="tr">On the cold earth were by thy courage laid?</l>
<l n="tr">Thy spear, of mountain ash, Eumenius first,</l>
<l n="tr">With fury driv'n, from side to side transpierc'd:</l>
<l n="tr">A purple stream came spouting from the wound;</l>
<l n="tr">Bath'd in his blood he lies, and bites the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Liris and Pegasus at once she slew:</l>
<l n="tr">The former, as the slacken'd reins he drew</l>
<l n="tr">Of his faint steed; the latter, as he stretch'd</l>
<l n="tr">His arm to prop his friend, the jav'lin reach'd.</l>
<l n="tr">By the same weapon, sent from the same hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Both fall together, and both spurn the sand.</l>
<l n="tr">Amastrus next is added to the slain:</l>
<l n="tr">The rest in rout she follows o'er the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">Tereus, Harpalycus, Demophoon,</l>
<l n="tr">And Chromis, at full speed her fury shun.</l>
<l n="tr">Of all her deadly darts, not one she lost;</l>
<l n="tr">Each was attended with a Trojan ghost.</l>
<l n="tr">Young Ornithus bestrode a hunter steed,</l>
<l n="tr">Swift for the chase, and of Apulian breed.</l>
<l n="tr">Him from afar she spied, in arms unknown:</l>
<l n="tr">O'er his broad back an ox's hide was thrown;</l>
<l n="tr">His helm a wolf, whose gaping jaws were spread</l>
<l n="tr">A cov'ring for his cheeks, and grinn'd around his head,</l>
<l n="tr">He clench'd within his hand an iron prong,</l>
<l n="tr">And tower'd above the rest, conspicuous in the throng.</l>
<l n="tr">Him soon she singled from the flying train,</l>
<l n="tr">And slew with ease; then thus insults the slain:</l>
<l n="tr">“Vain hunter, didst thou think thro' woods to chase</l>
<l n="tr">The savage herd, a vile and trembling race?</l>
<l n="tr">Here cease thy vaunts, and own my victory:</l>
<l n="tr">A woman warrior was too strong for thee.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, if the ghosts demand the conqu'ror's name,</l>
<l n="tr">Confessing great <persName>Camilla</persName>, save thy shame.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="690" unit="card"/>Then Butes and Orsilochus she slew,</l>
<l n="tr">The bulkiest bodies of the Trojan crew;</l>
<l n="tr">But Butes breast to breast: the spear descends</l>
<l n="tr">Above the gorget, where his helmet ends,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er the shield which his left side defends.</l>
<l n="tr">Orsilochus and she their courses ply:</l>
<l n="tr">He seems to follow, and she seems to fly;</l>
<l n="tr">But in a narrower ring she makes the race;</l>
<l n="tr">And then he flies, and she pursues the chase.</l>
<l n="tr">Gath'ring at length on her deluded foe,</l>
<l n="tr">She swings her ax, and rises to the blow</l>
<l n="tr">Full on the helm behind, with such a sway</l>
<l n="tr">The weapon falls, the riven steel gives way:</l>
<l n="tr">He groans, he roars, he sues in vain for grace;</l>
<l n="tr">Brains, mingled with his blood, besmear his face.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Astonish'd Aunus just arrives by chance,</l>
<l n="tr">To see his fall; nor farther dares advance;</l>
<l n="tr">But, fixing on the horrid maid his eye,</l>
<l n="tr">He stares, and shakes, and finds it vain to fly;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, like a true Ligurian, born to cheat,</l>
<l n="tr">(At least while fortune favor'd his deceit,)</l>
<l n="tr">Cries out aloud: “What courage have you shown,</l>
<l n="tr">Who trust your courser's strength, and not your own?</l>
<l n="tr">Forego the vantage of your horse, alight,</l>
<l n="tr">And then on equal terms begin the fight:</l>
<l n="tr">It shall be seen, weak woman, what you can,</l>
<l n="tr">When, foot to foot, you combat with a man,”</l>
<l n="tr">He said. She glows with anger and disdain,</l>
<l n="tr">Dismounts with speed to dare him on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">And leaves her horse at large among her train;</l>
<l n="tr">With her drawn sword defies him to the field,</l>
<l n="tr">And, marching, lifts aloft her maiden shield.</l>
<l n="tr">The youth, who thought his cunning did succeed,</l>
<l n="tr">Reins round his horse, and urges all his speed;</l>
<l n="tr">Adds the remembrance of the spur, and hides</l>
<l n="tr">The goring rowels in his bleeding sides.</l>
<l n="tr">“Vain fool, and coward!” cries the lofty maid,</l>
<l n="tr">“Caught in the train which thou thyself hast laid!</l>
<l n="tr">On others practice thy Ligurian arts;</l>
<l n="tr">Thin stratagems and tricks of little hearts</l>
<l n="tr">Are lost on me: nor shalt thou safe retire,</l>
<l n="tr">With vaunting lies, to thy fallacious sire.”</l>
<l n="tr">At this, so fast her flying feet she sped,</l>
<l n="tr">That soon she strain'd beyond his horse's head:</l>
<l n="tr">Then turning short, at once she seiz'd the rein,</l>
<l n="tr">And laid the boaster grov'ling on the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Not with more ease the falcon, from above,</l>
<l n="tr">Trusses in middle air the trembling dove,</l>
<l n="tr">Then plumes the prey, in her strong pounces bound:</l>
<l n="tr">The feathers, foul with blood, come tumbling to the ground.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="725" unit="card"/>Now mighty Jove, from his superior height,</l>
<l n="tr">With his broad eye surveys  th'  unequal fight.</l>
<l n="tr">He fires the breast of Tarchon with disdain,</l>
<l n="tr">And sends him to redeem  th' abandon'd plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the broken ranks the Tuscan rides,</l>
<l n="tr">And these encourages, and those he chides;</l>
<l n="tr">Recalls each leader, by his name, from flight;</l>
<l n="tr">Renews their ardor, and restores the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">“What panic fear has seiz'd your souls? O shame,</l>
<l n="tr">O brand perpetual of  th'  Etrurian name!</l>
<l n="tr">Cowards incurable, a woman's hand</l>
<l n="tr">Drives, breaks, and scatters your ignoble band!</l>
<l n="tr">Now cast away the sword, and quit the shield!</l>
<l n="tr">What use of weapons which you dare not wield?</l>
<l n="tr">Not thus you fly your female foes by night,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor shun the feast, when the full bowls invite;</l>
<l n="tr">When to fat off'rings the glad augur calls,</l>
<l n="tr">And the shrill hornpipe sounds to bacchanals.</l>
<l n="tr">These are your studied cares, your lewd delight:</l>
<l n="tr">Swift to debauch, but slow to manly fight.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, he spurs amid the foes,</l>
<l n="tr">Not managing the life he meant to lose.</l>
<l n="tr">The first he found he seiz'd with headlong haste,</l>
<l n="tr">In his strong gripe, and clasp'd around the waist;</l>
<l n="tr">'T was Venulus, whom from his horse he tore,</l>
<l n="tr">And, laid athwart his own, in triumph bore.</l>
<l n="tr">Loud shouts ensue; the Latins turn their eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And view  th'  unusual sight with vast surprise.</l>
<l n="tr">The fiery Tarchon, flying o'er the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">Press'd in his arms the pond'rous prey sustains;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, with his shorten'd spear, explores around</l>
<l n="tr">His jointed arms, to fix a deadly wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor less the captive struggles for his life:</l>
<l n="tr">He writhes his body to prolong the strife,</l>
<l n="tr">And, fencing for his naked throat, exerts</l>
<l n="tr">His utmost vigor, and the point averts.</l>
<l n="tr">So stoops the yellow eagle from on high,</l>
<l n="tr">And bears a speckled serpent thro' the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Fast'ning his crooked talons on the prey:</l>
<l n="tr">The pris'ner hisses thro' the liquid way;</l>
<l n="tr">Resists the royal hawk; and, tho' oppress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">She fights in volumes, and erects her crest:</l>
<l n="tr">Turn'd to her foe, she stiffens ev'ry scale,</l>
<l n="tr">And shoots her forky tongue, and whisks her threat'ning tail.</l>
<l n="tr">Against the victor, all defense is weak:</l>
<l n="tr">Th' imperial bird still plies her with his beak;</l>
<l n="tr">He tears her bowels, and her breast he gores;</l>
<l n="tr">Then claps his pinions, and securely soars.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, thro' the midst of circling enemies,</l>
<l n="tr">Strong Tarchon snatch'd and bore away his prize.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrrhene troops, that shrunk before, now press</l>
<l n="tr">The Latins, and presume the like success.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Aruns, doom'd to death, his arts assay'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To murther, unespied, the Volscian maid:</l>
<l n="tr">This way and that his winding course he bends,</l>
<l n="tr">And, whereso'er she turns, her steps attends.</l>
<l n="tr">When she retires victorious from the chase,</l>
<l n="tr">He wheels about with care, and shifts his place;</l>
<l n="tr">When, rushing on, she seeks her foes flight,</l>
<l n="tr">He keeps aloof, but keeps her still in sight:</l>
<l n="tr">He threats, and trembles, trying ev'ry way,</l>
<l n="tr">Unseen to kill, and safely to betray.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="768" unit="card"/>Chloreus, the priest of Cybele, from far,</l>
<l n="tr">Glitt'ring in Phrygian arms amidst the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Was by the virgin view'd. The steed he press'd</l>
<l n="tr">Was proud with trappings, and his brawny chest</l>
<l n="tr">With scales of gilded brass was cover'd o'er;</l>
<l n="tr">A robe of Tyrian dye the rider wore.</l>
<l n="tr">With deadly wounds he gall'd the distant foe;</l>
<l n="tr">Gnossian his shafts, and Lycian was his bow:</l>
<l n="tr">A golden helm his front and head surrounds</l>
<l n="tr">A gilded quiver from his shoulder sounds.</l>
<l n="tr">Gold, weav'd with linen, on his thighs he wore,</l>
<l n="tr">With flowers of needlework distinguish'd o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">With golden buckles bound, and gather'd up before.</l>
<l n="tr">Him the fierce maid beheld with ardent eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Fond and ambitious of so rich a prize,</l>
<l n="tr">Or that the temple might his trophies hold,</l>
<l n="tr">Or else to shine herself in Trojan gold.</l>
<l n="tr">Blind in her haste, she chases him alone.</l>
<l n="tr">And seeks his life, regardless of her own.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This lucky moment the sly traitor chose:</l>
<l n="tr">Then, starting from his ambush, up he rose,</l>
<l n="tr">And threw, but first to Heav'n address'd his vows:</l>
<l n="tr">“O patron of Soractes' high abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">Phoebus, the ruling pow'r among the gods,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom first we serve, whole woods of unctuous pine</l>
<l n="tr">Are fell'd for thee, and to thy glory shine;</l>
<l n="tr">By thee protected with our naked soles,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' flames unsing'd we march, and tread the kindled coals</l>
<l n="tr">Give me, propitious pow'r, to wash away</l>
<l n="tr">The stains of this dishonorable day:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor spoils, nor triumph, from the fact I claim,</l>
<l n="tr">But with my future actions trust my fame.</l>
<l n="tr">Let me, by stealth, this female plague o'ercome,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the field return inglorious home.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="794" unit="card"/>Apollo heard, and, granting half his pray'r,</l>
<l n="tr">Shuffled in winds the rest, and toss'd in empty air.</l>
<l n="tr">He gives the death desir'd; his safe return</l>
<l n="tr">By southern tempests to the seas is borne.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, when the jav'lin whizz'd along the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">Both armies on <persName>Camilla</persName> turn'd their eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Directed by the sound. Of either host,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unhappy virgin, tho' concern'd the most,</l>
<l n="tr">Was only deaf; so greedy was she bent</l>
<l n="tr">On golden spoils, and on her prey intent;</l>
<l n="tr">Till in her pap the winged weapon stood</l>
<l n="tr">Infix'd, and deeply drunk the purple blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Her sad attendants hasten to sustain</l>
<l n="tr">Their dying lady, drooping on the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Far from their sight the trembling Aruns flies,</l>
<l n="tr">With beating heart, and fear confus'd with joys;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor dares he farther to pursue his blow,</l>
<l n="tr">Or ev'n to bear the sight of his expiring foe.</l>
<l n="tr">As, when the wolf has torn a bullock's hide</l>
<l n="tr">At unawares, or ranch'd a shepherd's side,</l>
<l n="tr">Conscious of his audacious deed, he flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And claps his quiv'ring tail between his thighs:</l>
<l n="tr">So, speeding once, the wretch no more attends,</l>
<l n="tr">But, spurring forward, herds among his friends.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She wrench'd the jav'lin with her dying hands,</l>
<l n="tr">But wedg'd within her breast the weapon stands;</l>
<l n="tr">The wood she draws, the steely point remains;</l>
<l n="tr">She staggers in her seat with agonizing pains:</l>
<l n="tr">(A gath'ring mist o'erclouds her cheerful eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And from her cheeks the rosy color flies:)</l>
<l n="tr">Then turns to her, whom of her female train</l>
<l n="tr">She trusted most, and thus she speaks with pain:</l>
<l n="tr">“<persName>Acca</persName>, 't is past! he swims before my sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Inexorable Death; and claims his right.</l>
<l n="tr">Bear my last words to Turnus; fly with speed,</l>
<l n="tr">And bid him timely to my charge succeed,</l>
<l n="tr">Repel the Trojans, and the town relieve:</l>
<l n="tr">Farewell! and in this kiss my parting breath receive.”</l>
<l n="tr">She said, and, sliding, sunk upon the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">Dying, her open'd hand forsakes the rein;</l>
<l n="tr">Short, and more short, she pants; by slow degrees</l>
<l n="tr">Her mind the passage from her body frees.</l>
<l n="tr">She drops her sword; she nods her plumy crest,</l>
<l n="tr">Her drooping head declining on her breast:</l>
<l n="tr">In the last sigh her struggling soul expires,</l>
<l n="tr">And, murm'ring with disdain, to Stygian sounds retires.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A shout, that struck the golden stars, ensued;</l>
<l n="tr">Despair and rage the languish'd fight renew'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan troops and Tuscans, in a line,</l>
<l n="tr">Advance to charge; the mix'd Arcadians join.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="836" unit="card"/>But Cynthia's maid, high seated, from afar</l>
<l n="tr">Surveys the field, and fortune of the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Unmov'd a while, till, prostrate on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Welt'ring in blood, she sees <persName>Camilla</persName> slain,</l>
<l n="tr">And, round her corpse, of friends and foes a fighting train.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, from the bottom of her breast, she drew</l>
<l n="tr">A mournful sigh, and these sad words ensue:</l>
<l n="tr">“Too dear a fine, ah much lamented maid,</l>
<l n="tr">For warring with the Trojans, thou hast paid!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor aught avail'd, in this unhappy strife,</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Diana</persName>'s sacred arms, to save thy life.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet unreveng'd thy goddess will not leave</l>
<l n="tr">Her vot'ry's death, nor; with vain sorrow grieve.</l>
<l n="tr">Branded the wretch, and be his name abhorr'd;</l>
<l n="tr">But after ages shall thy praise record.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' inglorious coward soon shall press the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus vows thy queen, and thus the Fates ordain.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>High o'er the field there stood a hilly mound,</l>
<l n="tr">Sacred the place, and spread with oaks around,</l>
<l n="tr">Where, in a marble tomb, Dercennus lay,</l>
<l n="tr">A king that once in <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> bore the sway.</l>
<l n="tr">The beauteous Opis thither bent her flight,</l>
<l n="tr">To mark the traitor Aruns from the height.</l>
<l n="tr">Him in refulgent arms she soon espied,</l>
<l n="tr">Swoln with success; and loudly thus she cried:</l>
<l n="tr">“Thy backward steps, vain boaster, are too late;</l>
<l n="tr">Turn like a man, at length, and meet thy fate.</l>
<l n="tr">Charg'd with my message, to <persName>Camilla</persName> go,</l>
<l n="tr">And say I sent thee to the shades below,</l>
<l n="tr">An honor undeserv'd from <persName>Cynthia</persName>'s bow.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said, and from her quiver chose with speed</l>
<l n="tr">The winged shaft, predestin'd for the deed;</l>
<l n="tr">Then to the stubborn yew her strength applied,</l>
<l n="tr">Till the far distant horns approach'd on either side.</l>
<l n="tr">The bowstring touch'd her breast, so strong she drew;</l>
<l n="tr">Whizzing in air the fatal arrow flew.</l>
<l n="tr">At once the twanging bow and sounding dart</l>
<l n="tr">The traitor heard, and felt the point within his heart.</l>
<l n="tr">Him, beating with his heels in pangs of death,</l>
<l n="tr">His flying friends to foreign fields bequeath.</l>
<l n="tr">The conqu'ring damsel, with expanded wings,</l>
<l n="tr">The welcome message to her mistress brings.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="868" unit="card"/>Their leader lost, the Volscians quit the field,</l>
<l n="tr">And, unsustain'd, the chiefs of Turnus yield.</l>
<l n="tr">The frighted soldiers, when their captains fly,</l>
<l n="tr">More on their speed than on their strength rely.</l>
<l n="tr">Confus'd in flight, they bear each other down,</l>
<l n="tr">And spur their horses headlong to the town.</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n by their foes, and to their fears resign'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Not once they turn, but take their wounds behind.</l>
<l n="tr">These drop the shield, and those the lance forego,</l>
<l n="tr">Or on their shoulders bear the slacken'd bow.</l>
<l n="tr">The hoofs of horses, with a rattling sound,</l>
<l n="tr">Beat short and thick, and shake the rotten ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Black clouds of dust come rolling in the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er the darken'd walls and rampires fly.</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling matrons, from their lofty stands,</l>
<l n="tr">Rend heav'n with female shrieks, and wring their hands.</l>
<l n="tr">All pressing on, pursuers and pursued,</l>
<l n="tr">Are crush'd in crowds, a mingled multitude.</l>
<l n="tr">Some happy few escape: the throng too late</l>
<l n="tr">Rush on for entrance, till they choke the gate.</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n in the sight of home, the wretched sire</l>
<l n="tr">Looks on, and sees his helpless son expire.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, in a fright, the folding gates they close,</l>
<l n="tr">But leave their friends excluded with their foes.</l>
<l n="tr">The vanquish'd cry; the victors loudly shout;</l>
<l n="tr">'T is terror all within, and slaughter all without.</l>
<l n="tr">Blind in their fear, they bounce against the wall,</l>
<l n="tr">Or, to the moats pursued, precipitate their fall.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The Latian virgins, valiant with despair,</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd on the tow'rs, the common danger share:</l>
<l n="tr">So much of zeal their country's cause inspir'd;</l>
<l n="tr">So much <persName>Camilla</persName>'s great example fir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Poles, sharpen'd in the flames, from high they throw,</l>
<l n="tr">With imitated darts, to gall the foe.</l>
<l n="tr">Their lives for godlike freedom they bequeath,</l>
<l n="tr">And crowd each other to be first in death.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="896" unit="card"/>Meantime to Turnus, ambush'd in the shade,</l>
<l n="tr">With heavy tidings came  th'  unhappy maid:</l>
<l n="tr">“The Volscians overthrown, <persName>Camilla</persName> kill'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The foes, entirely masters of the field,</l>
<l n="tr">Like a resistless flood, come rolling on:</l>
<l n="tr">The cry goes off the plain, and thickens to the town.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Inflam'd with rage, (for so the Furies fire</l>
<l n="tr">The Daunian's breast, and so the Fates require,)</l>
<l n="tr">He leaves the hilly pass, the woods in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd, and downward issues on the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce was he gone, when to the straits, now freed</l>
<l n="tr">From secret foes, the Trojan troops succeed.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the black forest and the ferny brake,</l>
<l n="tr">Unknowingly secure, their way they take;</l>
<l n="tr">From the rough mountains to the plain descend,</l>
<l n="tr">And there, in order drawn, their line extend.</l>
<l n="tr">Both armies now in open fields are seen;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor far the distance of the space between.</l>
<l n="tr">Both to the city bend. Aeneas sees,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' smoking fields, his hast'ning enemies;</l>
<l n="tr">And Turnus views the Trojans in array,</l>
<l n="tr">And hears  th'  approaching horses proudly neigh.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon had their hosts in bloody battle join'd;</l>
<l n="tr">But westward to the sea the sun declin'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Intrench'd before the town both armies lie,</l>
<l n="tr">While Night with sable wings involves the sky.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>