<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">All were attentive to the godlike man,</l>
<l n="tr">When from his lofty couch he thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">Great queen, what you command me to relate</l>
<l n="tr">Renews the sad remembrance of our fate:</l>
<l n="tr">An empire from its old foundations rent,</l>
<l n="tr">And ev'ry woe the Trojans underwent;</l>
<l n="tr">A peopled city made a desart place;</l>
<l n="tr">All that I saw, and part of which I was:</l>
<l n="tr">Not ev'n the hardest of our foes could hear,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor stern Ulysses tell without a tear.</l>
<l n="tr">And now the latter watch of wasting night,</l>
<l n="tr">And setting stars, to kindly rest invite;</l>
<l n="tr">But, since you take such int'rest in our woe,</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s disastrous end desire to know,</l>
<l n="tr">I will restrain my tears, and briefly tell</l>
<l n="tr">What in our last and fatal night befell.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="13" unit="card"/>By destiny compell'd, and in despair,</l>
<l n="tr">The Greeks grew weary of the tedious war,</l>
<l n="tr">And by Minerva's aid a fabric rear'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Which like a steed of monstrous height appear'd:</l>
<l n="tr">The sides were plank'd with pine; they feign'd it made</l>
<l n="tr">For their return, and this the vow they paid.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus they pretend, but in the hollow side</l>
<l n="tr">Selected numbers of their soldiers hide:</l>
<l n="tr">With inward arms the dire machine they load,</l>
<l n="tr">And iron bowels stuff the dark abode.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="21" unit="card"/>In sight of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> lies <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos" authname="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>, an isle</l>
<l n="tr">(While Fortune did on Priam's empire smile)</l>
<l n="tr">Renown'd for wealth; but, since, a faithless bay,</l>
<l n="tr">Where ships expos'd to wind and weather lay.</l>
<l n="tr">There was their fleet conceal'd. We thought, for <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">Their sails were hoisted, and our fears release.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans, coop'd within their walls so long,</l>
<l n="tr">Unbar their gates, and issue in a throng,</l>
<l n="tr">Like swarming bees, and with delight survey</l>
<l n="tr">The camp deserted, where the Grecians lay:</l>
<l n="tr">The quarters of the sev'ral chiefs they show'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Here Phoenix, here Achilles, made abode;</l>
<l n="tr">Here join'd the battles; there the navy rode.</l>
<l n="tr">Part on the pile their wond'ring eyes employ:</l>
<l n="tr">The pile by Pallas rais'd to ruin <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">Thymoetes first ('t is doubtful whether hir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Or so the Trojan destiny requir'd)</l>
<l n="tr">Mov'd that the ramparts might be broken down,</l>
<l n="tr">To lodge the monster fabric in the town.</l>
<l n="tr">But Capys, and the rest of sounder mind,</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal present to the flames designed,</l>
<l n="tr">Or to the wat'ry deep; at least to bore</l>
<l n="tr">The hollow sides, and hidden frauds explore.</l>
<l n="tr">The giddy vulgar, as their fancies guide,</l>
<l n="tr">With noise say nothing, and in parts divide.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="40" unit="card"/>Laocoon, follow'd by a num'rous crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">Ran from the fort, and cried, from far, aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">‘O wretched countrymen! what fury reigns?</l>
<l n="tr">What more than madness has possess'd your brains?</l>
<l n="tr">Think you the Grecians from your coasts are gone?</l>
<l n="tr">And are Ulysses' arts no better known?</l>
<l n="tr">This hollow fabric either must inclose,</l>
<l n="tr">Within its blind recess, our secret foes;</l>
<l n="tr">Or 't is an engine rais'd above the town,</l>
<l n="tr">T' o'erlook the walls, and then to batter down.</l>
<l n="tr">Somewhat is sure design'd, by fraud or force:</l>
<l n="tr">Trust not their presents, nor admit the horse.’</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, against the steed he threw</l>
<l n="tr">His forceful spear, which, hissing as flew,</l>
<l n="tr">Pierc'd thro' the yielding planks of jointed wood,</l>
<l n="tr">And trembling in the hollow belly stood.</l>
<l n="tr">The sides, transpierc'd, return a rattling sound,</l>
<l n="tr">And groans of Greeks inclos'd come issuing thro' the wound</l>
<l n="tr">And, had not Heav'n the fall of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Or had not men been fated to be blind,</l>
<l n="tr">Enough was said and done t'inspire a better mind.</l>
<l n="tr">Then had our lances pierc'd the treach'rous wood,</l>
<l n="tr">And Ilian tow'rs and Priam's empire stood.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="57" unit="card"/>Meantime, with shouts, the Trojan shepherds bring</l>
<l n="tr">A captive Greek, in bands, before the king;</l>
<l n="tr">Taken to take; who made himself their prey,</l>
<l n="tr">T' impose on their belief, and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> betray;</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd on his aim, and obstinately bent</l>
<l n="tr">To die undaunted, or to circumvent.</l>
<l n="tr">About the captive, tides of Trojans flow;</l>
<l n="tr">All press to see, and some insult the foe.</l>
<l n="tr">Now hear how well the Greeks their wiles disguis'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Behold a nation in a man compris'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Trembling the miscreant stood, unarm'd and bound;</l>
<l n="tr">He star'd, and roll'd his haggard eyes around,</l>
<l n="tr">Then said: ‘Alas! what earth remains, what sea</l>
<l n="tr">Is open to receive unhappy me?</l>
<l n="tr">What fate a wretched fugitive attends,</l>
<l n="tr">Scorn'd by my foes, abandon'd by my friends?’</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and sigh'd, and cast a rueful eye:</l>
<l n="tr">Our pity kindles, and our passions die.</l>
<l n="tr">We cheer youth to make his own defense,</l>
<l n="tr">And freely tell us what he was, and whence:</l>
<l n="tr">What news he could impart, we long to know,</l>
<l n="tr">And what to credit from a captive foe.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>His fear at length dismiss'd, he said:<milestone ed="p" n="77" unit="card"/>‘Whate'er</l>
<l n="tr">My fate ordains, my words shall be sincere:</l>
<l n="tr">I neither can nor dare my birth disclaim;</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> is my country, Sinon is my name.</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' plung'd by Fortune's pow'r in misery,</l>
<l n="tr">'T is not in Fortune's pow'r to make me lie.</l>
<l n="tr">If any chance has hither brought the name</l>
<l n="tr">Of Palamedes, not unknown to fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Who suffer'd from the malice of the times,</l>
<l n="tr">Accus'd and sentenc'd for pretended crimes,</l>
<l n="tr">Because these fatal wars he would prevent;</l>
<l n="tr">Whose death the wretched Greeks too late lament—</l>
<l n="tr">Me, then a boy, my father, poor and bare</l>
<l n="tr">Of other means, committed to his care,</l>
<l n="tr">His kinsman and companion in the war.</l>
<l n="tr">While Fortune favor'd, while his arms support</l>
<l n="tr">The cause, and rul'd the counsels, of the court,</l>
<l n="tr">I made some figure there; nor was my name</l>
<l n="tr">Obscure, nor I without my share of fame.</l>
<l n="tr">But when <persName>Ulysses</persName>, with fallacious arts,</l>
<l n="tr">Had made impression in the people's hearts,</l>
<l n="tr">And forg'd a treason in my patron's name</l>
<l n="tr">(I speak of things too far divulg'd by fame),</l>
<l n="tr">My kinsman fell. Then I, without support,</l>
<l n="tr">In private mourn'd his loss, and left the court.</l>
<l n="tr">Mad as I was, I could not bear his fate</l>
<l n="tr">With silent grief, but loudly blam'd the state,</l>
<l n="tr">And curs'd the direful author of my woes.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was told again; and hence my ruin rose.</l>
<l n="tr">I threaten'd, if indulgent Heav'n once more</l>
<l n="tr">Would land me safely on my native shore,</l>
<l n="tr">His death with double vengeance to restore.</l>
<l n="tr">This mov'd the murderer's hate; and soon ensued</l>
<l n="tr">Th' effects of malice from a man so proud.</l>
<l n="tr">Ambiguous rumors thro' the camp he spread,</l>
<l n="tr">And sought, by treason, my devoted head;</l>
<l n="tr">New crimes invented; left unturn'd no stone,</l>
<l n="tr">To make my guilt appear, and hide his own;</l>
<l n="tr">Till Calchas was by force and threat'ning wrought—</l>
<l n="tr">But why—why dwell I on that anxious thought?</l>
<l n="tr">If on my nation just revenge you seek,</l>
<l n="tr">And 't is t' appear a foe, t' appear a Greek;</l>
<l n="tr">Already you my name and country know;</l>
<l n="tr">Assuage your thirst of blood, and strike the blow:</l>
<l n="tr">My death will both the kingly brothers please,</l>
<l n="tr">And set insatiate Ithacus at ease.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="card"/>This fair unfinish'd tale, these broken starts,</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd expectations in our longing hearts:</l>
<l n="tr">Unknowing as we were in Grecian arts.</l>
<l n="tr">His former trembling once again renew'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With acted fear, the villain thus pursued:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>‘Long had the Grecians (tir'd with fruitless care,</l>
<l n="tr">And wearied with an unsuccessful war)</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd to raise the siege, and leave the town;</l>
<l n="tr">And, had the gods permitted, they had gone;</l>
<l n="tr">But oft the wintry seas and southern winds</l>
<l n="tr">Withstood their passage home, and chang'd their minds.</l>
<l n="tr">Portents and prodigies their souls amaz'd;</l>
<l n="tr">But most, when this stupendous pile was rais'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Then flaming meteors, hung in air, were seen,</l>
<l n="tr">And thunders rattled thro' a sky serene.</l>
<l n="tr">Dismay'd, and fearful of some dire event,</l>
<l n="tr">Eurypylus T' enquire their fate was sent.</l>
<l n="tr">He from the gods this dreadful answer brought:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“O Grecians, when the Trojan shores you sought,</l>
<l n="tr">Your passage with a virgin's blood was bought:</l>
<l n="tr">So must your safe return be bought again,</l>
<l n="tr">And Grecian blood once more atone the main.”</l>
<l n="tr">The spreading rumor round the people ran;</l>
<l n="tr">All fear'd, and each believ'd himself the man.</l>
<l n="tr">Ulysses took  th'  advantage of their fright;</l>
<l n="tr">Call'd Calchas, and produc'd in open sight:</l>
<l n="tr">Then bade him name the wretch, ordain'd by fate</l>
<l n="tr">The public victim, to redeem the state.</l>
<l n="tr">Already some presag'd the dire event,</l>
<l n="tr">And saw what sacrifice Ulysses meant.</l>
<l n="tr">For twice five days the good old seer withstood</l>
<l n="tr">Th' intended treason, and was dumb to blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Till, tir'd, with endless clamors and pursuit</l>
<l n="tr">Of Ithacus, he stood no longer mute;</l>
<l n="tr">But, as it was agreed, pronounc'd that I</l>
<l n="tr">Was destin'd by the wrathful gods to die.</l>
<l n="tr">All prais'd the sentence, pleas'd the storm should fall</l>
<l n="tr">On one alone, whose fury threaten'd all.</l>
<l n="tr">The dismal day was come; the priests prepare</l>
<l n="tr">Their leaven'd cakes, and fillets for my hair.</l>
<l n="tr">I follow'd nature's laws, and must avow</l>
<l n="tr">I broke my bonds and fled the fatal blow.</l>
<l n="tr">Hid in a weedy lake all night I lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Secure of safety when they sail'd away.</l>
<l n="tr">But now what further hopes for me remain,</l>
<l n="tr">To see my friends, or native soil, again;</l>
<l n="tr">My tender infants, or my careful sire,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom they returning will to death require;</l>
<l n="tr">Will perpetrate on them their first design,</l>
<l n="tr">And take the forfeit of their heads for mine?</l>
<l n="tr">Which, O! if pity mortal minds can move,</l>
<l n="tr">If there be faith below, or gods above,</l>
<l n="tr">If innocence and truth can claim desert,</l>
<l n="tr">Ye Trojans, from an injur'd wretch avert.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="145" unit="card"/>False tears true pity move; the king commands</l>
<l n="tr">To loose his fetters, and unbind his hands:</l>
<l n="tr">Then adds these friendly words: ‘Dismiss thy fears;</l>
<l n="tr">Forget the Greeks; be mine as thou wert theirs.</l>
<l n="tr">But truly tell, was it for force or guile,</l>
<l n="tr">Or some religious end, you rais'd the pile?’</l>
<l n="tr">Thus said the king. He, full of fraudful arts,</l>
<l n="tr">This well-invented tale for truth imparts:</l>
<l n="tr">‘Ye lamps of heav'n!’ he said, and lifted high</l>
<l n="tr">His hands now free, ‘thou venerable sky!</l>
<l n="tr">Inviolable pow'rs, ador'd with dread!</l>
<l n="tr">Ye fatal fillets, that once bound this head!</l>
<l n="tr">Ye sacred altars, from whose flames I fled!</l>
<l n="tr">Be all of you adjur'd; and grant I may,</l>
<l n="tr">Without a crime,  th'  ungrateful Greeks betray,</l>
<l n="tr">Reveal the secrets of the guilty state,</l>
<l n="tr">And justly punish whom I justly hate!</l>
<l n="tr">But you, O king, preserve the faith you gave,</l>
<l n="tr">If I, to save myself, your empire save.</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian hopes, and all  th'  attempts they made,</l>
<l n="tr">Were only founded on <persName>Minerva</persName>'s aid.</l>
<l n="tr">But from the time when impious Diomede,</l>
<l n="tr">And false <persName>Ulysses</persName>, that inventive head,</l>
<l n="tr">Her fatal image from the temple drew,</l>
<l n="tr">The sleeping guardians of the castle slew,</l>
<l n="tr">Her virgin statue with their bloody hands</l>
<l n="tr">Polluted, and profan'd her holy bands;</l>
<l n="tr">From thence the tide of fortune left their shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And ebb'd much faster than it flow'd before:</l>
<l n="tr">Their courage languish'd, as their hopes decay'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And <persName>Pallas</persName>, now averse, refus'd her aid.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did the goddess doubtfully declare</l>
<l n="tr">Her alter'd mind and alienated care.</l>
<l n="tr">When first her fatal image touch'd the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">She sternly cast her glaring eyes around,</l>
<l n="tr">That sparkled as they roll'd, and seem'd to threat:</l>
<l n="tr">Her heav'nly limbs distill'd a briny sweat.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice from the ground she leap'd, was seen to wield</l>
<l n="tr">Her brandish'd lance, and shake her horrid shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Calchas bade our host for flight</l>
<l n="tr">And hope no conquest from the tedious war,</l>
<l n="tr">Till first they sail'd for <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>; with pray'rs besought</l>
<l n="tr">Her injur'd pow'r, and better omens brought.</l>
<l n="tr">And now their navy plows the wat'ry main,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet soon expect it on your shores again,</l>
<l n="tr">With <persName>Pallas</persName> pleas'd; as Calchas did ordain.</l>
<l n="tr">But first, to reconcile the blue-ey'd maid</l>
<l n="tr">For her stol'n statue and her tow'r betray'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Warn'd by the seer, to her offended name</l>
<l n="tr">We rais'd and dedicate this wondrous frame,</l>
<l n="tr">So lofty, lest thro' your forbidden gates</l>
<l n="tr">It pass, and intercept our better fates:</l>
<l n="tr">For, once admitted there, our hopes are lost;</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> may then a new Palladium boast;</l>
<l n="tr">For so religion and the gods ordain,</l>
<l n="tr">That, if you violate with hands profane</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Minerva</persName>'s gift, your town in flames shall burn,</l>
<l n="tr">(Which omen, O ye gods, on Graecia turn!)</l>
<l n="tr">But if it climb, with your assisting hands,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan walls, and in the city stands;</l>
<l n="tr">Then <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> shall <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> burn,</l>
<l n="tr">And the reverse of fate on us return.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="195" unit="card"/>With such deceits he gain'd their easy hearts,</l>
<l n="tr">Too prone to credit his perfidious arts.</l>
<l n="tr">What Diomede, nor Thetis' greater son,</l>
<l n="tr">A thousand ships, nor ten years' siege, had done—</l>
<l n="tr">False tears and fawning words the city won.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A greater omen, and of worse portent,</l>
<l n="tr">Did our unwary minds with fear torment,</l>
<l n="tr">Concurring to produce the dire event.</l>
<l n="tr">Laocoon, <persName>Neptune</persName>'s priest by lot that year,</l>
<l n="tr">With solemn pomp then sacrific'd a steer;</l>
<l n="tr">When, dreadful to behold, from sea we spied</l>
<l n="tr">Two serpents, rank'd abreast, the seas divide,</l>
<l n="tr">And smoothly sweep along the swelling tide.</l>
<l n="tr">Their flaming crests above the waves they show;</l>
<l n="tr">Their bellies seem to burn the seas below;</l>
<l n="tr">Their speckled tails advance to steer their course,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the sounding shore the flying billows force.</l>
<l n="tr">And now the strand, and now the plain they held;</l>
<l n="tr">Their ardent eyes with bloody streaks were fill'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Their nimble tongues they brandish'd as they came,</l>
<l n="tr">And lick'd their hissing jaws, that sputter'd flame.</l>
<l n="tr">We fled amaz'd; their destin'd way they take,</l>
<l n="tr">And to Laocoon and his children make;</l>
<l n="tr">And first around the tender boys they wind,</l>
<l n="tr">Then with their sharpen'd fangs their limbs and bodies grind.</l>
<l n="tr">The wretched father, running to their aid</l>
<l n="tr">With pious haste, but vain, they next invade;</l>
<l n="tr">Twice round his waist their winding volumes roll'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And twice about his gasping throat they fold.</l>
<l n="tr">The priest thus doubly chok'd, their crests divide,</l>
<l n="tr">And tow'ring o'er his head in triumph ride.</l>
<l n="tr">With both his hands he labors at the knots;</l>
<l n="tr">His holy fillets the blue venom blots;</l>
<l n="tr">His roaring fills the flitting air around.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, when an ox receives a glancing wound,</l>
<l n="tr">He breaks his bands, the fatal altar flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And with loud bellowings breaks the yielding skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Their tasks perform'd, the serpents quit their prey,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the tow'r of <persName>Pallas</persName> make their way:</l>
<l n="tr">Couch'd at her feet, they lie protected there</l>
<l n="tr">By her large buckler and protended spear.</l>
<l n="tr">Amazement seizes all; the gen'ral cry</l>
<l n="tr">Proclaims Laocoon justly doom'd to die,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose hand the will of <persName>Pallas</persName> had withstood,</l>
<l n="tr">And dared to violate the sacred wood.</l>
<l n="tr">All vote T' admit the steed, that vows be paid</l>
<l n="tr">And incense offer'd to  th'  offended maid.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="234" unit="card"/>A spacious breach is made; the town lies bare;</l>
<l n="tr">Some hoisting-levers, some the wheels prepare</l>
<l n="tr">And fasten to the horse's feet; the rest</l>
<l n="tr">With cables haul along  th'  unwieldly beast.</l>
<l n="tr">Each on his fellow for assistance calls;</l>
<l n="tr">At length the fatal fabric mounts the walls,</l>
<l n="tr">Big with destruction. Boys with chaplets crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And choirs of virgins, sing and dance around.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus rais'd aloft, and then descending down,</l>
<l n="tr">It enters o'er our heads, and threats the town.</l>
<l n="tr">O sacred city, built by hands divine!</l>
<l n="tr">O valiant heroes of the Trojan line!</l>
<l n="tr">Four times he struck: as oft the clashing sound</l>
<l n="tr">Of arms was heard, and inward groans rebound.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, mad with zeal, and blinded with our fate,</l>
<l n="tr">We haul along the horse in solemn state;</l>
<l n="tr">Then place the dire portent within the tow'r.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Cassandra</persName> cried, and curs'd  th'  unhappy hour;</l>
<l n="tr">Foretold our fate; but, by the god's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">All heard, and none believ'd the prophecy.</l>
<l n="tr">With branches we the fanes adorn, and waste,</l>
<l n="tr">In jollity, the day ordain'd to be the last.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="250" unit="card"/>Meantime the rapid heav'ns roll'd down the light,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the shaded ocean rush'd the night;</l>
<l n="tr">Our men, secure, nor guards nor sentries held,</l>
<l n="tr">But easy sleep their weary limbs compell'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecians had embark'd their naval pow'rs</l>
<l n="tr">From Tenedos, and sought our well-known shores,</l>
<l n="tr">Safe under covert of the silent night,</l>
<l n="tr">And guided by  th'  imperial galley's light;</l>
<l n="tr">When Sinon, favor'd by the partial gods,</l>
<l n="tr">Unlock'd the horse, and op'd his dark abodes;</l>
<l n="tr">Restor'd to vital air our hidden foes,</l>
<l n="tr">Who joyful from their long confinement rose.</l>
<l n="tr">Tysander bold, and Sthenelus their guide,</l>
<l n="tr">And dire <persName>Ulysses</persName> down the cable slide:</l>
<l n="tr">Then Thoas, Athamas, and Pyrrhus haste;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor was the Podalirian hero last,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor injur'd Menelaus, nor the fam'd</l>
<l n="tr">Epeus, who the fatal engine fram'd.</l>
<l n="tr">A nameless crowd succeed; their forces join</l>
<l n="tr">T' invade the town, oppress'd with sleep and wine.</l>
<l n="tr">Those few they find awake first meet their fate;</l>
<l n="tr">Then to their fellows they unbar the gate.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="268" unit="card"/>'T was in the dead of night, when sleep repairs</l>
<l n="tr">Our bodies worn with toils, our minds with cares,</l>
<l n="tr">When <persName>Hector</persName>'s ghost before my sight appears:</l>
<l n="tr">A bloody shroud he seem'd, and bath'd in tears;</l>
<l n="tr">Such as he was, when, by Pelides slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Thessalian coursers dragg'd him o'er the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Swoln were his feet, as when the thongs were thrust</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the bor'd holes; his body black with dust;</l>
<l n="tr">Unlike that Hector who return'd from toils</l>
<l n="tr">Of war, triumphant, in Aeacian spoils,</l>
<l n="tr">Or him who made the fainting Greeks retire,</l>
<l n="tr">And launch'd against their navy Phrygian fire.</l>
<l n="tr">His hair and beard stood stiffen'd with his gore;</l>
<l n="tr">And all the wounds he for his country bore</l>
<l n="tr">Now stream'd afresh, and with new purple ran.</l>
<l n="tr">I wept to see the visionary man,</l>
<l n="tr">And, while my trance continued, thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">‘O light of Trojans, and support of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Thy father's champion, and thy country's joy!</l>
<l n="tr">O, long expected by thy friends! from whence</l>
<l n="tr">Art thou so late return'd for our defense?</l>
<l n="tr">Do we behold thee, wearied as we are</l>
<l n="tr">With length of labors, and with toils of war?</l>
<l n="tr">After so many fun'rals of thy own</l>
<l n="tr">Art thou restor'd to thy declining town?</l>
<l n="tr">But say, what wounds are these? What new disgrace</l>
<l n="tr">Deforms the manly features of thy face?’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To this the specter no reply did frame,</l>
<l n="tr">But answer'd to the cause for which he came,</l>
<l n="tr">And, groaning from the bottom of his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">This warning in these mournful words express'd:</l>
<l n="tr">‘O goddess-born! escape, by timely flight,</l>
<l n="tr">The flames and horrors of this fatal night.</l>
<l n="tr">The foes already have possess'd the wall;</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> nods from high, and totters to her fall.</l>
<l n="tr">Enough is paid to Priam's royal name,</l>
<l n="tr">More than enough to duty and to fame.</l>
<l n="tr">If by a mortal hand my father's throne</l>
<l n="tr">Could be defended, 't was by mine alone.</l>
<l n="tr">Now <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> to thee commends her future state,</l>
<l n="tr">And gives her gods companions of thy fate:</l>
<l n="tr">From their assistance walls expect,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, wand'ring long, at last thou shalt erect.’</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and brought me, from their blest abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">The venerable statues of the gods,</l>
<l n="tr">With ancient <persName>Vesta</persName> from the sacred choir,</l>
<l n="tr">The wreaths and relics of  th'  immortal fire.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="298" unit="card"/>Now peals of shouts come thund'ring from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Cries, threats, and loud laments, and mingled war:</l>
<l n="tr">The noise approaches, tho' our palace stood</l>
<l n="tr">Aloof from streets, encompass'd with a wood.</l>
<l n="tr">Louder, and yet more loud, I hear  th'  alarms</l>
<l n="tr">Of human cries distinct, and clashing arms.</l>
<l n="tr">Fear broke my slumbers; I no longer stay,</l>
<l n="tr">But mount the terrace, thence the town survey,</l>
<l n="tr">And hearken what the frightful sounds convey.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, when a flood of fire by wind is borne,</l>
<l n="tr">Crackling it rolls, and mows the standing corn;</l>
<l n="tr">Or deluges, descending on the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">Sweep o'er the yellow year, destroy the pains</l>
<l n="tr">Of lab'ring oxen and the peasant's gains;</l>
<l n="tr">Unroot the forest oaks, and bear away</l>
<l n="tr">Flocks, folds, and trees, and undistinguish'd prey:</l>
<l n="tr">The shepherd climbs the cliff, and sees from far</l>
<l n="tr">The wasteful ravage of the wat'ry war.</l>
<l n="tr">Then <persName>Hector</persName>'s faith was manifestly clear'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And Grecian frauds in open light appear'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The palace of Deiphobus ascends</l>
<l n="tr">In smoky flames, and catches on his friends.</l>
<l n="tr">Ucalegon burns next: the seas are bright</l>
<l n="tr">With splendor not their own, and shine with Trojan light.</l>
<l n="tr">New clamors and new clangors now arise,</l>
<l n="tr">The sound of trumpets mix'd with fighting cries.</l>
<l n="tr">With frenzy seiz'd, I run to meet  th'  alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd on death, resolv'd to die in arms,</l>
<l n="tr">But first to gather friends, with them T' oppose</l>
<l n="tr">(If fortune favor'd) and repel the foes;</l>
<l n="tr">Spurr'd by my courage, by my country fir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With sense of honor and revenge inspir'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="318" unit="card"/>Pantheus, Apollo's priest, a sacred name,</l>
<l n="tr">Had scap'd the Grecian swords, and pass'd the flame:</l>
<l n="tr">With relics loaden. to my doors he fled,</l>
<l n="tr">And by the hand his tender grandson led.</l>
<l n="tr">‘What hope, O Pantheus? whither can we run?</l>
<l n="tr">Where make a stand? and what may yet be done?’</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had I said, when Pantheus, with a groan:</l>
<l n="tr">‘<placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> is no more, and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> was a town!</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal day,  th'  appointed hour, is come,</l>
<l n="tr">When wrathful Jove's irrevocable doom</l>
<l n="tr">Transfers the Trojan state to Grecian hands.</l>
<l n="tr">The fire consumes the town, the foe commands;</l>
<l n="tr">And armed hosts, an unexpected force,</l>
<l n="tr">Break from the bowels of the fatal horse.</l>
<l n="tr">Within the gates, proud Sinon throws about</l>
<l n="tr">The flames; and foes for entrance press without,</l>
<l n="tr">With thousand others, whom I fear to name,</l>
<l n="tr">More than from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> or <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> came.</l>
<l n="tr">To sev'ral posts their parties they divide;</l>
<l n="tr">Some block the narrow streets, some scour the wide:</l>
<l n="tr">The bold they kill,  th'  unwary they surprise;</l>
<l n="tr">Who fights finds death, and death finds him who flies.</l>
<l n="tr">The warders of the gate but scarce maintain</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unequal combat, and resist in vain.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I heard; and Heav'n, that well-born souls inspires,</l>
<l n="tr">Prompts me thro' lifted swords and rising fires</l>
<l n="tr">To run where clashing arms and clamor calls,</l>
<l n="tr">And rush undaunted to defend the walls.</l>
<l n="tr">Ripheus and Iph'itus by my side engage,</l>
<l n="tr">For valor one renown'd, and one for age.</l>
<l n="tr">Dymas and Hypanis by moonlight knew</l>
<l n="tr">My motions and my mien, and to my party drew;</l>
<l n="tr">With young Coroebus, who by love was led</l>
<l n="tr">To win renown and fair Cassandra's bed,</l>
<l n="tr">And lately brought his troops to Priam's aid,</l>
<l n="tr">Forewarn'd in vain by the prophetic maid.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="347" unit="card"/>Whom when I saw resolv'd in arms to fall,</l>
<l n="tr">And that one spirit animated all:</l>
<l n="tr">‘Brave souls!’ said I, ‘but brave, alas! in vain—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Come, finish what our cruel fates ordain.</l>
<l n="tr">You see the desp'rate state of our affairs,</l>
<l n="tr">And heav'n's protecting pow'rs are deaf to pray'rs.</l>
<l n="tr">The passive gods behold the Greeks defile</l>
<l n="tr">Their temples, and abandon to the spoil</l>
<l n="tr">Their own abodes: we, feeble few, conspire</l>
<l n="tr">To save a sinking town, involv'd in fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Then let us fall, but fall amidst our foes:</l>
<l n="tr">Despair of life the means of living shows.’</l>
<l n="tr">So bold a speech incourag'd their desire</l>
<l n="tr">Of death, and added fuel to their fire.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As hungry wolves, with raging appetite,</l>
<l n="tr">Scour thro' the fields, nor fear the stormy nighT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Their whelps at home expect the promis'd food,</l>
<l n="tr">And long to temper their dry chaps in blood—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">So rush'd we forth at once; resolv'd to die,</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd, in death, the last extremes to try.</l>
<l n="tr">We leave the narrow lanes behind, and dare</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unequal combat in the public square:</l>
<l n="tr">Night was our friend; our leader was despair.</l>
<l n="tr">What tongue can tell the slaughter of that night?</l>
<l n="tr">What eyes can weep the sorrows and affright?</l>
<l n="tr">An ancient and imperial city falls:</l>
<l n="tr">The streets are fill'd with frequent funerals;</l>
<l n="tr">Houses and holy temples float in blood,</l>
<l n="tr">And hostile nations make a common flood.</l>
<l n="tr">Not only Trojans fall; but, in their turn,</l>
<l n="tr">The vanquish'd triumph, and the victors mourn.</l>
<l n="tr">Ours take new courage from despair and night:</l>
<l n="tr">Confus'd the fortune is, confus'd the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">All parts resound with tumults, plaints, and fears;</l>
<l n="tr">And grisly Death in sundry shapes appears.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="370" unit="card"/>Androgeos fell among us, with his band,</l>
<l n="tr">Who thought us Grecians newly come to land.</l>
<l n="tr">‘From whence,’ said he, ‘my friends, this long delay?</l>
<l n="tr">You loiter, while the spoils are borne away:</l>
<l n="tr">Our ships are laden with the Trojan store;</l>
<l n="tr">And you, like truants, come too late ashore.’</l>
<l n="tr">He said, but soon corrected his mistake,</l>
<l n="tr">Found, by the doubtful answers which we make:</l>
<l n="tr">Amaz'd, he would have shunn'd  th'  unequal fight;</l>
<l n="tr">But we, more num'rous, intercept his flight.</l>
<l n="tr">As when some peasant, in a bushy brake,</l>
<l n="tr">Has with unwary footing press'd a snake;</l>
<l n="tr">He starts aside, astonish'd, when he spies</l>
<l n="tr">His rising crest, blue neck, and rolling eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">So from our arms surpris'd Androgeos flies.</l>
<l n="tr">In vain; for him and his we compass'd round,</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd with fear, unknowing of the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And of their lives an easy conquest found.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus Fortune on our first endeavor smil'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Coroebus then, with youthful hopes beguil'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Swoln with success, and a daring mind,</l>
<l n="tr">This new invention fatally design'd.</l>
<l n="tr">‘My friends,’ said he, ‘since Fortune shows the way,</l>
<l n="tr">'T is fit we should  th'  auspicious guide obey.</l>
<l n="tr">For what has she these Grecian arms bestow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">But their destruction, and the Trojans' good?</l>
<l n="tr">Then change we shields, and their devices bear:</l>
<l n="tr">Let fraud supply the want of force in war.</l>
<l n="tr">They find us arms.’ This said, himself he dress'd</l>
<l n="tr">In dead Androgeos' spoils, his upper vest,</l>
<l n="tr">His painted buckler, and his plumy crest.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus Ripheus, Dymas, all the Trojan train,</l>
<l n="tr">Lay down their own attire, and strip the slain.</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd with the Greeks, we go with ill presage,</l>
<l n="tr">Flatter'd with hopes to glut our greedy rage;</l>
<l n="tr">Unknown, assaulting whom we blindly meet,</l>
<l n="tr">And strew with Grecian carcasses the street.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while their straggling parties we defeat,</l>
<l n="tr">Some to the shore and safer ships retreat;</l>
<l n="tr">And some, oppress'd with more ignoble fear,</l>
<l n="tr">Remount the hollow horse, and pant in secret there.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="402" unit="card"/>But, ah! what use of valor can be made,</l>
<l n="tr">When heav'n's propitious pow'rs refuse their aid!</l>
<l n="tr">Behold the royal prophetess, the fair</l>
<l n="tr">Cassandra, dragg'd by her dishevel'd hair,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom not Minerva's shrine, nor sacred bands,</l>
<l n="tr">In safety could protect from sacrilegious hands:</l>
<l n="tr">On heav'n she cast her eyes, she sigh'd, she cried—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">'T was all she could—her tender arms were tied.</l>
<l n="tr">So sad a sight Coroebus could not bear;</l>
<l n="tr">But, fir'd with rage, distracted with despair,</l>
<l n="tr">Amid the barb'rous ravishers he flew:</l>
<l n="tr">Our leader's rash example we pursue.</l>
<l n="tr">But storms of stones, from the proud temple's height,</l>
<l n="tr">Pour down, and on our batter'd helms alight:</l>
<l n="tr">We from our friends receiv'd this fatal blow,</l>
<l n="tr">Who thought us Grecians, as we seem'd in show.</l>
<l n="tr">They aim at the mistaken crests, from high;</l>
<l n="tr">And ours beneath the pond'rous ruin lie.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, mov'd with anger and disdain, to see</l>
<l n="tr">Their troops dispers'd, the royal virgin free,</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecians rally, and their pow'rs unite,</l>
<l n="tr">With fury charge us, and renew the fight.</l>
<l n="tr">The brother kings with Ajax join their force,</l>
<l n="tr">And the whole squadron of Thessalian horse.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus, when the rival winds their quarrel try,</l>
<l n="tr">Contending for the kingdom of the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">South, east, and west, on airy coursers borne;</l>
<l n="tr">The whirlwind gathers, and the woods are torn:</l>
<l n="tr">Then Nereus strikes the deep; the billows rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And, mix'd with ooze and sand, pollute the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">The troops we squander'd first again appear</l>
<l n="tr">From several quarters, and enclose the rear.</l>
<l n="tr">They first observe, and to the rest betray,</l>
<l n="tr">Our diff'rent speech; our borrow'd arms survey.</l>
<l n="tr">Oppress'd with odds, we fall; Coroebus first,</l>
<l n="tr">At Pallas' altar, by Peneleus pierc'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Ripheus follow'd, in  th'  unequal fight;</l>
<l n="tr">Just of his word, observant of the right:</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'n thought not so. Dymas their fate attends,</l>
<l n="tr">With Hypanis, mistaken by their friends.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor, Pantheus, thee, thy miter, nor the bands</l>
<l n="tr">Of awful Phoebus, sav'd from impious hands.</l>
<l n="tr">Ye Trojan flames, your testimony bear,</l>
<l n="tr">What I perform'd, and what I suffer'd there;</l>
<l n="tr">No sword avoiding in the fatal strife,</l>
<l n="tr">Expos'd to death, and prodigal of life;</l>
<l n="tr">Witness, ye heavens! I live not by my fault:</l>
<l n="tr">I strove to have deserv'd the death I sought.</l>
<l n="tr">But, when I could not fight, and would have died,</l>
<l n="tr">Borne off to distance by the growing tide,</l>
<l n="tr">Old Iphitus and I were hurried thence,</l>
<l n="tr">With Pelias wounded, and without defense.</l>
<l n="tr">New clamors from  th'  invested palace ring:</l>
<l n="tr">We run to die, or disengage the king.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="438" unit="card"/>So hot  th'  assault, so high the tumult rose,</l>
<l n="tr">While ours defend, and while the Greeks oppose</l>
<l n="tr">As all the Dardan and Argolic race</l>
<l n="tr">Had been contracted in that narrow space;</l>
<l n="tr">Or as all <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> else were void of fear,</l>
<l n="tr">And tumult, war, and slaughter, only there.</l>
<l n="tr">Their targets in a tortoise cast, the foes,</l>
<l n="tr">Secure advancing, to the turrets rose:</l>
<l n="tr">Some mount the scaling ladders; some, more bold,</l>
<l n="tr">Swerve upwards, and by posts and pillars hold;</l>
<l n="tr">Their left hand gripes their bucklers in  th'  ascent,</l>
<l n="tr">While with their right they seize the battlement.</l>
<l n="tr">From their demolish'd tow'rs the Trojans throw</l>
<l n="tr">Huge heaps of stones, that, falling, crush the foe;</l>
<l n="tr">And heavy beams and rafters from the sides</l>
<l n="tr">(Such arms their last necessity provides)</l>
<l n="tr">And gilded roofs, come tumbling from on high,</l>
<l n="tr">The marks of state and ancient royalty.</l>
<l n="tr">The guards below, fix'd in the pass, attend</l>
<l n="tr">The charge undaunted, and the gate defend.</l>
<l n="tr">Renew'd in courage with recover'd breath,</l>
<l n="tr">A second time we ran to tempt our death,</l>
<l n="tr">To clear the palace from the foe, succeed</l>
<l n="tr">The weary living, and revenge the dead.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="453" unit="card"/>A postern door, yet unobserv'd and free,</l>
<l n="tr">Join'd by the length of a blind gallery,</l>
<l n="tr">To the king's closet led: a way well known</l>
<l n="tr">To Hector's wife, while Priam held the throne,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' which she brought Astyanax, unseen,</l>
<l n="tr">To cheer his grandsire and his grandsire's queen.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' this we pass, and mount the tow'r, from whence</l>
<l n="tr">With unavailing arms the Trojans make defense.</l>
<l n="tr">From this the trembling king had oft descried</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian camp, and saw their navy ride.</l>
<l n="tr">Beams from its lofty height with swords we hew,</l>
<l n="tr">Then, wrenching with our hands,  th'  assault renew;</l>
<l n="tr">And, where the rafters on the columns meet,</l>
<l n="tr">We push them headlong with our arms and feet.</l>
<l n="tr">The lightning flies not swifter than the fall,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thunder louder than the ruin'd wall:</l>
<l n="tr">Down goes the top at once; the Greeks beneath</l>
<l n="tr">Are piecemeal torn, or pounded into death.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet more succeed, and more to death are sent;</l>
<l n="tr">We cease not from above, nor they below relent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="469" unit="card"/>Before the gate stood Pyrrhus, threat'ning loud,</l>
<l n="tr">With glitt'ring arms conspicuous in the crowd.</l>
<l n="tr">So shines, renew'd in youth, the crested snake,</l>
<l n="tr">Who slept the winter in a thorny brake,</l>
<l n="tr">And, casting off his slough when spring returns,</l>
<l n="tr">Now looks aloft, and with new glory burns;</l>
<l n="tr">Restor'd with poisonous herbs, his ardent sides</l>
<l n="tr">Reflect the sun; and rais'd on spires he rides;</l>
<l n="tr">High o'er the grass, hissing he rolls along,</l>
<l n="tr">And brandishes by fits his forky tongue.</l>
<l n="tr">Proud Periphas, and fierce Automedon,</l>
<l n="tr">His father's charioteer, together run</l>
<l n="tr">To force the gate; the Scyrian infantry</l>
<l n="tr">Rush on in crowds, and the barr'd passage free.</l>
<l n="tr">Ent'ring the court, with shouts the skies they rend;</l>
<l n="tr">And flaming firebrands to the roofs ascend.</l>
<l n="tr">Himself, among the foremost, deals his blows,</l>
<l n="tr">And with his ax repeated strokes bestows</l>
<l n="tr">On the strong doors; then all their shoulders ply,</l>
<l n="tr">Till from the posts the brazen hinges fly.</l>
<l n="tr">He hews apace; the double bars at length</l>
<l n="tr">Yield to his ax and unresisted strength.</l>
<l n="tr">A mighty breach is made: the rooms conceal'd</l>
<l n="tr">Appear, and all the palace is reveal'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The halls of audience, and of public state,</l>
<l n="tr">And where the lonely queen in secret sate.</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd soldiers now by trembling maids are seen,</l>
<l n="tr">With not a door, and scarce a space, between.</l>
<l n="tr">The house is fill'd with loud laments and cries,</l>
<l n="tr">And shrieks of women rend the vaulted skies;</l>
<l n="tr">The fearful matrons run from place to place,</l>
<l n="tr">And kiss the thresholds, and the posts embrace.</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal work inhuman Pyrrhus plies,</l>
<l n="tr">And all his father sparkles in his eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor bars, nor fighting guards, his force sustain:</l>
<l n="tr">The bars are broken, and the guards are slain.</l>
<l n="tr">In rush the Greeks, and all the apartments fill;</l>
<l n="tr">Those few defendants whom they find, they kill.</l>
<l n="tr">Not with so fierce a rage the foaming flood</l>
<l n="tr">Roars, when he finds his rapid course withstood;</l>
<l n="tr">Bears down the dams with unresisted sway,</l>
<l n="tr">And sweeps the cattle and the cots away.</l>
<l n="tr">These eyes beheld him when he march'd between</l>
<l n="tr">The brother kings: I saw  th'  unhappy queen,</l>
<l n="tr">The hundred wives, and where old Priam stood,</l>
<l n="tr">To stain his hallow'd altar with his brood.</l>
<l n="tr">The fifty nuptial beds (such hopes had he,</l>
<l n="tr">So large a promise, of a progeny),</l>
<l n="tr">The posts, of plated gold, and hung with spoils,</l>
<l n="tr">Fell the reward of the proud victor's toils.</l>
<l n="tr">Where'er the raging fire had left a space,</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecians enter and possess the place.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="506" unit="card"/>Perhaps you may of Priam's fate enquire.</l>
<l n="tr">He, when he saw his regal town on fire,</l>
<l n="tr">His ruin'd palace, and his ent'ring foes,</l>
<l n="tr">On ev'ry side inevitable woes,</l>
<l n="tr">In arms, disus'd, invests his limbs, decay'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Like them, with age; a late and useless aid.</l>
<l n="tr">His feeble shoulders scarce the weight sustain;</l>
<l n="tr">Loaded, not arm'd, he creeps along with pain,</l>
<l n="tr">Despairing of success, ambitious to be slain!</l>
<l n="tr">Uncover'd but by heav'n, there stood in view</l>
<l n="tr">An altar; near the hearth a laurel grew,</l>
<l n="tr">Dodder'd with age, whose boughs encompass round</l>
<l n="tr">The household gods, and shade the holy ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Here Hecuba, with all her helpless train</l>
<l n="tr">Of dames, for shelter sought, but sought in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n like a flock of doves along the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Their images they hug, and to their altars fly.</l>
<l n="tr">The Queen, when she beheld her trembling lord,</l>
<l n="tr">And hanging by his side a heavy sword,</l>
<l n="tr">‘What rage,’ she cried, ‘has seiz'd my husband's mind?</l>
<l n="tr">What arms are these, and to what use design'd?</l>
<l n="tr">These times want other aids! Were Hector here,</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n Hector now in vain, like Priam, would appear.</l>
<l n="tr">With us, one common shelter thou shalt find,</l>
<l n="tr">Or in one common fate with us be join'd.’</l>
<l n="tr">She said, and with a last salute embrac'd</l>
<l n="tr">The poor old man, and by the laurel plac'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="526" unit="card"/>Behold! Polites, one of Priam's sons,</l>
<l n="tr">Pursued by Pyrrhus, there for safety runs.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' swords and foes, amaz'd and hurt, he flies</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' empty courts and open galleries.</l>
<l n="tr">Him Pyrrhus, urging with his lance, pursues,</l>
<l n="tr">And often reaches, and his thrusts renews.</l>
<l n="tr">The youth, transfix'd, with lamentable cries,</l>
<l n="tr">Expires before his wretched parent's eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">Whom gasping at his feet when Priam saw,</l>
<l n="tr">The fear of death gave place to nature's law;</l>
<l n="tr">And, shaking more with anger than with age,</l>
<l n="tr">‘The gods,’ said he, ‘requite thy brutal rage!</l>
<l n="tr">As sure they will, barbarian, sure they must,</l>
<l n="tr">If there be gods in heav'n, and gods be jusT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Who tak'st in wrongs an insolent delight;</l>
<l n="tr">With a son's death T' infect a father's sight.</l>
<l n="tr">Not he, whom thou and lying fame conspire</l>
<l n="tr">To call thee his—not he, thy vaunted sire,</l>
<l n="tr">Thus us'd my wretched age: the gods he fear'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The laws of nature and of nations heard.</l>
<l n="tr">He cheer'd my sorrows, and, for sums of gold,</l>
<l n="tr">The bloodless carcass of my Hector sold;</l>
<l n="tr">Pitied the woes a parent underwent,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent me back in safety from his tent.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This said, his feeble hand a javelin threw,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, flutt'ring, seem'd to loiter as it flew:</l>
<l n="tr">Just, and but barely, to the mark it held,</l>
<l n="tr">And faintly tinkled on the brazen shield.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Pyrrhus thus: ‘Go thou from me to fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And to my father my foul deeds relate.</l>
<l n="tr">Now die!’ With that he dragg'd the trembling sire,</l>
<l n="tr">Slidd'ring thro' clotter'd blood and holy mire,</l>
<l n="tr">(The mingled paste his murder'd son had made,)</l>
<l n="tr">Haul'd from beneath the violated shade,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the sacred pile the royal victim laid.</l>
<l n="tr">His right hand held his bloody falchion bare,</l>
<l n="tr">His left he twisted in his hoary hair;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, with a speeding thrust, his heart he found:</l>
<l n="tr">The lukewarm blood came rushing thro' the wound,</l>
<l n="tr">And sanguine streams distain'd the sacred ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus Priam fell, and shar'd one common fate</l>
<l n="tr">With <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> in ashes, and his ruin'd state:</l>
<l n="tr">He, who the scepter of all <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> sway'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom monarchs like domestic slaves obey'd.</l>
<l n="tr">On the bleak shore now lies  th'  abandon'd king,</l>
<l n="tr">A headless carcass, and a nameless thing.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="559" unit="card"/>Then, not before, I felt my cruddled blood</l>
<l n="tr">Congeal with fear, my hair with horror stood:</l>
<l n="tr">My father's image fill'd my pious mind,</l>
<l n="tr">Lest equal years might equal fortune find.</l>
<l n="tr">Again I thought on my forsaken wife,</l>
<l n="tr">And trembled for my son's abandon'd life.</l>
<l n="tr">I look'd about, but found myself alone,</l>
<l n="tr">Deserted at my need! My friends were gone.</l>
<l n="tr">Some spent with toil, some with despair oppress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Leap'd headlong from the heights; the flames consum'd the rest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="567" unit="card"/>Thus, wand'ring in my way, without a guide,</l>
<l n="tr">The graceless Helen in the porch I spied</l>
<l n="tr">Of Vesta's temple; there she lurk'd alone;</l>
<l n="tr">Muffled she sate, and, what she could, unknown:</l>
<l n="tr">But, by the flames that cast their blaze around,</l>
<l n="tr">That common bane of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> I found.</l>
<l n="tr">For <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> burnt, she dreads the Trojan sword;</l>
<l n="tr">More dreads the vengeance of her injur'd lord;</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n by those gods who refug'd her abhorr'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Trembling with rage, the strumpet I regard,</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd to give her guilt the due reward:</l>
<l n="tr">‘Shall she triumphant sail before the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">And leave in flames unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> behind?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall she her kingdom and her friends review,</l>
<l n="tr">In state attended with a captive crew,</l>
<l n="tr">While unreveng'd the good old Priam falls,</l>
<l n="tr">And Grecian fires consume the Trojan walls?</l>
<l n="tr">For this the Phrygian fields and Xanthian flood</l>
<l n="tr">Were swell'd with bodies, and were drunk with blood?</l>
<l n="tr">'T is true, a soldier can small honor gain,</l>
<l n="tr">And boast no conquest, from a woman slain:</l>
<l n="tr">Yet shall the fact not pass without applause,</l>
<l n="tr">Of vengeance taken in so just a cause;</l>
<l n="tr">The punish'd crime shall set my soul at ease,</l>
<l n="tr">And murm'ring manes of my friends appease.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="588" unit="card"/>Thus while I rave, a gleam of pleasing light</l>
<l n="tr">Spread o'er the place; and, shining heav'nly bright,</l>
<l n="tr">My mother stood reveal'd before my sight</l>
<l n="tr">Never so radiant did her eyes appear;</l>
<l n="tr">Not her own star confess'd a light so clear:</l>
<l n="tr">Great in her charms, as when on gods above</l>
<l n="tr">She looks, and breathes herself into their love.</l>
<l n="tr">She held my hand, the destin'd blow to break;</l>
<l n="tr">Then from her rosy lips began to speak:</l>
<l n="tr">‘My son, from whence this madness, this neglect</l>
<l n="tr">Of my commands, and those whom I protect?</l>
<l n="tr">Why this unmanly rage? Recall to mind</l>
<l n="tr">Whom you forsake, what pledges leave behind.</l>
<l n="tr">Look if your helpless father yet survive,</l>
<l n="tr">Or if Ascanius or Creusa live.</l>
<l n="tr">Around your house the greedy Grecians err;</l>
<l n="tr">And these had perish'd in the nightly war,</l>
<l n="tr">But for my presence and protecting care.</l>
<l n="tr">Not Helen's face, nor <persName>Paris</persName>, was in fault;</l>
<l n="tr">But by the gods was this destruction brought.</l>
<l n="tr">Now cast your eyes around, while I dissolve</l>
<l n="tr">The mists and films that mortal eyes involve,</l>
<l n="tr">Purge from your sight the dross, and make you see</l>
<l n="tr">The shape of each avenging deity.</l>
<l n="tr">Enlighten'd thus, my just commands fulfil,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor fear obedience to your mother's will.</l>
<l n="tr">Where yon disorder'd heap of ruin lies,</l>
<l n="tr">Stones rent from stones; where clouds of dust arise—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Amid that smother Neptune holds his place,</l>
<l n="tr">Below the wall's foundation drives his mace,</l>
<l n="tr">And heaves the building from the solid base.</l>
<l n="tr">Look where, in arms, imperial Juno stands</l>
<l n="tr">Full in the Scaean gate, with loud commands,</l>
<l n="tr">Urging on shore the tardy Grecian bands.</l>
<l n="tr">See! Pallas, of her snaky buckler proud,</l>
<l n="tr">Bestrides the tow'r, refulgent thro' the cloud:</l>
<l n="tr">See! Jove new courage to the foe supplies,</l>
<l n="tr">And arms against the town the partial deities.</l>
<l n="tr">Haste hence, my son; this fruitless labor end:</l>
<l n="tr">Haste, where your trembling spouse and sire attend:</l>
<l n="tr">Haste; and a mother's care your passage shall befriend.’</l>
<l n="tr">She said, and swiftly vanish'd from my sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Obscure in clouds and gloomy shades of night.</l>
<l n="tr">I look'd, I listen'd; dreadful sounds I hear;</l>
<l n="tr">And the dire forms of hostile gods appear.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="624" unit="card"/><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> sunk in flames I saw (nor could prevent),</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> from its old foundations rent;</l>
<l n="tr">Rent like a mountain ash, which dar'd the winds,</l>
<l n="tr">And stood the sturdy strokes of lab'ring hinds.</l>
<l n="tr">About the roots the cruel ax resounds;</l>
<l n="tr">The stumps are pierc'd with oft-repeated wounds:</l>
<l n="tr">The war is felt on high; the nodding crown</l>
<l n="tr">Now threats a fall, and throws the leafy honors down.</l>
<l n="tr">To their united force it yields, tho' late,</l>
<l n="tr">And mourns with mortal groans  th'  approaching fate:</l>
<l n="tr">The roots no more their upper load sustain;</l>
<l n="tr">But down she falls, and spreads a ruin thro' the plain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Descending thence, I scape thro' foes and fire:</l>
<l n="tr">Before the goddess, foes and flames retire.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="634" unit="card"/>Arriv'd at home, he, for whose only sake,</l>
<l n="tr">Or most for his, such toils I undertake,</l>
<l n="tr">The good Anchises, whom, by timely flight,</l>
<l n="tr">I purpos'd to secure on Ida's height,</l>
<l n="tr">Refus'd the journey, resolute to die</l>
<l n="tr">And add his fun'rals to the fate of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Rather than exile and old age sustain.</l>
<l n="tr">‘Go you, whose blood runs warm in ev'ry vein.</l>
<l n="tr">Had Heav'n decreed that I should life enjoy,</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'n had decreed to save unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is, sure, enough, if not too much, for one,</l>
<l n="tr">Twice to have seen our <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> overthrown.</l>
<l n="tr">Make haste to save the poor remaining crew,</l>
<l n="tr">And give this useless corpse a long adieu.</l>
<l n="tr">These weak old hands suffice to stop my breath;</l>
<l n="tr">At least the pitying foes will aid my death,</l>
<l n="tr">To take my spoils, and leave my body bare:</l>
<l n="tr">As for my sepulcher, let Heav'n take care.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is long since I, for my celestial wife</l>
<l n="tr">Loath'd by the gods, have dragg'd a ling'ring life;</l>
<l n="tr">Since ev'ry hour and moment I expire,</l>
<l n="tr">Blasted from heav'n by Jove's avenging fire.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="650" unit="card"/>This oft repeated, he stood fix'd to die:</l>
<l n="tr">Myself, my wife, my son, my family,</l>
<l n="tr">Intreat, pray, beg, and raise a doleful cry—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">‘What, will he still persist, on death resolve,</l>
<l n="tr">And in his ruin all his house involve!’</l>
<l n="tr">He still persists his reasons to maintain;</l>
<l n="tr">Our pray'rs, our tears, our loud laments, are vain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Urg'd by despair, again I go to try</l>
<l n="tr">The fate of arms, resolv'd in fight to die:</l>
<l n="tr">‘What hope remains, but what my death must give?</l>
<l n="tr">Can I, without so dear a father, live?</l>
<l n="tr">You term it prudence, what I baseness call:</l>
<l n="tr">Could such a word from such a parent fall?</l>
<l n="tr">If Fortune please, and so the gods ordain,</l>
<l n="tr">That nothing should of ruin'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> remain,</l>
<l n="tr">And you conspire with Fortune to be slain,</l>
<l n="tr">The way to death is wide,  th'  approaches near:</l>
<l n="tr">For soon relentless Pyrrhus will appear,</l>
<l n="tr">Reeking with Priam's blood—the wretch who slew</l>
<l n="tr">The son (inhuman) in the father's view,</l>
<l n="tr">And then the sire himself to the dire altar drew.</l>
<l n="tr">O goddess mother, give me back to Fate;</l>
<l n="tr">Your gift was undesir'd, and came too late!</l>
<l n="tr">Did you, for this, unhappy me convey</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' foes and fires, to see my house a prey?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall I my father, wife, and son behold,</l>
<l n="tr">Welt'ring in blood, each other's arms infold?</l>
<l n="tr">Haste! gird my sword, tho' spent and overcome:</l>
<l n="tr">'T is the last summons to receive our doom.</l>
<l n="tr">I hear thee, Fate; and I obey thy call!</l>
<l n="tr">Not unreveng'd the foe shall see my fall.</l>
<l n="tr">Restore me to the yet unfinish'd fight:</l>
<l n="tr">My death is wanting to conclude the night.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="671" unit="card"/>Arm'd once again, my glitt'ring sword I wield,</l>
<l n="tr">While  th'  other hand sustains my weighty shield,</l>
<l n="tr">And forth I rush to seek  th'  abandon'd field.</l>
<l n="tr">I went; but sad Creusa stopp'd my way,</l>
<l n="tr">And cross the threshold in my passage lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Embrac'd my knees, and, when I would have gone,</l>
<l n="tr">Shew'd me my feeble sire and tender son:</l>
<l n="tr">‘If death be your design, at least,’ said she,</l>
<l n="tr">‘Take us along to share your destiny.</l>
<l n="tr">If any farther hopes in arms remain,</l>
<l n="tr">This place, these pledges of your love, maintain.</l>
<l n="tr">To whom do you expose your father's life,</l>
<l n="tr">Your son's, and mine, your now forgotten wife!’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="679" unit="card"/>While thus she fills the house with clam'rous cries,</l>
<l n="tr">Our hearing is diverted by our eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">For, while I held my son, in the short space</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt our kisses and our last embrace;</l>
<l n="tr">Strange to relate, from young Iulus' head</l>
<l n="tr">A lambent flame arose, which gently spread</l>
<l n="tr">Around his brows, and on his temples fed.</l>
<l n="tr">Amaz'd, with running water we prepare</l>
<l n="tr">To quench the sacred fire, and slake his hair;</l>
<l n="tr">But old Anchises, vers'd in omens, rear'd</l>
<l n="tr">His hands to heav'n, and this request preferr'd:</l>
<l n="tr">‘If any vows, almighty Jove, can bend</l>
<l n="tr">Thy will; if piety can pray'rs commend,</l>
<l n="tr">Confirm the glad presage which thou art pleas'd to send.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="692" unit="card"/>Scarce had he said, when, on our left, we hear</l>
<l n="tr">A peal of rattling thunder roll in air:</l>
<l n="tr">There shot a streaming lamp along the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Which on the winged lightning seem'd to fly;</l>
<l n="tr">From o'er the roof the blaze began to move,</l>
<l n="tr">And, trailing, vanish'd in  th'  Idaean grove.</l>
<l n="tr">It swept a path in heav'n, and shone a guide,</l>
<l n="tr">Then in a steaming stench of sulphur died.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The good old man with suppliant hands implor'd</l>
<l n="tr">The gods' protection, and their star ador'd.</l>
<l n="tr">‘Now, now,’ said he, ‘my son, no more delay!</l>
<l n="tr">I yield, I follow where Heav'n shews the way.</l>
<l n="tr">Keep, O my country gods, our dwelling place,</l>
<l n="tr">And guard this relic of the Trojan race,</l>
<l n="tr">This tender child! These omens are your own,</l>
<l n="tr">And you can yet restore the ruin'd town.</l>
<l n="tr">At least accomplish what your signs foreshow:</l>
<l n="tr">I stand resign'd, and am prepar'd to go.’</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He said. The crackling flames appear on high.</l>
<l n="tr">And driving sparkles dance along the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">With <persName>Vulcan</persName>'s rage the rising winds conspire,</l>
<l n="tr">And near our palace roll the flood of fire.</l>
<l n="tr">‘Haste, my dear father, ('t is no time to wait,)</l>
<l n="tr">And load my shoulders with a willing freight.</l>
<l n="tr">Whate'er befalls, your life shall be my care;</l>
<l n="tr">One death, or one deliv'rance, we will share.</l>
<l n="tr">My hand shall lead our little son; and you,</l>
<l n="tr">My faithful consort, shall our steps pursue.</l>
<l n="tr">Next, you, my servants, heed my strict commands:</l>
<l n="tr">Without the walls a ruin'd temple stands,</l>
<l n="tr">To <persName>Ceres</persName> hallow'd once; a cypress nigh</l>
<l n="tr">Shoots up her venerable head on high,</l>
<l n="tr">By long religion kept; there bend your feet,</l>
<l n="tr">And in divided parties let us meet.</l>
<l n="tr">Our country gods, the relics, and the bands,</l>
<l n="tr">Hold you, my father, in your guiltless hands:</l>
<l n="tr">In me 't is impious holy things to bear,</l>
<l n="tr">Red as I am with slaughter, new from war,</l>
<l n="tr">Till in some living stream I cleanse the guilt</l>
<l n="tr">Of dire debate, and blood in battle spilt.’</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, ord'ring all that prudence could provide,</l>
<l n="tr">I clothe my shoulders with a lion's hide</l>
<l n="tr">And yellow spoils; then, on my bending back,</l>
<l n="tr">The welcome load of my dear father take;</l>
<l n="tr">While on my better hand Ascanius hung,</l>
<l n="tr">And with unequal paces tripp'd along.</l>
<l n="tr">Creusa kept behind; by choice we stray</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' ev'ry dark and ev'ry devious way.</l>
<l n="tr">I, who so bold and dauntless, just before,</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian darts and shock of lances bore,</l>
<l n="tr">At ev'ry shadow now am seiz'd with fear,</l>
<l n="tr">Not for myself, but for the charge I bear;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, near the ruin'd gate arriv'd at last,</l>
<l n="tr">Secure, and deeming all the danger past,</l>
<l n="tr">A frightful noise of trampling feet we hear.</l>
<l n="tr">My father, looking thro' the shades, with fear,</l>
<l n="tr">Cried out: ‘Haste, haste, my son, the foes are nigh;</l>
<l n="tr">Their swords and shining armor I descry.’</l>
<l n="tr">Some hostile god, for some unknown offense,</l>
<l n="tr">Had sure bereft my mind of better sense;</l>
<l n="tr">For, while thro' winding ways I took my flight,</l>
<l n="tr">And sought the shelter of the gloomy night,</l>
<l n="tr">Alas! I lost Creusa: hard to tell</l>
<l n="tr">If by her fatal destiny she fell,</l>
<l n="tr">Or weary sate, or wander'd with affright;</l>
<l n="tr">But she was lost for ever to my sight.</l>
<l n="tr">I knew not, or reflected, till I meet</l>
<l n="tr">My friends, at <persName>Ceres</persName>' now deserted seat.</l>
<l n="tr">We met: not one was wanting; only she</l>
<l n="tr">Deceiv'd her friends, her son, and wretched me.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What mad expressions did my tongue refuse!</l>
<l n="tr">Whom did I not, of gods or men, accuse!</l>
<l n="tr">This was the fatal blow, that pain'd me more</l>
<l n="tr">Than all I felt from ruin'd <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> before.</l>
<l n="tr">Stung with my loss, and raving with despair,</l>
<l n="tr">Abandoning my now forgotten care,</l>
<l n="tr">Of counsel, comfort, and of hope bereft,</l>
<l n="tr">My sire, my son, my country gods I left.</l>
<l n="tr">In shining armor once again I sheathe</l>
<l n="tr">My limbs, not feeling wounds, nor fearing death.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="752" unit="card"/>Then headlong to the burning walls I run,</l>
<l n="tr">And seek the danger I was forc'd to shun.</l>
<l n="tr">I tread my former tracks; thro' night explore</l>
<l n="tr">Each passage, ev'ry street I cross'd before.</l>
<l n="tr">All things were full of horror and affright,</l>
<l n="tr">And dreadful ev'n the silence of the night.</l>
<l n="tr">Then to my father's house I make repair,</l>
<l n="tr">With some small glimpse of hope to find her there.</l>
<l n="tr">Instead of her, the cruel Greeks I met;</l>
<l n="tr">The house was fill'd with foes, with flames beset.</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n on the wings of winds, whole sheets of fire,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' air transported, to the roofs aspire.</l>
<l n="tr">From thence to Priam's palace I resort,</l>
<l n="tr">And search the citadel and desart court.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, unobserv'd, I pass by Juno's church:</l>
<l n="tr">A guard of Grecians had possess'd the porch;</l>
<l n="tr">There Phoenix and Ulysses watch prey,</l>
<l n="tr">And thither all the wealth of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> convey:</l>
<l n="tr">The spoils which they from ransack'd houses brought,</l>
<l n="tr">And golden bowls from burning altars caught,</l>
<l n="tr">The tables of the gods, the purple vests,</l>
<l n="tr">The people's treasure, and the pomp of priests.</l>
<l n="tr">A rank of wretched youths, with pinion'd hands,</l>
<l n="tr">And captive matrons, in long order stands.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, with ungovern'd madness, I proclaim,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' all the silent street, Creusa's name:</l>
<l n="tr">Creusa still I call; at length she hears,</l>
<l n="tr">And sudden thro' the shades of night appears—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Appears, no more Creusa, nor my wife,</l>
<l n="tr">But a pale specter, larger than the life.</l>
<l n="tr">Aghast, astonish'd, and struck dumb with fear,</l>
<l n="tr">I stood; like bristles rose my stiffen'd hair.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus the ghost began to soothe my grief</l>
<l n="tr">‘Nor tears, nor cries, can give the dead relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Desist, my much-lov'd lord, t' indulge your pain;</l>
<l n="tr">You bear no more than what the gods ordain.</l>
<l n="tr">My fates permit me not from hence to fly;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor he, the great controller of the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">Long wand'ring ways for you the pow'rs decree;</l>
<l n="tr">On land hard labors, and a length of sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, after many painful years are past,</l>
<l n="tr">On <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>'s happy shore you shall be cast,</l>
<l n="tr">Where gentle <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> from his bed beholds</l>
<l n="tr">The flow'ry meadows, and the feeding folds.</l>
<l n="tr">There end your toils; and there your fates provide</l>
<l n="tr">A quiet kingdom, and a royal bride:</l>
<l n="tr">There fortune shall the Trojan line restore,</l>
<l n="tr">And you for lost Creusa weep no more.</l>
<l n="tr">Fear not that I shall watch, with servile shame,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' imperious looks of some proud Grecian dame;</l>
<l n="tr">Or, stooping to the victor's lust, disgrace</l>
<l n="tr">My goddess mother, or my royal race.</l>
<l n="tr">And now, farewell! The parent of the gods</l>
<l n="tr">Restrains my fleeting soul in her abodes:</l>
<l n="tr">I trust our common issue to your care.’</l>
<l n="tr">She said, and gliding pass'd unseen in air.</l>
<l n="tr">I strove to speak: but horror tied my tongue;</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice about her neck my arms I flung,</l>
<l n="tr">And, thrice deceiv'd, on vain embraces hung.</l>
<l n="tr">Light as an empty dream at break of day,</l>
<l n="tr">Or as a blast of wind, she rush'd away.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="795" unit="card"/>Thus having pass'd the night in fruitless pain,</l>
<l n="tr">I to my longing friends return again,</l>
<l n="tr">Amaz'd  th'  augmented number to behold,</l>
<l n="tr">Of men and matrons mix'd, of young and old;</l>
<l n="tr">A wretched exil'd crew together brought,</l>
<l n="tr">With arms appointed, and with treasure fraught,</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd, and willing, under my command,</l>
<l n="tr">To run all hazards both of sea and land.</l>
<l n="tr">The Morn began, from Ida, to display</l>
<l n="tr">Her rosy cheeks; and Phosphor led the day:</l>
<l n="tr">Before the gates the Grecians took their post,</l>
<l n="tr">And all pretense of late relief was lost.</l>
<l n="tr">I yield to Fate, unwillingly retire,</l>
<l n="tr">And, loaded, up the hill convey my sire.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>