<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="4" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">But anxious cares already seiz'd the queen:</l>
<l n="tr">She fed within her veins a flame unseen;</l>
<l n="tr">The hero's valor, acts, and birth inspire</l>
<l n="tr">Her soul with love, and fan the secret fire.</l>
<l n="tr">His words, his looks, imprinted in her heart,</l>
<l n="tr">Improve the passion, and increase the smart.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, when the purple morn had chas'd away</l>
<l n="tr">The dewy shadows, and restor'd the day,</l>
<l n="tr">Her sister first with early care she sought,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus in mournful accents eas'd her thought:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“My dearest Anna, what new dreams affright</l>
<l n="tr">My lab'ring soul! what visions of the night</l>
<l n="tr">Disturb my quiet, and distract my breast</l>
<l n="tr">With strange ideas of our Trojan guest!</l>
<l n="tr">His worth, his actions, and majestic air,</l>
<l n="tr">A man descended from the gods declare.</l>
<l n="tr">Fear ever argues a degenerate kind;</l>
<l n="tr">His birth is well asserted by his mind.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, what he suffer'd, when by Fate betray'd!</l>
<l n="tr">What brave attempts for falling <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> he made!</l>
<l n="tr">Such were his looks, so gracefully he spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">That, were I not resolv'd against the yoke</l>
<l n="tr">Of hapless marriage, never to be curst</l>
<l n="tr">With second love, so fatal was my first,</l>
<l n="tr">To this one error I might yield again;</l>
<l n="tr">For, since Sichaeus was untimely slain,</l>
<l n="tr">This only man is able to subvert</l>
<l n="tr">The fix'd foundations of my stubborn heart.</l>
<l n="tr">And, to confess my frailty, to my shame,</l>
<l n="tr">Somewhat I find within, if not the same,</l>
<l n="tr">Too like the sparkles of my former flame.</l>
<l n="tr">But first let yawning earth a passage rend,</l>
<l n="tr">And let me thro' the dark abyss descend;</l>
<l n="tr">First let avenging Jove, with flames from high,</l>
<l n="tr">Drive down this body to the nether sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Condemn'd with ghosts in endless night to lie,</l>
<l n="tr">Before I break the plighted faith I gave!</l>
<l n="tr">No! he who had my vows shall ever have;</l>
<l n="tr">For, whom I lov'd on earth, I worship in the grave.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said: the tears ran gushing from her eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And stopp'd her speech.<milestone ed="p" n="31" unit="card"/>Her sister thus replies:</l>
<l n="tr">“O dearer than the vital air I breathe,</l>
<l n="tr">Will you to grief your blooming years bequeath,</l>
<l n="tr">Condemn'd to waste in woes your lonely life,</l>
<l n="tr">Without the joys of mother or of wife?</l>
<l n="tr">Think you these tears, this pompous train of woe,</l>
<l n="tr">Are known or valued by the ghosts below?</l>
<l n="tr">I grant that, while your sorrows yet were green,</l>
<l n="tr">It well became a woman, and a queen,</l>
<l n="tr">The vows of Tyrian princes to neglect,</l>
<l n="tr">To scorn Hyarbas, and his love reject,</l>
<l n="tr">With all the Libyan lords of mighty name;</l>
<l n="tr">But will you fight against a pleasing flame!</l>
<l n="tr">This little spot of land, which Heav'n bestows,</l>
<l n="tr">On ev'ry side is hemm'd with warlike foes;</l>
<l n="tr">Gaetulian cities here are spread around,</l>
<l n="tr">And fierce Numidians there your frontiers bound;</l>
<l n="tr">Here lies a barren waste of thirsty land,</l>
<l n="tr">And there the Syrtes raise the moving sand;</l>
<l n="tr">Barcaean troops besiege the narrow shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the sea Pygmalion threatens more.</l>
<l n="tr">Propitious Heav'n, and gracious Juno, lead</l>
<l n="tr">This wand'ring navy to your needful aid:</l>
<l n="tr">How will your empire spread, your city rise,</l>
<l n="tr">From such a union, and with such allies?</l>
<l n="tr">Implore the favor of the pow'rs above,</l>
<l n="tr">And leave the conduct of the rest to love.</l>
<l n="tr">Continue still your hospitable way,</l>
<l n="tr">And still invent occasions of their stay,</l>
<l n="tr">Till storms and winter winds shall cease to threat,</l>
<l n="tr">And planks and oars repair their shatter'd fleet.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="54" unit="card"/>These words, which from a friend and sister came,</l>
<l n="tr">With ease resolv'd the scruples of her fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And added fury to the kindled flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Inspir'd with hope, the project they pursue;</l>
<l n="tr">On ev'ry altar sacrifice renew:</l>
<l n="tr">A chosen ewe of two years old they pay</l>
<l n="tr">To <persName>Ceres</persName>, Bacchus, and the God of Day;</l>
<l n="tr">Preferring Juno's pow'r, for Juno ties</l>
<l n="tr">The nuptial knot and makes the marriage joys.</l>
<l n="tr">The beauteous queen before her altar stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And holds the golden goblet in her hands.</l>
<l n="tr">A milk-white heifer she with flow'rs adorns,</l>
<l n="tr">And pours the ruddy wine betwixt her horns;</l>
<l n="tr">And, while the priests with pray'r the gods invoke,</l>
<l n="tr">She feeds their altars with Sabaean smoke,</l>
<l n="tr">With hourly care the sacrifice renews,</l>
<l n="tr">And anxiously the panting entrails views.</l>
<l n="tr">What priestly rites, alas! what pious art,</l>
<l n="tr">What vows avail to cure a bleeding heart!</l>
<l n="tr">A gentle fire she feeds within her veins,</l>
<l n="tr">Where the soft god secure in silence reigns.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Sick with desire, and seeking him she loves,</l>
<l n="tr">From street to street the raving Dido roves.</l>
<l n="tr">So when the watchful shepherd, from the blind,</l>
<l n="tr">Wounds with a random shaft the careless hind,</l>
<l n="tr">Distracted with her pain she flies the woods,</l>
<l n="tr">Bounds o'er the lawn, and seeks the silent floods,</l>
<l n="tr">With fruitless care; for still the fatal dart</l>
<l n="tr">Sticks in her side, and rankles in her heart.</l>
<l n="tr">And now she leads the Trojan chief along</l>
<l n="tr">The lofty walls, amidst the busy throng;</l>
<l n="tr">Displays her Tyrian wealth, and rising town,</l>
<l n="tr">Which love, without his labor, makes his own.</l>
<l n="tr">This pomp she shows, to tempt her wand'ring guest;</l>
<l n="tr">Her falt'ring tongue forbids to speak the rest.</l>
<l n="tr">When day declines, and feasts renew the night,</l>
<l n="tr">Still on his face she feeds her famish'd sight;</l>
<l n="tr">She longs again to hear the prince relate</l>
<l n="tr">His own adventures and the Trojan fate.</l>
<l n="tr">He tells it o'er and o'er; but still in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">For still she begs to hear it once again.</l>
<l n="tr">The hearer on the speaker's mouth depends,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus the tragic story never ends.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then, when they part, when Phoebe's paler light</l>
<l n="tr">Withdraws, and falling stars to sleep invite,</l>
<l n="tr">She last remains, when ev'ry guest is gone,</l>
<l n="tr">Sits on the bed he press'd, and sighs alone;</l>
<l n="tr">Absent, her absent hero sees and hears;</l>
<l n="tr">Or in her bosom young Ascanius bears,</l>
<l n="tr">And seeks the father's image in the child,</l>
<l n="tr">If love by likeness might be so beguil'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Meantime the rising tow'rs are at a stand;</l>
<l n="tr">No labors exercise the youthful band,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor use of arts, nor toils of arms they know;</l>
<l n="tr">The mole is left unfinish'd to the foe;</l>
<l n="tr">The mounds, the works, the walls, neglected lie,</l>
<l n="tr">Short of their promis'd heighth, that seem'd to threat the sky.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="90" unit="card"/>But when imperial Juno, from above,</l>
<l n="tr">Saw Dido fetter'd in the chains of love,</l>
<l n="tr">Hot with the venom which her veins inflam'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And by no sense of shame to be reclaim'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With soothing words to Venus she begun:</l>
<l n="tr">“High praises, endless honors, you have won,</l>
<l n="tr">And mighty trophies, with your worthy son!</l>
<l n="tr">Two gods a silly woman have undone!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor am I ignorant, you both suspect</l>
<l n="tr">This rising city, which my hands erect:</l>
<l n="tr">But shall celestial discord never cease?</l>
<l n="tr">'T is better ended in a lasting peace.</l>
<l n="tr">You stand possess'd of all your soul desir'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Poor Dido with consuming love is fir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Your Trojan with my Tyrian let us join;</l>
<l n="tr">So Dido shall be yours, Aeneas mine:</l>
<l n="tr">One common kingdom, one united line.</l>
<l n="tr">Eliza shall a Dardan lord obey,</l>
<l n="tr">And lofty <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> for a dow'r convey.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="card"/>Then Venus, who her hidden fraud descried,</l>
<l n="tr">Which would the scepter of the world misguide</l>
<l n="tr">To Libyan shores, thus artfully replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“Who, but a fool, would wars with Juno choose,</l>
<l n="tr">And such alliance and such gifts refuse,</l>
<l n="tr">If Fortune with our joint desires comply?</l>
<l n="tr">The doubt is all from Jove and destiny;</l>
<l n="tr">Lest he forbid, with absolute command,</l>
<l n="tr">To mix the people in one common land—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Or will the Trojan and the Tyrian line</l>
<l n="tr">In lasting leagues and sure succession join?</l>
<l n="tr">But you, the partner of his bed and throne,</l>
<l n="tr">May move his mind; my wishes are your own.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Mine,” said imperial Juno, “be the care;</l>
<l n="tr">Time urges, now, to perfect this affair:</l>
<l n="tr">Attend my counsel, and the secret share.</l>
<l n="tr">When next the Sun his rising light displays,</l>
<l n="tr">And gilds the world below with purple rays,</l>
<l n="tr">The queen, Aeneas, and the Tyrian court</l>
<l n="tr">Shall to the shady woods, for sylvan game, resort.</l>
<l n="tr">There, while the huntsmen pitch their toils around,</l>
<l n="tr">And cheerful horns from side to side resound,</l>
<l n="tr">A pitchy cloud shall cover all the plain</l>
<l n="tr">With hail, and thunder, and tempestuous rain;</l>
<l n="tr">The fearful train shall take their speedy flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Dispers'd, and all involv'd in gloomy night;</l>
<l n="tr">One cave a grateful shelter shall afford</l>
<l n="tr">To the fair princess and the Trojan lord.</l>
<l n="tr">I will myself the bridal bed prepare,</l>
<l n="tr">If you, to bless the nuptials, will be there:</l>
<l n="tr">So shall their loves be crown'd with due delights,</l>
<l n="tr">And Hymen shall be present at the rites.”</l>
<l n="tr">The Queen of Love consents, and closely smiles</l>
<l n="tr">At her vain project, and discover'd wiles.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="129" unit="card"/>The rosy morn was risen from the main,</l>
<l n="tr">And horns and hounds awake the princely train:</l>
<l n="tr">They issue early thro' the city gate,</l>
<l n="tr">Where the more wakeful huntsmen ready wait,</l>
<l n="tr">With nets, and toils, and darts, beside the force</l>
<l n="tr">Of Spartan dogs, and swift Massylian horse.</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrian peers and officers of state</l>
<l n="tr">For the slow queen in antechambers wait;</l>
<l n="tr">Her lofty courser, in the court below,</l>
<l n="tr">Who his majestic rider seems to know,</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of his purple trappings, paws the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And champs the golden bit, and spreads the foam around.</l>
<l n="tr">The queen at length appears; on either hand</l>
<l n="tr">The brawny guards in martial order stand.</l>
<l n="tr">A flow'r'd simar with golden fringe she wore,</l>
<l n="tr">And at her back a golden quiver bore;</l>
<l n="tr">Her flowing hair a golden caul restrains,</l>
<l n="tr">A golden clasp the Tyrian robe sustains.</l>
<l n="tr">Then young Ascanius, with a sprightly grace,</l>
<l n="tr">Leads on the Trojan youth to view the chase.</l>
<l n="tr">But far above the rest in beauty shines</l>
<l n="tr">The great Aeneas, the troop he joins;</l>
<l n="tr">Like fair Apollo, when he leaves the frost</l>
<l n="tr">Of wint'ry <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>, and the Lycian coast,</l>
<l n="tr">When to his native <placeName key="perseus,Delos" authname="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> he resorts,</l>
<l n="tr">Ordains the dances, and renews the sports;</l>
<l n="tr">Where painted Scythians, mix'd with Cretan bands,</l>
<l n="tr">Before the joyful altars join their hands:</l>
<l n="tr">Himself, on Cynthus walking, sees below</l>
<l n="tr">The merry madness of the sacred show.</l>
<l n="tr">Green wreaths of bays his length of hair inclose;</l>
<l n="tr">A golden fillet binds his awful brows;</l>
<l n="tr">His quiver sounds: not less the prince is seen</l>
<l n="tr">In manly presence, or in lofty mien.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now had they reach'd the hills, and storm'd the seat</l>
<l n="tr">Of salvage beasts, in dens, their last retreat.</l>
<l n="tr">The cry pursues the mountain goats: they bound</l>
<l n="tr">From rock to rock, and keep the craggy ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Quite otherwise the stags, a trembling train,</l>
<l n="tr">In herds unsingled, scour the dusty plain,</l>
<l n="tr">And a long chase in open view maintain.</l>
<l n="tr">The glad Ascanius, as his courser guides,</l>
<l n="tr">Spurs thro' the vale, and these and those outrides.</l>
<l n="tr">His horse's flanks and sides are forc'd to feel</l>
<l n="tr">The clanking lash, and goring of the steel.</l>
<l n="tr">Impatiently he views the feeble prey,</l>
<l n="tr">Wishing some nobler beast to cross his way,</l>
<l n="tr">And rather would the tusky boar attend,</l>
<l n="tr">Or see the tawny lion downward bend.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="160" unit="card"/>Meantime, the gath'ring clouds obscure the skies:</l>
<l n="tr">From pole to pole the forky lightning flies;</l>
<l n="tr">The rattling thunders roll; and Juno pours</l>
<l n="tr">A wintry deluge down, and sounding show'rs.</l>
<l n="tr">The company, dispers'd, to converts ride,</l>
<l n="tr">And seek the homely cots, or mountain's hollow side.</l>
<l n="tr">The rapid rains, descending from the hills,</l>
<l n="tr">To rolling torrents raise the creeping rills.</l>
<l n="tr">The queen and prince, as love or fortune guides,</l>
<l n="tr">One common cavern in her bosom hides.</l>
<l n="tr">Then first the trembling earth the signal gave,</l>
<l n="tr">And flashing fires enlighten all the cave;</l>
<l n="tr">Hell from below, and Juno from above,</l>
<l n="tr">And howling nymphs, were conscious of their love.</l>
<l n="tr">From this ill-omen'd hour in time arose</l>
<l n="tr">Debate and death, and all succeeding woes.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The queen, whom sense of honor could not move,</l>
<l n="tr">No longer made a secret of her love,</l>
<l n="tr">But call'd it marriage, by that specious name</l>
<l n="tr">To veil the crime and sanctify the shame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="173" unit="card"/>The loud report thro' Libyan cities goes.</l>
<l n="tr">Fame, the great ill, from small beginnings grows:</l>
<l n="tr">Swift from the first; and ev'ry moment brings</l>
<l n="tr">New vigor to her flights, new pinions to her wings.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon grows the pigmy to gigantic size;</l>
<l n="tr">Her feet on earth, her forehead in the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Inrag'd against the gods, revengeful Earth</l>
<l n="tr">Produc'd her last of the Titanian birth.</l>
<l n="tr">Swift is her walk, more swift her winged haste:</l>
<l n="tr">A monstrous phantom, horrible and vast.</l>
<l n="tr">As many plumes as raise her lofty flight,</l>
<l n="tr">So many piercing eyes inlarge her sight;</l>
<l n="tr">Millions of opening mouths to Fame belong,</l>
<l n="tr">And ev'ry mouth is furnish'd with a tongue,</l>
<l n="tr">And round with list'ning ears the flying plague is hung.</l>
<l n="tr">She fills the peaceful universe with cries;</l>
<l n="tr">No slumbers ever close her wakeful eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">By day, from lofty tow'rs her head she shews,</l>
<l n="tr">And spreads thro' trembling crowds disastrous news;</l>
<l n="tr">With court informers haunts, and royal spies;</l>
<l n="tr">Things done relates, not done she feigns, and mingles truth with lies.</l>
<l n="tr">Talk is her business, and her chief delight</l>
<l n="tr">To tell of prodigies and cause affright.</l>
<l n="tr">She fills the people's ears with Dido's name,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, lost to honor and the sense of shame,</l>
<l n="tr">Admits into her throne and nuptial bed</l>
<l n="tr">A wand'ring guest, who from his country fled:</l>
<l n="tr">Whole days with him she passes in delights,</l>
<l n="tr">And wastes in luxury long winter nights,</l>
<l n="tr">Forgetful of her fame and royal trust,</l>
<l n="tr">Dissolv'd in ease, abandon'd to her lust.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The goddess widely spreads the loud report,</l>
<l n="tr">And flies at length to King Hyarba's court.</l>
<l n="tr">When first possess'd with this unwelcome news</l>
<l n="tr">Whom did he not of men and gods accuse?</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="198" unit="card"/>This prince, from ravish'd Garamantis born,</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred temples did with spoils adorn,</l>
<l n="tr">In Ammon's honor, his celestial sire;</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred altars fed with wakeful fire;</l>
<l n="tr">And, thro' his vast dominions, priests ordain'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose watchful care these holy rites maintain'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The gates and columns were with garlands crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And blood of victim beasts enrich'd the ground.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He, when he heard a fugitive could move</l>
<l n="tr">The Tyrian princess, who disdain'd his love,</l>
<l n="tr">His breast with fury burn'd, his eyes with fire,</l>
<l n="tr">Mad with despair, impatient with desire;</l>
<l n="tr">Then on the sacred altars pouring wine,</l>
<l n="tr">He thus with pray'rs implor'd his sire divine:</l>
<l n="tr">“Great Jove! propitious to the Moorish race,</l>
<l n="tr">Who feast on painted beds, with off'rings grace</l>
<l n="tr">Thy temples, and adore thy pow'r divine</l>
<l n="tr">With blood of victims, and with sparkling wine,</l>
<l n="tr">Seest thou not this? or do we fear in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Thy boasted thunder, and thy thoughtless reign?</l>
<l n="tr">Do thy broad hands the forky lightnings lance?</l>
<l n="tr">Thine are the bolts, or the blind work of chance?</l>
<l n="tr">A wand'ring woman builds, within our state,</l>
<l n="tr">A little town, bought at an easy rate;</l>
<l n="tr">She pays me homage, and my grants allow</l>
<l n="tr">A narrow space of Libyan lands to plow;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, scorning me, by passion blindly led,</l>
<l n="tr">Admits a banish'd Trojan to her bed!</l>
<l n="tr">And now this other <persName>Paris</persName>, with his train</l>
<l n="tr">Of conquer'd cowards, must in Afric reign!</l>
<l n="tr">(Whom, what they are, their looks and garb confess,</l>
<l n="tr">Their locks with oil perfum'd, their Lydian dress.)</l>
<l n="tr">He takes the spoil, enjoys the princely dame;</l>
<l n="tr">And I, rejected I, adore an empty name.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="219" unit="card"/>His vows, in haughty terms, he thus preferr'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And held his altar's horns. The mighty Thund'rer heard;</l>
<l n="tr">Then cast his eyes on <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, where he found</l>
<l n="tr">The lustful pair in lawless pleasure drown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Lost in their loves, insensible of shame,</l>
<l n="tr">And both forgetful of their better fame.</l>
<l n="tr">He calls Cyllenius, and the god attends,</l>
<l n="tr">By whom his menacing command he sends:</l>
<l n="tr">“Go, mount the western winds, and cleave the sky;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, with a swift descent, to <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> fly:</l>
<l n="tr">There find the Trojan chief, who wastes his days</l>
<l n="tr">In slothful not and inglorious ease,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor minds the future city, giv'n by fate.</l>
<l n="tr">To him this message from my mouth relate:</l>
<l n="tr">‘Not so fair Venus hop'd, when twice she won</l>
<l n="tr">Thy life with pray'rs, nor promis'd such a son.</l>
<l n="tr">Hers was a hero, destin'd to command</l>
<l n="tr">A martial race, and rule the Latian land,</l>
<l n="tr">Who should his ancient line from Teucer draw,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the conquer'd world impose the law.’</l>
<l n="tr">If glory cannot move a mind so mean,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor future praise from fading pleasure wean,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet why should he defraud his son of fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And grudge the Romans their immortal name!</l>
<l n="tr">What are his vain designs! what hopes he more</l>
<l n="tr">From his long ling'ring on a hostile shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Regardless to redeem his honor lost,</l>
<l n="tr">And for his race to gain  th'  Ausonian coast!</l>
<l n="tr">Bid him with speed the Tyrian court forsake;</l>
<l n="tr">With this command the slumb'ring warrior wake.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="238" unit="card"/>Hermes obeys; with golden pinions binds</l>
<l n="tr">His flying feet, and mounts the western winds:</l>
<l n="tr">And, whether o'er the seas or earth he flies,</l>
<l n="tr">With rapid force they bear him down the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">But first he grasps within his awful hand</l>
<l n="tr">The mark of sov'reign pow'r, his magic wand;</l>
<l n="tr">With this he draws the ghosts from hollow graves;</l>
<l n="tr">With this he drives them down the Stygian waves;</l>
<l n="tr">With this he seals in sleep the wakeful sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And eyes, tho' clos'd in death, restores to light.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus arm'd, the god begins his airy race,</l>
<l n="tr">And drives the racking clouds along the liquid space;</l>
<l n="tr">Now sees the tops of Atlas, as he flies,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose brawny back supports the starry skies;</l>
<l n="tr">Atlas, whose head, with piny forests crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Is beaten by the winds, with foggy vapors bound.</l>
<l n="tr">Snows hide his shoulders; from beneath his chin</l>
<l n="tr">The founts of rolling streams their race begin;</l>
<l n="tr">A beard of ice on his large breast depends.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, pois'd upon his wings, the god descends:</l>
<l n="tr">Then, rested thus, he from the tow'ring height</l>
<l n="tr">Plung'd downward, with precipitated flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Lights on the seas, and skims along the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">As waterfowl, who seek their fishy food,</l>
<l n="tr">Less, and yet less, to distant prospect show;</l>
<l n="tr">By turns they dance aloft, and dive below:</l>
<l n="tr">Like these, the steerage of his wings he plies,</l>
<l n="tr">And near the surface of the water flies,</l>
<l n="tr">Till, having pass'd the seas, and cross'd the sands,</l>
<l n="tr">He clos'd his wings, and stoop'd on Libyan lands:</l>
<l n="tr">Where shepherds once were hous'd in homely sheds,</l>
<l n="tr">Now tow'rs within the clouds advance their heads.</l>
<l n="tr">Arriving there, he found the Trojan prince</l>
<l n="tr">New ramparts raising for the town's defense.</l>
<l n="tr">A purple scarf, with gold embroider'd o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">(Queen Dido's gift,) about his waist he wore;</l>
<l n="tr">A sword, with glitt'ring gems diversified,</l>
<l n="tr">For ornament, not use, hung idly by his side.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus, with winged words, the god began,</l>
<l n="tr">Resuming his own shape: “Degenerate man,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou woman's property, what mak'st thou here,</l>
<l n="tr">These foreign walls and Tyrian tow'rs to rear,</l>
<l n="tr">Forgetful of thy own? All-pow'rful Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">Who sways the world below and heav'n above,</l>
<l n="tr">Has sent me down with this severe command:</l>
<l n="tr">What means thy ling'ring in the Libyan land?</l>
<l n="tr">If glory cannot move a mind so mean,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor future praise from flitting pleasure wean,</l>
<l n="tr">Regard the fortunes of thy rising heir:</l>
<l n="tr">The promis'd crown let young Ascanius wear,</l>
<l n="tr">To whom  th'  Ausonian scepter, and the state</l>
<l n="tr">Of <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>'s imperial name is ow'd by fate.”</l>
<l n="tr">So spoke the god; and, speaking, took his flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Involv'd in clouds, and vanish'd out of sight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="279" unit="card"/>The pious prince was seiz'd with sudden fear;</l>
<l n="tr">Mute was his tongue, and upright stood his hair.</l>
<l n="tr">Revolving in his mind the stern command,</l>
<l n="tr">He longs to fly, and loathes the charming land.</l>
<l n="tr">What should he say? or how should he begin?</l>
<l n="tr">What course, alas! remains to steer between</l>
<l n="tr">Th' offended lover and the pow'rful queen?</l>
<l n="tr">This way and that he turns his anxious mind,</l>
<l n="tr">And all expedients tries, and none can find.</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd on the deed, but doubtful of the means,</l>
<l n="tr">After long thought, to this advice he leans:</l>
<l n="tr">Three chiefs he calls, commands them to repair</l>
<l n="tr">The fleet, and ship their men with silent care;</l>
<l n="tr">Some plausible pretense he bids them find,</l>
<l n="tr">To color what in secret he design'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Himself, meantime, the softest hours would choose,</l>
<l n="tr">Before the love-sick lady heard the news;</l>
<l n="tr">And move her tender mind, by slow degrees,</l>
<l n="tr">To suffer what the sov'reign pow'r decrees:</l>
<l n="tr">Jove will inspire him, when, and what to say.</l>
<l n="tr">They hear with pleasure, and with haste obey.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="296" unit="card"/>But soon the queen perceives the thin disguise:</l>
<l n="tr">(What arts can blind a jealous woman's eyes!)</l>
<l n="tr">She was the first to find the secret fraud,</l>
<l n="tr">Before the fatal news was blaz'd abroad.</l>
<l n="tr">Love the first motions of the lover hears,</l>
<l n="tr">Quick to presage, and ev'n in safety fears.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor impious Fame was wanting to report</l>
<l n="tr">The ships repair'd, the Trojans' thick resort,</l>
<l n="tr">And purpose to forsake the Tyrian court.</l>
<l n="tr">Frantic with fear, impatient of the wound,</l>
<l n="tr">And impotent of mind, she roves the city round.</l>
<l n="tr">Less wild the Bacchanalian dames appear,</l>
<l n="tr">When, from afar, their nightly god they hear,</l>
<l n="tr">And howl about the hills, and shake the wreathy spear.</l>
<l n="tr">At length she finds the dear perfidious man;</l>
<l n="tr">Prevents his form'd excuse, and thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Base and ungrateful! could you hope to fly,</l>
<l n="tr">And undiscover'd scape a lover's eye?</l>
<l n="tr">Nor could my kindness your compassion move.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor plighted vows, nor dearer bands of love?</l>
<l n="tr">Or is the death of a despairing queen</l>
<l n="tr">Not worth preventing, tho' too well foreseen?</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n when the wintry winds command your stay,</l>
<l n="tr">You dare the tempests, and defy the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">False as you are, suppose you were not bound</l>
<l n="tr">To lands unknown, and foreign coasts to sound;</l>
<l n="tr">Were <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> restor'd, and Priam's happy reign,</l>
<l n="tr">Now durst you tempt, for <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, the raging main?</l>
<l n="tr">See whom you fly! am I the foe you shun?</l>
<l n="tr">Now, by those holy vows, so late begun,</l>
<l n="tr">By this right hand, (since I have nothing more</l>
<l n="tr">To challenge, but the faith you gave before;)</l>
<l n="tr">I beg you by these tears too truly shed,</l>
<l n="tr">By the new pleasures of our nuptial bed;</l>
<l n="tr">If ever Dido, when you most were kind,</l>
<l n="tr">Were pleasing in your eyes, or touch'd your mind;</l>
<l n="tr">By these my pray'rs, if pray'rs may yet have place,</l>
<l n="tr">Pity the fortunes of a falling race.</l>
<l n="tr">For you I have provok'd a tyrant's hate,</l>
<l n="tr">Incens'd the Libyan and the Tyrian state;</l>
<l n="tr">For you alone I suffer in my fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Bereft of honor, and expos'd to shame.</l>
<l n="tr">Whom have I now to trust, ungrateful guest?</l>
<l n="tr">(That only name remains of all the rest!)</l>
<l n="tr">What have I left? or whither can I fly?</l>
<l n="tr">Must I attend Pygmalion's cruelty,</l>
<l n="tr">Or till Hyarba shall in triumph lead</l>
<l n="tr">A queen that proudly scorn'd his proffer'd bed?</l>
<l n="tr">Had you deferr'd, at least, your hasty flight,</l>
<l n="tr">And left behind some pledge of our delight,</l>
<l n="tr">Some babe to bless the mother's mournful sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Some young Aeneas, to supply your place,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose features might express his father's face;</l>
<l n="tr">I should not then complain to live bereft</l>
<l n="tr">Of all my husband, or be wholly left.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="331" unit="card"/>Here paus'd the queen. Unmov'd he holds his eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">By Jove's command; nor suffer'd love to rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' heaving in his heart; and thus at length replies:</l>
<l n="tr">“Fair queen, you never can enough repeat</l>
<l n="tr">Your boundless favors, or I own my debt;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor can my mind forget Eliza's name,</l>
<l n="tr">While vital breath inspires this mortal frame.</l>
<l n="tr">This only let me speak in my defense:</l>
<l n="tr">I never hop'd a secret flight from hence,</l>
<l n="tr">Much less pretended to the lawful claim</l>
<l n="tr">Of sacred nuptials, or a husband's name.</l>
<l n="tr">For, if indulgent Heav'n would leave me free,</l>
<l n="tr">And not submit my life to fate's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">My choice would lead me to the Trojan shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Those relics to review, their dust adore,</l>
<l n="tr">And Priam's ruin'd palace to restore.</l>
<l n="tr">But now the Delphian oracle commands,</l>
<l n="tr">And fate invites me to the Latian lands.</l>
<l n="tr">That is the promis'd place to which I steer,</l>
<l n="tr">And all my vows are terminated there.</l>
<l n="tr">If you, a Tyrian, and a stranger born,</l>
<l n="tr">With walls and tow'rs a Libyan town adorn,</l>
<l n="tr">Why may not we—like you, a foreign race—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Like you, seek shelter in a foreign place?</l>
<l n="tr">As often as the night obscures the skies</l>
<l n="tr">With humid shades, or twinkling stars arise,</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises' angry ghost in dreams appears,</l>
<l n="tr">Chides my delay, and fills my soul with fears;</l>
<l n="tr">And young Ascanius justly may complain</l>
<l n="tr">Of his defrauded and destin'd reign.</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n now the herald of the gods appear'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Waking I saw him, and his message heard.</l>
<l n="tr">From Jove he came commission'd, heav'nly bright</l>
<l n="tr">With radiant beams, and manifest to sight</l>
<l n="tr">(The sender and the sent I both attest)</l>
<l n="tr">These walls he enter'd, and those words express'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Fair queen, oppose not what the gods command;</l>
<l n="tr">Forc'd by my fate, I leave your happy land.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="362" unit="card"/>Thus while he spoke, already she began,</l>
<l n="tr">With sparkling eyes, to view the guilty man;</l>
<l n="tr">From head to foot survey'd his person o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor longer these outrageous threats forebore:</l>
<l n="tr">“False as thou art, and, more than false, forsworn!</l>
<l n="tr">Not sprung from noble blood, nor goddess-born,</l>
<l n="tr">But hewn from harden'd entrails of a rock!</l>
<l n="tr">And rough Hyrcanian tigers gave thee suck!</l>
<l n="tr">Why should I fawn? what have I worse to fear?</l>
<l n="tr">Did he once look, or lent a list'ning ear,</l>
<l n="tr">Sigh'd when I sobb'd, or shed one kindly tear?—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">All symptoms of a base ungrateful mind,</l>
<l n="tr">So foul, that, which is worse, 't is hard to find.</l>
<l n="tr">Of man's injustice why should I complain?</l>
<l n="tr">The gods, and Jove himself, behold in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Triumphant treason; yet no thunder flies,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor Juno views my wrongs with equal eyes;</l>
<l n="tr">Faithless is earth, and faithless are the skies!</l>
<l n="tr">Justice is fled, and Truth is now no more!</l>
<l n="tr">I sav'd the shipwrack'd exile on my shore;</l>
<l n="tr">With needful food his hungry Trojans fed;</l>
<l n="tr">I took the traitor to my throne and bed:</l>
<l n="tr">Fool that I was—'t is little to repeat</l>
<l n="tr">The rest—I stor'd and rigg'd his ruin'd fleet.</l>
<l n="tr">I rave, I rave! A god's command he pleads,</l>
<l n="tr">And makes Heav'n accessary to his deeds.</l>
<l n="tr">Now Lycian lots, and now the Delian god,</l>
<l n="tr">Now Hermes is employ'd from Jove's abode,</l>
<l n="tr">To warn him hence; as if the peaceful state</l>
<l n="tr">Of heav'nly pow'rs were touch'd with human fate!</l>
<l n="tr">But go! thy flight no longer I detain—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Go seek thy promis'd kingdom thro' the main!</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, if the heav'ns will hear my pious vow,</l>
<l n="tr">The faithless waves, not half so false as thou,</l>
<l n="tr">Or secret sands, shall sepulchers afford</l>
<l n="tr">To thy proud vessels, and their perjur'd lord.</l>
<l n="tr">Then shalt thou call on injur'd Dido's name:</l>
<l n="tr">Dido shall come in a black sulph'ry flame,</l>
<l n="tr">When death has once dissolv'd her mortal frame;</l>
<l n="tr">Shall smile to see the traitor vainly weep:</l>
<l n="tr">Her angry ghost, arising from the deep,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall haunt thee waking, and disturb thy sleep.</l>
<l n="tr">At least my shade thy punishment shall know,</l>
<l n="tr">And Fame shall spread the pleasing news below.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Abruptly here she stops; then turns away</l>
<l n="tr">Her loathing eyes, and shuns the sight of day.</l>
<l n="tr">Amaz'd he stood, revolving in his mind</l>
<l n="tr">What speech to frame, and what excuse to find.</l>
<l n="tr">Her fearful maids their fainting mistress led,</l>
<l n="tr">And softly laid her on her ivory bed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="393" unit="card"/>But good Aeneas, tho' he much desir'd</l>
<l n="tr">To give that pity which her grief requir'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' much he mourn'd, and labor'd with his love,</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd at length, obeys the will of Jove;</l>
<l n="tr">Reviews his forces: they with early care</l>
<l n="tr">Unmoor their vessels, and for sea prepare.</l>
<l n="tr">The fleet is soon afloat, in all its pride,</l>
<l n="tr">And well-calk'd galleys in the harbor ride.</l>
<l n="tr">Then oaks for oars they fell'd; or, as they stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Of its green arms despoil'd the growing wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Studious of flight. The beach is cover'd o'er</l>
<l n="tr">With Trojan bands, that blacken all the shore:</l>
<l n="tr">On ev'ry side are seen, descending down,</l>
<l n="tr">Thick swarms of soldiers, loaden from the town.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, in battalia, march embodied ants,</l>
<l n="tr">Fearful of winter, and of future wants,</l>
<l n="tr">T' invade the corn, and to their cells convey</l>
<l n="tr">The plunder'd forage of their yellow prey.</l>
<l n="tr">The sable troops, along the narrow tracks,</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce bear the weighty burthen on their backs:</l>
<l n="tr">Some set their shoulders to the pond'rous grain;</l>
<l n="tr">Some guard the spoil; some lash the lagging train;</l>
<l n="tr">All ply their sev'ral tasks, and equal toil sustain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What pangs the tender breast of Dido tore,</l>
<l n="tr">When, from the tow'r, she saw the cover'd shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And heard the shouts of sailors from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd with the murmurs of the wat'ry war!</l>
<l n="tr">All-pow'rful Love! what changes canst thou cause</l>
<l n="tr">In human hearts, subjected to thy laws!</l>
<l n="tr">Once more her haughty soul the tyrant bends:</l>
<l n="tr">To pray'rs and mean submissions she descends.</l>
<l n="tr">No female arts or aids she left untried,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor counsels unexplor'd, before she died.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="416" unit="card"/>“Look, Anna! look! the Trojans crowd to sea;</l>
<l n="tr">They spread their canvas, and their anchors weigh.</l>
<l n="tr">The shouting crew their ships with garlands bind,</l>
<l n="tr">Invoke the sea gods, and invite the wind.</l>
<l n="tr">Could I have thought this threat'ning blow so near,</l>
<l n="tr">My tender soul had been forewarn'd to bear.</l>
<l n="tr">But do not you my last request deny;</l>
<l n="tr">With yon perfidious man your int'rest try,</l>
<l n="tr">And bring me news, if I must live or die.</l>
<l n="tr">You are his fav'rite; you alone can find</l>
<l n="tr">The dark recesses of his inmost mind:</l>
<l n="tr">In all his trusted secrets you have part,</l>
<l n="tr">And know the soft approaches to his heart.</l>
<l n="tr">Haste then, and humbly seek my haughty foe;</l>
<l n="tr">Tell him, I did not with the Grecians go,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did my fleet against his friends employ,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor swore the ruin of unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor mov'd with hands profane his father's dust:</l>
<l n="tr">Why should he then reject a just!</l>
<l n="tr">Whom does he shun, and whither would he fly!</l>
<l n="tr">Can he this last, this only pray'r deny!</l>
<l n="tr">Let him at least his dang'rous flight delay,</l>
<l n="tr">Wait better winds, and hope a calmer sea.</l>
<l n="tr">The nuptials he disclaims I urge no more:</l>
<l n="tr">Let him pursue the promis'd Latian shore.</l>
<l n="tr">A short delay is all I ask him now;</l>
<l n="tr">A pause of grief, an interval from woe,</l>
<l n="tr">Till my soft soul be temper'd to sustain</l>
<l n="tr">Accustom'd sorrows, and inur'd to pain.</l>
<l n="tr">If you in pity grant this one request,</l>
<l n="tr">My death shall glut the hatred of his breast.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="437" unit="card"/>This mournful message pious Anna bears,</l>
<l n="tr">And seconds with her own her sister's tears:</l>
<l n="tr">But all her arts are still employ'd in vain;</l>
<l n="tr">Again she comes, and is refus'd again.</l>
<l n="tr">His harden'd heart nor pray'rs nor threat'nings move;</l>
<l n="tr">Fate, and the god, had stopp'd his ears to love.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As, when the winds their airy quarrel try,</l>
<l n="tr">Justling from ev'ry quarter of the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">This way and that the mountain oak they bend,</l>
<l n="tr">His boughs they shatter, and his branches rend;</l>
<l n="tr">With leaves and falling mast they spread the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">The hollow valleys echo to the sound:</l>
<l n="tr">Unmov'd, the royal plant their fury mocks,</l>
<l n="tr">Or, shaken, clings more closely to the rocks;</l>
<l n="tr">Far as he shoots his tow'ring head on high,</l>
<l n="tr">So deep in earth his fix'd foundations lie.</l>
<l n="tr">No less a storm the Trojan hero bears;</l>
<l n="tr">Thick messages and loud complaints he hears,</l>
<l n="tr">And bandied words, still beating on his ears.</l>
<l n="tr">Sighs, groans, and tears proclaim his inward pains;</l>
<l n="tr">But the firm purpose of his heart remains.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="450" unit="card"/>The wretched queen, pursued by cruel fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Begins at length the light of heav'n to hate,</l>
<l n="tr">And loathes to live. Then dire portents she sees,</l>
<l n="tr">To hasten on the death her soul decrees:</l>
<l n="tr">Strange to relate! for when, before the shrine,</l>
<l n="tr">She pours in sacrifice the purple wine,</l>
<l n="tr">The purple wine is turn'd to putrid blood,</l>
<l n="tr">And the white offer'd milk converts to mud.</l>
<l n="tr">This dire presage, to her alone reveal'd,</l>
<l n="tr">From all, and ev'n her sister, she conceal'd.</l>
<l n="tr">A marble temple stood within the grove,</l>
<l n="tr">Sacred to death, and to her murther'd love;</l>
<l n="tr">That honor'd chapel she had hung around</l>
<l n="tr">With snowy fleeces, and with garlands crown'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Oft, when she visited this lonely dome,</l>
<l n="tr">Strange voices issued from her husband's tomb;</l>
<l n="tr">She thought she heard him summon her away,</l>
<l n="tr">Invite her to his grave, and chide her stay.</l>
<l n="tr">Hourly 't is heard, when with a boding note</l>
<l n="tr">The solitary screech owl strains her throat,</l>
<l n="tr">And, on a chimney's top, or turret's height,</l>
<l n="tr">With songs obscene disturbs the silence of the night.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, old prophecies augment her fears;</l>
<l n="tr">And stern Aeneas in her dreams appears,</l>
<l n="tr">Disdainful as by day: she seems, alone,</l>
<l n="tr">To wander in her sleep, thro' ways unknown,</l>
<l n="tr">Guideless and dark; or, in a desart plain,</l>
<l n="tr">To seek her subjects, and to seek in vain:</l>
<l n="tr">Like Pentheus, when, distracted with his fear,</l>
<l n="tr">He saw two suns, and double <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, appear;</l>
<l n="tr">Or mad Orestes, when his mother's ghost</l>
<l n="tr">Full in his face infernal torches toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And shook her snaky locks: he shuns the sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Flies o'er the stage, surpris'd with mortal fright;</l>
<l n="tr">The Furies guard the door and intercept his flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="474" unit="card"/>Now, sinking underneath a load of grief,</l>
<l n="tr">From death alone she seeks her last relief;</l>
<l n="tr">The time and means resolv'd within her breast,</l>
<l n="tr">She to her mournful sister thus address'd</l>
<l n="tr">(Dissembling hope, her cloudy front she clears,</l>
<l n="tr">And a false vigor in her eyes appears):</l>
<l n="tr">“Rejoice!” she said. “Instructed from above,</l>
<l n="tr">My lover I shall gain, or lose my love.</l>
<l n="tr">Nigh rising Atlas, next the falling sun,</l>
<l n="tr">Long tracts of Ethiopian climates run:</l>
<l n="tr">There a Massylian priestess I have found,</l>
<l n="tr">Honor'd for age, for magic arts renown'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Hesperian temple was her trusted care;</l>
<l n="tr">'T was she supplied the wakeful dragon's fare.</l>
<l n="tr">She poppy seeds in honey taught to steep,</l>
<l n="tr">Reclaim'd his rage, and sooth'd him into sleep.</l>
<l n="tr">She watch'd the golden fruit; her charms unbind</l>
<l n="tr">The chains of love, or fix them on the mind:</l>
<l n="tr">She stops the torrents, leaves the channel dry,</l>
<l n="tr">Repels the stars, and backward bears the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">The yawning earth rebellows to her call,</l>
<l n="tr">Pale ghosts ascend, and mountain ashes fall.</l>
<l n="tr">Witness, ye gods, and thou my better part,</l>
<l n="tr">How loth I am to try this impious art!</l>
<l n="tr">Within the secret court, with silent care,</l>
<l n="tr">Erect a lofty pile, expos'd in air:</l>
<l n="tr">Hang on the topmost part the Trojan vest,</l>
<l n="tr">Spoils, arms, and presents, of my faithless guest.</l>
<l n="tr">Next, under these, the bridal bed be plac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Where I my ruin in his arms embrac'd:</l>
<l n="tr">All relics of the wretch are doom'd to fire;</l>
<l n="tr">For so the priestess and her charms require.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus far she said, and farther speech forbears;</l>
<l n="tr">A mortal paleness in her face appears:</l>
<l n="tr">Yet the mistrustless Anna could not find</l>
<l n="tr">The secret fun'ral in these rites design'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thought so dire a rage possess'd her mind.</l>
<l n="tr">Unknowing of a train conceal'd so well,</l>
<l n="tr">She fear'd no worse than when Sichaeus fell;</l>
<l n="tr">Therefore obeys.<milestone ed="p" n="504" unit="card"/>The fatal pile they rear,</l>
<l n="tr">Within the secret court, expos'd in air.</l>
<l n="tr">The cloven holms and pines are heap'd on high,</l>
<l n="tr">And garlands on the hollow spaces lie.</l>
<l n="tr">Sad cypress, vervain, yew, compose the wreath,</l>
<l n="tr">And ev'ry baleful green denoting death.</l>
<l n="tr">The queen, determin'd to the fatal deed,</l>
<l n="tr">The spoils and sword he left, in order spread,</l>
<l n="tr">And the man's image on the nuptial bed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And now (the sacred altars plac'd around)</l>
<l n="tr">The priestess enters, with her hair unbound,</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice invokes the pow'rs below the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Night, Erebus, and Chaos she proclaims,</l>
<l n="tr">And threefold Hecate, with her hundred names,</l>
<l n="tr">And three Dianas: next, she sprinkles round</l>
<l n="tr">With feign'd Avernian drops the hallow'd ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Culls hoary simples, found by Phoebe's light,</l>
<l n="tr">With brazen sickles reap'd at noon of night;</l>
<l n="tr">Then mixes baleful juices in the bowl,</l>
<l n="tr">And cuts the forehead of a newborn foal,</l>
<l n="tr">Robbing the mother's love. The destin'd queen</l>
<l n="tr">Observes, assisting at the rites obscene;</l>
<l n="tr">A leaven'd cake in her devoted hands</l>
<l n="tr">She holds, and next the highest altar stands:</l>
<l n="tr">One tender foot was shod, her other bare;</l>
<l n="tr">Girt was her gather'd gown, and loose her hair.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus dress'd, she summon'd, with her dying breath,</l>
<l n="tr">The heav'ns and planets conscious of her death,</l>
<l n="tr">And ev'ry pow'r, if any rules above,</l>
<l n="tr">Who minds, or who revenges, injur'd love.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="522" unit="card"/>'T was dead of night, when weary bodies close</l>
<l n="tr">Their eyes in balmy sleep and soft repose:</l>
<l n="tr">The winds no longer whisper thro' the woods,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor murm'ring tides disturb the gentle floods.</l>
<l n="tr">The stars in silent order mov'd around;</l>
<l n="tr">And Peace, with downy wings, was brooding on the ground</l>
<l n="tr">The flocks and herds, and party-color'd fowl,</l>
<l n="tr">Which haunt the woods, or swim the weedy pool,</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch'd on the quiet earth, securely lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Forgetting the past labors of the day.</l>
<l n="tr">All else of nature's common gift partake:</l>
<l n="tr">Unhappy Dido was alone awake.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor sleep nor ease the furious queen can find;</l>
<l n="tr">Sleep fled her eyes, as quiet fled her mind.</l>
<l n="tr">Despair, and rage, and love divide her heart;</l>
<l n="tr">Despair and rage had some, but love the greater part.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus she said within her secret mind:</l>
<l n="tr">“What shall I do? what succor can I find?</l>
<l n="tr">Become a suppliant to Hyarba's pride,</l>
<l n="tr">And take my turn, to court and be denied?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall I with this ungrateful Trojan go,</l>
<l n="tr">Forsake an empire, and attend a foe?</l>
<l n="tr">Himself I refug'd, and his train reliev'd—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">'T is true—but am I sure to be receiv'd?</l>
<l n="tr">Can gratitude in Trojan souls have place!</l>
<l n="tr">Laomedon still lives in all his race!</l>
<l n="tr">Then, shall I seek alone the churlish crew,</l>
<l n="tr">Or with my fleet their flying sails pursue?</l>
<l n="tr">What force have I but those whom scarce before</l>
<l n="tr">I drew reluctant from their native shore?</l>
<l n="tr">Will they again embark at my desire,</l>
<l n="tr">Once more sustain the seas, and quit their second <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>?</l>
<l n="tr">Rather with steel thy guilty breast invade,</l>
<l n="tr">And take the fortune thou thyself hast made.</l>
<l n="tr">Your pity, sister, first seduc'd my mind,</l>
<l n="tr">Or seconded too well what I design'd.</l>
<l n="tr">These dear-bought pleasures had I never known,</l>
<l n="tr">Had I continued free, and still my own;</l>
<l n="tr">Avoiding love, I had not found despair,</l>
<l n="tr">But shar'd with salvage beasts the common air.</l>
<l n="tr">Like them, a lonely life I might have led,</l>
<l n="tr">Not mourn'd the living, nor disturb'd the dead.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="553" unit="card"/>These thoughts she brooded in her anxious breast.</l>
<l n="tr">On board, the Trojan found more easy rest.</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd to sail, in sleep he pass'd the night;</l>
<l n="tr">And order'd all things for his early flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To whom once more the winged god appears;</l>
<l n="tr">His former youthful mien and shape he wears,</l>
<l n="tr">And with this new alarm invades his ears:</l>
<l n="tr">“Sleep'st thou, O goddess-born! and canst thou drown</l>
<l n="tr">Thy needful cares, so near a hostile town,</l>
<l n="tr">Beset with foes; nor hear'st the western gales</l>
<l n="tr">Invite thy passage, and inspire thy sails?</l>
<l n="tr">She harbors in her heart a furious hate,</l>
<l n="tr">And thou shalt find the dire effects too late;</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd on revenge, and obstinate to die.</l>
<l n="tr">Haste swiftly hence, while thou hast pow'r to fly.</l>
<l n="tr">The sea with ships will soon be cover'd o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">And blazing firebrands kindle all the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Prevent her rage, while night obscures the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And sail before the purple morn arise.</l>
<l n="tr">Who knows what hazards thy delay may bring?</l>
<l n="tr">Woman's a various and a changeful thing.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus Hermes in the dream; then took his flight</l>
<l n="tr">Aloft in air unseen, and mix'd with night.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="571" unit="card"/>Twice warn'd by the celestial messenger,</l>
<l n="tr">The pious prince arose with hasty fear;</l>
<l n="tr">Then rous'd his drowsy train without delay:</l>
<l n="tr">“Haste to your banks; your crooked anchors weigh,</l>
<l n="tr">And spread your flying sails, and stand to sea.</l>
<l n="tr">A god commands: he stood before my sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And urg'd us once again to speedy flight.</l>
<l n="tr">O sacred pow'r, what pow'r soe'er thou art,</l>
<l n="tr">To thy blest orders I resign my heart.</l>
<l n="tr">Lead thou the way; protect thy Trojan bands,</l>
<l n="tr">And prosper the design thy will commands.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said: and, drawing forth his flaming sword,</l>
<l n="tr">His thund'ring arm divides the many-twisted cord.</l>
<l n="tr">An emulating zeal inspires his train:</l>
<l n="tr">They run; they snatch; they rush into the main.</l>
<l n="tr">With headlong haste they leave the desert shores,</l>
<l n="tr">And brush the liquid seas with lab'ring oars.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="584" unit="card"/>Aurora now had left her saffron bed,</l>
<l n="tr">And beams of early light the heav'ns o'erspread,</l>
<l n="tr">When, from a tow'r, the queen, with wakeful eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Saw day point upward from the rosy skies.</l>
<l n="tr">She look'd to seaward; but the sea was void,</l>
<l n="tr">And scarce in ken the sailing ships descried.</l>
<l n="tr">Stung with despite, and furious with despair,</l>
<l n="tr">She struck her trembling breast, and tore her hair.</l>
<l n="tr">“And shall  th'  ungrateful traitor go,” she said,</l>
<l n="tr">“My land forsaken, and my love betray'd?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall we not arm? not rush from ev'ry street,</l>
<l n="tr">To follow, sink, and burn his perjur'd fleet?</l>
<l n="tr">Haste, haul my galleys out! pursue the foe!</l>
<l n="tr">Bring flaming brands! set sail, and swiftly row!</l>
<l n="tr">What have I said? where am I? Fury turns</l>
<l n="tr">My brain; and my distemper'd bosom burns.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, when I gave my person and my throne,</l>
<l n="tr">This hate, this rage, had been more timely shown.</l>
<l n="tr">See now the promis'd faith, the vaunted name,</l>
<l n="tr">The pious man, who, rushing thro' the flame,</l>
<l n="tr">Preserv'd his gods, and to the Phrygian shore</l>
<l n="tr">The burthen of his feeble father bore!</l>
<l n="tr">I should have torn him piecemeal; strow'd in floods</l>
<l n="tr">His scatter'd limbs, or left expos'd in woods;</l>
<l n="tr">Destroy'd his friends and son; and, from the fire,</l>
<l n="tr">Have set the reeking boy before the sire.</l>
<l n="tr">Events are doubtful, which on battles wait:</l>
<l n="tr">Yet where's the doubt, to souls secure of fate?</l>
<l n="tr">My Tyrians, at their injur'd queen's command,</l>
<l n="tr">Had toss'd their fires amid the Trojan band;</l>
<l n="tr">At once extinguish'd all the faithless name;</l>
<l n="tr">And I myself, in vengeance of my shame,</l>
<l n="tr">Had fall'n upon the pile, to mend the fun'ral flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou Sun, who view'st at once the world below;</l>
<l n="tr">Thou Juno, guardian of the nuptial vow;</l>
<l n="tr">Thou Hecate hearken from thy dark abodes!</l>
<l n="tr">Ye Furies, fiends, and violated gods,</l>
<l n="tr">All pow'rs invok'd with Dido's dying breath,</l>
<l n="tr">Attend her curses and avenge her death!</l>
<l n="tr">If so the Fates ordain, Jove commands,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' ungrateful wretch should find the Latian lands,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet let a race untam'd, and haughty foes,</l>
<l n="tr">His peaceful entrance with dire arms oppose:</l>
<l n="tr">Oppress'd with numbers in  th'  unequal field,</l>
<l n="tr">His men discourag'd, and himself expell'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Let him for succor sue from place to place,</l>
<l n="tr">Torn from his subjects, and his son's embrace.</l>
<l n="tr">First, let him see his friends in battle slain,</l>
<l n="tr">And their untimely fate lament in vain;</l>
<l n="tr">And when, at length, the cruel war shall cease,</l>
<l n="tr">On hard conditions may he buy his peace:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor let him then enjoy supreme command;</l>
<l n="tr">But fall, untimely, by some hostile hand,</l>
<l n="tr">And lie unburied on the barren sand!</l>
<l n="tr">These are my pray'rs, and this my dying will;</l>
<l n="tr">And you, my Tyrians, ev'ry curse fulfil.</l>
<l n="tr">Perpetual hate and mortal wars proclaim,</l>
<l n="tr">Against the prince, the people, and the name.</l>
<l n="tr">These grateful off'rings on my grave bestow;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor league, nor love, the hostile nations know!</l>
<l n="tr">Now, and from hence, in ev'ry future age,</l>
<l n="tr">When rage excites your arms, and strength supplies the rage</l>
<l n="tr">Rise some avenger of our Libyan blood,</l>
<l n="tr">With fire and sword pursue the perjur'd brood;</l>
<l n="tr">Our arms, our seas, our shores, oppos'd to theirs;</l>
<l n="tr">And the same hate descend on all our heirs!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="630" unit="card"/>This said, within her anxious mind she weighs</l>
<l n="tr">The means of cutting short her odious days.</l>
<l n="tr">Then to Sichaeus' nurse she briefly said</l>
<l n="tr">(For, when she left her country, hers was dead):</l>
<l n="tr">“Go, <persName>Barce</persName>, call my sister. Let her care</l>
<l n="tr">The solemn rites of sacrifice prepare;</l>
<l n="tr">The sheep, and all  th'  atoning off'rings bring,</l>
<l n="tr">Sprinkling her body from the crystal spring</l>
<l n="tr">With living drops; then let her come, and thou</l>
<l n="tr">With sacred fillets bind thy hoary brow.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus will I pay my vows to Stygian Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">And end the cares of my disastrous love;</l>
<l n="tr">Then cast the Trojan image on the fire,</l>
<l n="tr">And, as that burns, my passions shall expire.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The nurse moves onward, with officious care,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the speed her aged limbs can bear.</l>
<l n="tr">But furious Dido, with dark thoughts involv'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Shook at the mighty mischief she resolv'd.</l>
<l n="tr">With livid spots distinguish'd was her face;</l>
<l n="tr">Red were her rolling eyes, and discompos'd her pace;</l>
<l n="tr">Ghastly she gaz'd, with pain she drew her breath,</l>
<l n="tr">And nature shiver'd at approaching death.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then swiftly to the fatal place she pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And mounts the fun'ral pile with furious haste;</l>
<l n="tr">Unsheathes the sword the Trojan left behind</l>
<l n="tr">(Not for so dire an enterprise design'd).</l>
<l n="tr">But when she view'd the garments loosely spread,</l>
<l n="tr">Which once he wore, and saw the conscious bed,</l>
<l n="tr">She paus'd, and with a sigh the robes embrac'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Then on the couch her trembling body cast,</l>
<l n="tr">Repress'd the ready tears, and spoke her last:</l>
<l n="tr">“Dear pledges of my love, while Heav'n so pleas'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Receive a soul, of mortal anguish eas'd:</l>
<l n="tr">My fatal course is finish'd; and I go,</l>
<l n="tr">A glorious name, among the ghosts below.</l>
<l n="tr">A lofty city by my hands is rais'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Pygmalion punish'd, and my lord appeas'd.</l>
<l n="tr">What could my fortune have afforded more,</l>
<l n="tr">Had the false Trojan never touch'd my shore!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="659" unit="card"/>Then kiss'd the couch; and, “Must I die,” she said,</l>
<l n="tr">“And unreveng'd? 'T is doubly to be dead!</l>
<l n="tr">Yet ev'n this death with pleasure I receive:</l>
<l n="tr">On any terms, 'T is better than to live.</l>
<l n="tr">These flames, from far, may the false Trojan view;</l>
<l n="tr">These boding omens his base flight pursue!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said, and struck; deep enter'd in her side</l>
<l n="tr">The piercing steel, with reeking purple dyed:</l>
<l n="tr">Clogg'd in the wound the cruel weapon stands;</l>
<l n="tr">The spouting blood came streaming on her hands.</l>
<l n="tr">Her sad attendants saw the deadly stroke,</l>
<l n="tr">And with loud cries the sounding palace shook.</l>
<l n="tr">Distracted, from the fatal sight they fled,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' the town the dismal rumor spread.</l>
<l n="tr">First from the frighted court the yell began;</l>
<l n="tr">Redoubled, thence from house to house it ran:</l>
<l n="tr">The groans of men, with shrieks, laments, and cries</l>
<l n="tr">Of mixing women, mount the vaulted skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Not less the clamor, than if—ancient <placeName key="tgn,7002862" authname="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Or the new <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, set by foes on fire—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">The rolling ruin, with their lov'd abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">Involv'd the blazing temples of their gods.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Her sister hears; and, furious with despair,</l>
<l n="tr">She beats her breast, and rends her yellow hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And, calling on Eliza's name aloud,</l>
<l n="tr">Runs breathless to the place, and breaks the crowd.</l>
<l n="tr">“Was all that pomp of woe for this prepar'd;</l>
<l n="tr">These fires, this fun'ral pile, these altars rear'd?</l>
<l n="tr">Was all this train of plots contriv'd,” said she,</l>
<l n="tr">“All only to deceive unhappy me?</l>
<l n="tr">Which is the worst? Didst thou in death pretend</l>
<l n="tr">To scorn thy sister, or delude thy friend?</l>
<l n="tr">Thy summon'd sister, and thy friend, had come;</l>
<l n="tr">One sword had serv'd us both, one common tomb:</l>
<l n="tr">Was I to raise the pile, the pow'rs invoke,</l>
<l n="tr">Not to be present at the fatal stroke?</l>
<l n="tr">At once thou hast destroy'd thyself and me,</l>
<l n="tr">Thy town, thy senate, and thy colony!</l>
<l n="tr">Bring water; bathe the wound; while I in death</l>
<l n="tr">Lay close my lips to hers, and catch the flying breath.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, she mounts the pile with eager haste,</l>
<l n="tr">And in her arms the gasping queen embrac'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Her temples chaf'd; and her own garments tore,</l>
<l n="tr">To stanch the streaming blood, and cleanse the gore.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice Dido tried to raise her drooping head,</l>
<l n="tr">And, fainting thrice, fell grov'ling on the bed;</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice op'd her heavy eyes, and sought the light,</l>
<l n="tr">But, having found it, sicken'd at the sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And clos'd her lids at last in endless night.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="693" unit="card"/>Then Juno, grieving that she should sustain</l>
<l n="tr">A death so ling'ring, and so full of pain,</l>
<l n="tr">Sent Iris down, to free her from the strife</l>
<l n="tr">Of lab'ring nature, and dissolve her life.</l>
<l n="tr">For since she died, not doom'd by Heav'n's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">Or her own crime, but human casualty,</l>
<l n="tr">And rage of love, that plung'd her in despair,</l>
<l n="tr">The Sisters had not cut the topmost hair,</l>
<l n="tr">Which Proserpine and they can only know;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor made her sacred to the shades below.</l>
<l n="tr">Downward the various goddess took her flight,</l>
<l n="tr">And drew a thousand colors from the light;</l>
<l n="tr">Then stood above the dying lover's head,</l>
<l n="tr">And said: “I thus devote thee to the dead.</l>
<l n="tr">This off'ring to  th'  infernal gods I bear.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while she spoke, she cut the fatal hair:</l>
<l n="tr">The struggling soul was loos'd, and life dissolv'd in air.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>