<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="5" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">Meantime the Trojan cuts his wat'ry way,</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd on his voyage, thro' the curling sea;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, casting back his eyes, with dire amaze,</l>
<l n="tr">Sees on the Punic shore the mounting blaze.</l>
<l n="tr">The cause unknown; yet his presaging mind</l>
<l n="tr">The fate of Dido from the fire divin'd;</l>
<l n="tr">He knew the stormy souls of womankind,</l>
<l n="tr">What secret springs their eager passions move,</l>
<l n="tr">How capable of death for injur'd love.</l>
<l n="tr">Dire auguries from hence the Trojans draw;</l>
<l n="tr">Till neither fires nor shining shores they saw.</l>
<l n="tr">Now seas and skies their prospect only bound;</l>
<l n="tr">An empty space above, a floating field around.</l>
<l n="tr">But soon the heav'ns with shadows were o'erspread;</l>
<l n="tr">A swelling cloud hung hov'ring o'er their head:</l>
<l n="tr">Livid it look'd, the threat'ning of a storm:</l>
<l n="tr">Then night and horror ocean's face deform.</l>
<l n="tr">The pilot, Palinurus, cried aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“What gusts of weather from that gath'ring cloud</l>
<l n="tr">My thoughts presage! Ere yet the tempest roars,</l>
<l n="tr">Stand to your tackle, mates, and stretch your oars;</l>
<l n="tr">Contract your swelling sails, and luff to wind.”</l>
<l n="tr">The frighted crew perform the task assign'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, to his fearless chief: “Not Heav'n,” said he,</l>
<l n="tr">“Tho' Jove himself should promise <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Can stem the torrent of this raging sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Mark how the shifting winds from west arise,</l>
<l n="tr">And what collected night involves the skies!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor can our shaken vessels live at sea,</l>
<l n="tr">Much less against the tempest force their way.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is fate diverts our course, and fate we must obey.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from hence, if I observ'd aright</l>
<l n="tr">The southing of the stars, and polar light,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicilia</placeName> lies, whose hospitable shores</l>
<l n="tr">In safety we may reach with struggling oars.”</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas then replied: “Too sure I find</l>
<l n="tr">We strive in vain against the seas and wind:</l>
<l n="tr">Now shift your sails; what place can please me more</l>
<l n="tr">Than what you promise, the Sicilian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose hallow'd earth Anchises' bones contains,</l>
<l n="tr">And where a prince of Trojan lineage reigns?”</l>
<l n="tr">The course resolv'd, before the western wind</l>
<l n="tr">They scud amain, and make the port assign'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="35" unit="card"/>Meantime Acestes, from a lofty stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Beheld the fleet descending on the land;</l>
<l n="tr">And, not unmindful of his ancient race,</l>
<l n="tr">Down from the cliff he ran with eager pace,</l>
<l n="tr">And held the hero in a strict embrace.</l>
<l n="tr">Of a rough Libyan bear the spoils he wore,</l>
<l n="tr">And either hand a pointed jav'lin bore.</l>
<l n="tr">His mother was a dame of Dardan blood;</l>
<l n="tr">His sire Crinisus, a Sicilian flood.</l>
<l n="tr">He welcomes his returning friends ashore</l>
<l n="tr">With plenteous country cates and homely store.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="42" unit="card"/>Now, when the following morn had chas'd away</l>
<l n="tr">The flying stars, and light restor'd the day,</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas call'd the Trojan troops around,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus bespoke them from a rising ground:</l>
<l n="tr">“Offspring of heav'n, divine Dardanian race!</l>
<l n="tr">The sun, revolving thro'  th'  ethereal space,</l>
<l n="tr">The shining circle of the year has fill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Since first this isle my father's ashes held:</l>
<l n="tr">And now the rising day renews the year;</l>
<l n="tr">A day for ever sad, for ever dear.</l>
<l n="tr">This would I celebrate with annual games,</l>
<l n="tr">With gifts on altars pil'd, and holy flames,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' banish'd to Gaetulia's barren sands,</l>
<l n="tr">Caught on the Grecian seas, or hostile lands:</l>
<l n="tr">But since this happy storm our fleet has driv'n</l>
<l n="tr">(Not, as I deem, without the will of Heav'n)</l>
<l n="tr">Upon these friendly shores and flow'ry plains,</l>
<l n="tr">Which hide Anchises and his blest remains,</l>
<l n="tr">Let us with joy perform his honors due,</l>
<l n="tr">And pray for prosp'rous winds, our voyage to renew;</l>
<l n="tr">Pray, that in towns and temples of our own,</l>
<l n="tr">The name of great Anchises may be known,</l>
<l n="tr">And yearly games may spread the gods' renown.</l>
<l n="tr">Our sports Acestes, of the Trojan race,</l>
<l n="tr">With royal gifts ordain'd, is pleas'd to grace:</l>
<l n="tr">Two steers on ev'ry ship the king bestows;</l>
<l n="tr">His gods and ours shall share your equal vows.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, if, nine days hence, the rosy morn</l>
<l n="tr">Shall with unclouded light the skies adorn,</l>
<l n="tr">That day with solemn sports I mean to grace:</l>
<l n="tr">Light galleys on the seas shall run a wat'ry race;</l>
<l n="tr">Some shall in swiftness for the goal contend,</l>
<l n="tr">And others try the twanging bow to bend;</l>
<l n="tr">The strong, with iron gauntlets arm'd, shall stand</l>
<l n="tr">Oppos'd in combat on the yellow sand.</l>
<l n="tr">Let all be present at the games prepar'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And joyful victors wait the just reward.</l>
<l n="tr">But now assist the rites, with garlands crown'd.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="72" unit="card"/>He said, and first his brows with myrtle bound.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Helymus, by his example led,</l>
<l n="tr">And old Acestes, each adorn'd his head;</l>
<l n="tr">Thus young Ascanius, with a sprightly grace,</l>
<l n="tr">His temples tied, and all the Trojan race.</l>
<l n="tr"> Aeneas then advanc'd amidst the train,</l>
<l n="tr">By thousands follow'd thro' the flow'ry plain,</l>
<l n="tr">To great Anchises' tomb; which when he found,</l>
<l n="tr">He pour'd to Bacchus, on the hallow'd ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Two bowls of sparkling wine, of milk two more,</l>
<l n="tr">And two (from offer'd bulls) of purple gore,</l>
<l n="tr">With roses then the sepulcher he strow'd</l>
<l n="tr">And thus his father's ghost bespoke aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“Hail, O ye holy manes! hail again,</l>
<l n="tr">Paternal ashes, now review'd in vain!</l>
<l n="tr">The gods permitted not, that you, with me,</l>
<l n="tr">Should reach the promis'd shores of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Or <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s flood, what flood soe'er it be.”</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had he finish'd, when, with speckled pride,</l>
<l n="tr">A serpent from the tomb began to glide;</l>
<l n="tr">His hugy bulk on sev'n high volumes roll'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Blue was his breadth of back, but streak'd with scaly gold:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus riding on his curls, he seem'd to pass</l>
<l n="tr">A rolling fire along, and singe the grass.</l>
<l n="tr">More various colors thro' his body run,</l>
<l n="tr">Than Iris when her bow imbibes the sun.</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the rising altars, and around,</l>
<l n="tr">The sacred monster shot along the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">With harmless play amidst the bowls he pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And with his lolling tongue assay'd the taste:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus fed with holy food, the wondrous guest</l>
<l n="tr">Within the hollow tomb retir'd to rest.</l>
<l n="tr">The pious prince, surpris'd at what he view'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The fun'ral honors with more zeal renew'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Doubtful if this place's genius were,</l>
<l n="tr">Or guardian of his father's sepulcher.</l>
<l n="tr">Five sheep, according to the rites, he slew;</l>
<l n="tr">As many swine, and steers of sable hue;</l>
<l n="tr">New gen'rous wine he from the goblets pour'd.</l>
<l n="tr">And call'd his father's ghost, from hell restor'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The glad attendants in long order come,</l>
<l n="tr">Off'ring their gifts at great Anchises' tomb:</l>
<l n="tr">Some add more oxen: some divide the spoil;</l>
<l n="tr">Some place the chargers on the grassy soil;</l>
<l n="tr">Some blow the fires, and off entrails broil.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="104" unit="card"/>Now came the day desir'd. The skies were bright</l>
<l n="tr">With rosy luster of the rising light:</l>
<l n="tr">The bord'ring people, rous'd by sounding fame</l>
<l n="tr">Of Trojan feasts and great Acestes' name,</l>
<l n="tr">The crowded shore with acclamations fill,</l>
<l n="tr">Part to behold, and part to prove their skill.</l>
<l n="tr">And first the gifts in public view they place,</l>
<l n="tr">Green laurel wreaths, and palm, the victors' grace:</l>
<l n="tr">Within the circle, arms and tripods lie,</l>
<l n="tr">Ingots of gold and silver, heap'd on high,</l>
<l n="tr">And vests embroider'd, of the Tyrian dye.</l>
<l n="tr">The trumpet's clangor then the feast proclaims,</l>
<l n="tr">And all prepare for their appointed games.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="114" unit="card"/>Four galleys first, which equal rowers bear,</l>
<l n="tr">Advancing, in the wat'ry lists appear.</l>
<l n="tr">The speedy Dolphin, that outstrips the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">Bore Mnestheus, author of the Memmian kind:</l>
<l n="tr">Gyas the vast Chimaera's bulk commands,</l>
<l n="tr">Which rising, like a tow'ring city stands;</l>
<l n="tr">Three Trojans tug at ev'ry lab'ring oar;</l>
<l n="tr">Three banks in three degrees the sailors bore;</l>
<l n="tr">Beneath their sturdy strokes the billows roar.</l>
<l n="tr">Sergesthus, who began the Sergian race,</l>
<l n="tr">In the great Centaur took the leading place;</l>
<l n="tr">Cloanthus on the sea-green Scylla stood,</l>
<l n="tr">From whom Cluentius draws his Trojan blood.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="124" unit="card"/>Far in the sea, against the foaming shore,</l>
<l n="tr">There stands a rock: the raging billows roar</l>
<l n="tr">Above his head in storms; but, when 't is clear,</l>
<l n="tr">Uncurl their ridgy backs, and at his foot appear.</l>
<l n="tr">In peace below the gentle waters run;</l>
<l n="tr">The cormorants above lie basking in the sun.</l>
<l n="tr">On this the hero fix'd an oak in sight,</l>
<l n="tr">The mark to guide the mariners aright.</l>
<l n="tr">To bear with this, the seamen stretch their oars;</l>
<l n="tr">Then round the rock they steer, and seek the former shores.</l>
<l n="tr">The lots decide their place. Above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Each leader shining in his Tyrian vest;</l>
<l n="tr">The common crew with wreaths of poplar boughs</l>
<l n="tr">Their temples crown, and shade their sweaty brows:</l>
<l n="tr">Besmear'd with oil, their naked shoulders shine.</l>
<l n="tr">All take their seats, and wait the sounding sign:</l>
<l n="tr">They gripe their oars; and ev'ry panting breast</l>
<l n="tr">Is rais'd by turns with hope, by turns with fear depress'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The clangor of the trumpet gives the sign;</l>
<l n="tr">At once they start, advancing in a line:</l>
<l n="tr">With shouts the sailors rend the starry skies;</l>
<l n="tr">Lash'd with their oars, the smoky billows rise;</l>
<l n="tr">Sparkles the briny main, and the vex'd ocean fries.</l>
<l n="tr">Exact in time, with equal strokes they row:</l>
<l n="tr">At once the brushing oars and brazen prow</l>
<l n="tr">Dash up the sandy waves, and ope the depths below.</l>
<l n="tr">Not fiery coursers, in a chariot race,</l>
<l n="tr">Invade the field with half so swift a pace;</l>
<l n="tr">Not the fierce driver with more fury lends</l>
<l n="tr">The sounding lash, and, ere the stroke descends,</l>
<l n="tr">Low to the wheels his pliant body bends.</l>
<l n="tr">The partial crowd their hopes and fears divide,</l>
<l n="tr">And aid with eager shouts the favor'd side.</l>
<l n="tr">Cries, murmurs, clamors, with a mixing sound,</l>
<l n="tr">From woods to woods, from hills to hills rebound.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="151" unit="card"/>Amidst the loud applauses of the shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Gyas outstripp'd the rest, and sprung before:</l>
<l n="tr">Cloanthus, better mann'd, pursued him fast,</l>
<l n="tr">But his o'er-masted galley check'd his haste.</l>
<l n="tr">The Centaur and the Dolphin brush the brine</l>
<l n="tr">With equal oars, advancing in a line;</l>
<l n="tr">And now the mighty Centaur seems to lead,</l>
<l n="tr">And now the speedy Dolphin gets ahead;</l>
<l n="tr">Now board to board the rival vessels row,</l>
<l n="tr">The billows lave the skies, and ocean groans below.</l>
<l n="tr">They reach'd the mark. Proud Gyas and his train</l>
<l n="tr">In triumph rode, the victors of the main;</l>
<l n="tr">But, steering round, he charg'd his pilot stand</l>
<l n="tr">More close to shore, and skim along the sand—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">“Let others bear to sea!” Menoetes heard;</l>
<l n="tr">But secret shelves too cautiously he fear'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, fearing, sought the deep; and still aloof he steer'd.</l>
<l n="tr">With louder cries the captain call'd again:</l>
<l n="tr">“Bear to the rocky shore, and shun the main.”</l>
<l n="tr">He spoke, and, speaking, at his stern he saw</l>
<l n="tr">The bold Cloanthus near the shelvings draw.</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the mark and him the Scylla stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a closer compass plow'd the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">He pass'd the mark; and, wheeling, got before:</l>
<l n="tr">Gyas blasphem'd the gods, devoutly swore,</l>
<l n="tr">Cried out for anger, and his hair he tore.</l>
<l n="tr">Mindless of others' lives (so high was grown</l>
<l n="tr">His rising rage) and careless of his own,</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling dotard to the deck he drew;</l>
<l n="tr">Then hoisted up, and overboard he threw:</l>
<l n="tr">This done, he seiz'd the helm; his fellows cheer'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Turn'd short upon the shelfs, and madly steer'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hardly his head the plunging pilot rears,</l>
<l n="tr">Clogg'd with his clothes, and cumber'd with his years:</l>
<l n="tr">Now dropping wet, he climbs the cliff with pain.</l>
<l n="tr">The crowd, that saw him fall and float again,</l>
<l n="tr">Shout from the distant shore; and loudly laugh'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To see his heaving breast disgorge the briny draught.</l>
<l n="tr">The following Centaur, and the Dolphin's crew,</l>
<l n="tr">Their vanish'd hopes of victory renew;</l>
<l n="tr">While Gyas lags, they kindle in the race,</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="183" unit="card"/>To reach the mark. Sergesthus takes the place;</l>
<l n="tr">Mnestheus pursues; and while around they wind,</l>
<l n="tr">Comes up, not half his galley's length behind;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, on the deck, amidst his mates appear'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus their drooping courage he cheer'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“My friends, and Hector's followers heretofore,</l>
<l n="tr">Exert your vigor; tug the lab'ring oar;</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch to your strokes, my still unconquer'd crew,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom from the flaming walls of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> I drew.</l>
<l n="tr">In this, our common int'rest, let me find</l>
<l n="tr">That strength of hand, that courage of the mind,</l>
<l n="tr">As when you stemm'd the strong Malean flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er the Syrtes' broken billows row'd.</l>
<l n="tr">I seek not now the foremost palm to gain;</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' yeT'mdash;but, ah! that haughty wish is vain!</l>
<l n="tr">Let those enjoy it whom the gods ordain.</l>
<l n="tr">But to be last, the lags of all the race!—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Redeem yourselves and me from that disgrace.”</l>
<l n="tr">Now, one and all, they tug amain; they row</l>
<l n="tr">At the full stretch, and shake the brazen prow.</l>
<l n="tr">The sea beneath 'em sinks; their lab'ring sides</l>
<l n="tr">Are swell'd, and sweat runs gutt'ring down in tides.</l>
<l n="tr">Chance aids their daring with unhop'd success;</l>
<l n="tr">Sergesthus, eager with his beak to press</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the rival galley and the rock,</l>
<l n="tr">Shuts up  th'  unwieldly Centaur in the lock.</l>
<l n="tr">The vessel struck; and, with the dreadful shock,</l>
<l n="tr">Her oars she shiver'd, and her head she broke.</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling rowers from their banks arise,</l>
<l n="tr">And, anxious for themselves, renounce the prize.</l>
<l n="tr">With iron poles they heave her off the shores,</l>
<l n="tr">And gather from the sea their floating oars.</l>
<l n="tr">The crew of Mnestheus, with elated minds,</l>
<l n="tr">Urge their success, and call the willing winds;</l>
<l n="tr">Then ply their oars, and cut their liquid way</l>
<l n="tr">In larger compass on the roomy sea.</l>
<l n="tr">As, when the dove her rocky hold forsakes,</l>
<l n="tr">Rous'd in a fright, her sounding wings she shakes;</l>
<l n="tr">The cavern rings with clatt'ring; out she flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And leaves her callow care, and cleaves the skies:</l>
<l n="tr">At first she flutters; but at length she springs</l>
<l n="tr">To smoother flight, and shoots upon her wings:</l>
<l n="tr">So Mnestheus in the Dolphin cuts the sea;</l>
<l n="tr">And, flying with a force, that force assists his way.</l>
<l n="tr">Sergesthus in the Centaur soon he pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Wedg'd in the rocky shoals, and sticking fast.</l>
<l n="tr">In vain the victor he with cries implores,</l>
<l n="tr">And practices to row with shatter'd oars.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Mnestheus bears with Gyas, and outflies:</l>
<l n="tr">The ship, without a pilot, yields the prize.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="225" unit="card"/>Unvanquish'd Scylla now alone remains;</l>
<l n="tr">Her he pursues, and all his vigor strains.</l>
<l n="tr">Shouts from the fav'ring multitude arise;</l>
<l n="tr">Applauding Echo to the shouts replies;</l>
<l n="tr">Shouts, wishes, and applause run rattling thro' the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">These clamors with disdain the Scylla heard,</l>
<l n="tr">Much grudg'd the praise, but more the robb'd reward:</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd to hold their own, they mend their pace,</l>
<l n="tr">All obstinate to die, or gain the race.</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd with success, the Dolphin swiftly ran;</l>
<l n="tr">For they can conquer, who believe they can.</l>
<l n="tr">Both urge their oars, and fortune both supplies,</l>
<l n="tr">And both perhaps had shar'd an equal prize;</l>
<l n="tr">When to the seas Cloanthus holds his hands,</l>
<l n="tr">And succor from the wat'ry pow'rs demands:</l>
<l n="tr">“Gods of the liquid realms, on which I row!</l>
<l n="tr">If, giv'n by you, the laurel bind my brow,</l>
<l n="tr">Assist to make me guilty of my vow!</l>
<l n="tr">A snow-white bull shall on your shore be slain;</l>
<l n="tr">His offer'd entrails cast into the main,</l>
<l n="tr">And ruddy wine, from golden goblets thrown,</l>
<l n="tr">Your grateful gift and my return shall own.”</l>
<l n="tr">The choir of nymphs, and Phorcus, from below,</l>
<l n="tr">With virgin Panopea, heard his vow;</l>
<l n="tr">And old Portunus, with his breadth of hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Push'd on, and sped the galley to the land.</l>
<l n="tr">Swift as a shaft, or winged wind, she flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And, darting to the port, obtains the prize.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="244" unit="card"/>The herald summons all, and then proclaims</l>
<l n="tr">Cloanthus conqu'ror of the naval games.</l>
<l n="tr">The prince with laurel crowns the victor's head,</l>
<l n="tr">And three fat steers are to his vessel led,</l>
<l n="tr">The ship's reward; with gen'rous wine beside,</l>
<l n="tr">And sums of silver, which the crew divide.</l>
<l n="tr">The leaders are distinguish'd from the rest;</l>
<l n="tr">The victor honor'd with a nobler vest,</l>
<l n="tr">Where gold and purple strive in equal rows,</l>
<l n="tr">And needlework its happy cost bestows.</l>
<l n="tr">There Ganymede is wrought with living art,</l>
<l n="tr">Chasing thro' Ida's groves the trembling hart:</l>
<l n="tr">Breathless he seems, yet eager to pursue;</l>
<l n="tr">When from aloft descends, in open view,</l>
<l n="tr">The bird of Jove, and, sousing on his prey,</l>
<l n="tr">With crooked talons bears the boy away.</l>
<l n="tr">In vain, with lifted hands and gazing eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">His guards behold him soaring thro' the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And dogs pursue his flight with imitated cries.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Mnestheus the second victor was declar'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And, summon'd there, the second prize he shard.</l>
<l n="tr">A coat of mail, brave Demoleus bore,</l>
<l n="tr">More brave Aeneas from his shoulders tore,</l>
<l n="tr">In single combat on the Trojan shore:</l>
<l n="tr">This was ordain'd for Mnestheus to possess;</l>
<l n="tr">In war for his defense, for ornament in peace.</l>
<l n="tr">Rich was the gift, and glorious to behold,</l>
<l n="tr">But yet so pond'rous with its plates of gold,</l>
<l n="tr">That scarce two servants could the weight sustain;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, loaded thus, Demoleus o'er the plain</l>
<l n="tr">Pursued and lightly seiz'd the Trojan train.</l>
<l n="tr">The third, succeeding to the last reward,</l>
<l n="tr">Two goodly bowls of massy silver shar'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With figures prominent, and richly wrought,</l>
<l n="tr">And two brass caldrons from <placeName key="perseus,Dodona" authname="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> brought.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus all, rewarded by the hero's hands,</l>
<l n="tr">Their conqu'ring temples bound with purple bands;</l>
<l n="tr">And now Sergesthus, clearing from the rock,</l>
<l n="tr">Brought back his galley shatter'd with the shock.</l>
<l n="tr">Forlorn she look'd, without an aiding oar,</l>
<l n="tr">And, houted by the vulgar, made to shore.</l>
<l n="tr">As when a snake, surpris'd upon the road,</l>
<l n="tr">Is crush'd athwart her body by the load</l>
<l n="tr">Of heavy wheels; or with a mortal wound</l>
<l n="tr">Her belly bruis'd, and trodden to the ground:</l>
<l n="tr">In vain, with loosen'd curls, she crawls along;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, fierce above, she brandishes her tongue;</l>
<l n="tr">Glares with her eyes, and bristles with her scales;</l>
<l n="tr">But, groveling in the dust, her parts unsound she trails:</l>
<l n="tr">So slowly to the port the Centaur tends,</l>
<l n="tr">But, what she wants in oars, with sails amends.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, for his galley sav'd, the grateful prince</l>
<l n="tr">Is pleas'd  th'  unhappy chief to recompense.</l>
<l n="tr">Pholoe, the Cretan slave, rewards his care,</l>
<l n="tr">Beauteous herself, with lovely twins as fair.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="286" unit="card"/>From thence his way the Trojan hero bent</l>
<l n="tr">Into the neighb'ring plain, with mountains pent,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose sides were shaded with surrounding wood.</l>
<l n="tr">Full in the midst of this fair valley stood</l>
<l n="tr">A native theater, which, rising slow</l>
<l n="tr">By just degrees, o'erlook'd the ground below.</l>
<l n="tr">High on a sylvan throne the leader sate;</l>
<l n="tr">A num'rous train attend in solemn state.</l>
<l n="tr">Here those that in the rapid course delight,</l>
<l n="tr">Desire of honor and the prize invite.</l>
<l n="tr">The rival runners without order stand;</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans mix'd with the Sicilian band.</l>
<l n="tr">First Nisus, with Euryalus, appears;</l>
<l n="tr">Euryalus a boy of blooming years,</l>
<l n="tr">With sprightly grace and equal beauty crown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Nisus, for friendship to the youth renown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Diores next, of Priam's royal race,</l>
<l n="tr">Then Salius joined with Patron, took their place;</l>
<l n="tr">(But Patron in <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName> had his birth,</l>
<l n="tr">And Salius his from Arcananian earth;)</l>
<l n="tr">Then two Sicilian youths—the names of these,</l>
<l n="tr">Swift Helymus, and lovely Panopes:</l>
<l n="tr">Both jolly huntsmen, both in forest bred,</l>
<l n="tr">And owning old Acestes for their head;</l>
<l n="tr">With sev'ral others of ignobler name,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom time has not deliver'd o'er to fame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To these the hero thus his thoughts explain'd,</l>
<l n="tr">In words which gen'ral approbation gain'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“One common largess is for all design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">(The vanquish'd and the victor shall be join'd,)</l>
<l n="tr">Two darts of polish'd steel and Gnosian wood,</l>
<l n="tr">A silver-studded ax, alike bestow'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The foremost three have olive wreaths decreed:</l>
<l n="tr">The first of these obtains a stately steed,</l>
<l n="tr">Adorn'd with trappings; and the next in fame,</l>
<l n="tr">The quiver of an Amazonian dame,</l>
<l n="tr">With feather'd Thracian arrows well supplied:</l>
<l n="tr">A golden belt shall gird his manly side,</l>
<l n="tr">Which with a sparkling diamond shall be tied.</l>
<l n="tr">The third this Grecian helmet shall content.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="315" unit="card"/>He said. To their appointed base they went;</l>
<l n="tr">With beating hearts  th'  expected sign receive,</l>
<l n="tr">And, starting all at once, the barrier leave.</l>
<l n="tr">Spread out, as on the winged winds, they flew,</l>
<l n="tr">And seiz'd the distant goal with greedy view.</l>
<l n="tr">Shot from the crowd, swift Nisus all o'erpass'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor storms, nor thunder, equal half his haste.</l>
<l n="tr">The next, but tho' the next, yet far disjoin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Came Salius, and Euryalus behind;</l>
<l n="tr">Then Helymus, whom young Diores plied,</l>
<l n="tr">Step after step, and almost side by side,</l>
<l n="tr">His shoulders pressing; and, in longer space,</l>
<l n="tr">Had won, or left at least a dubious race.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, spent, the goal they almost reach at last,</l>
<l n="tr">When eager Nisus, hapless in his haste,</l>
<l n="tr">Slipp'd first, and, slipping, fell upon the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Soak'd with the blood of oxen newly slain.</l>
<l n="tr">The careless victor had not mark'd his way;</l>
<l n="tr">But, treading where the treach'rous puddle lay,</l>
<l n="tr">His heels flew up; and on the grassy floor</l>
<l n="tr">He fell, besmear'd with filth and holy gore.</l>
<l n="tr">Not mindless then, Euryalus, of thee,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor of the sacred bonds of amity,</l>
<l n="tr">He strove  th'  immediate rival's hope to cross,</l>
<l n="tr">And caught the foot of Salius as he rose.</l>
<l n="tr">So Salius lay extended on the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Euryalus springs out, the prize to gain,</l>
<l n="tr">And leaves the crowd: applauding peals attend</l>
<l n="tr">The victor to the goal, who vanquish'd by his friend.</l>
<l n="tr">Next Helymus; and then Diores came,</l>
<l n="tr">By two misfortunes made the third in fame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But Salius enters, and, exclaiming loud</l>
<l n="tr">For justice, deafens and disturbs the crowd;</l>
<l n="tr">Urges his cause may in the court be heard;</l>
<l n="tr">And pleads the prize is wrongfully conferr'd.</l>
<l n="tr">But favor for Euryalus appears;</l>
<l n="tr">His blooming beauty, with his tender tears,</l>
<l n="tr">Had brib'd the judges for the promis'd prize.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, Diores fills the court with cries,</l>
<l n="tr">Who vainly reaches at the last reward,</l>
<l n="tr">If the first palm on Salius be conferr'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="348" unit="card"/>Then thus the prince: “Let no disputes arise:</l>
<l n="tr">Where fortune plac'd it, I award the prize.</l>
<l n="tr">But fortune's errors give me leave to mend,</l>
<l n="tr">At least to pity my deserving friend.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and, from among the spoils, he draws</l>
<l n="tr">(Pond'rous with shaggy mane and golden paws)</l>
<l n="tr">A lion's hide: to Salius this he gives.</l>
<l n="tr">Nisus with envy sees the gift, and grieves.</l>
<l n="tr">“If such rewards to vanquish'd men are due.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, “and falling is to rise by you,</l>
<l n="tr">What prize may Nisus from your bounty claim,</l>
<l n="tr">Who merited the first rewards and fame?</l>
<l n="tr">In falling, both an equal fortune tried;</l>
<l n="tr">Would fortune for my fall so well provide!”</l>
<l n="tr">With this he pointed to his face, and show'd</l>
<l n="tr">His hand and all his habit smear'd with blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' indulgent father of the people smil'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And caus'd to be produc'd an ample shield,</l>
<l n="tr">Of wondrous art, by Didymaon wrought,</l>
<l n="tr">Long since from Neptune's bars in triumph brought.</l>
<l n="tr">This giv'n to Nisus, he divides the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">And equal justice in his gifts express'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="362" unit="card"/>The race thus ended, and rewards bestow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Once more the princes bespeaks  th'  attentive crowd:</l>
<l n="tr">“If there he here whose dauntless courage dare</l>
<l n="tr">In gauntlet-fight, with limbs and body bare,</l>
<l n="tr">His opposite sustain in open view,</l>
<l n="tr">Stand forth the champion, and the games renew.</l>
<l n="tr">Two prizes I propose, and thus divide:</l>
<l n="tr">A bull with gilded horns, and fillets tied,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall be the portion of the conqu'ring chief;</l>
<l n="tr">A sword and helm shall cheer the loser's grief.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then haughty Dares in the lists appears;</l>
<l n="tr">Stalking he strides, his head erected bears:</l>
<l n="tr">His nervous arms the weighty gauntlet wield,</l>
<l n="tr">And loud applauses echo thro' the field.</l>
<l n="tr">Dares alone in combat us'd to stand</l>
<l n="tr">The match of mighty <persName>Paris</persName>, hand to hand;</l>
<l n="tr">The same, at Hector's fun'rals, undertook</l>
<l n="tr">Gigantic Butes, of  th'  Amycian stock,</l>
<l n="tr">And, by the stroke of his resistless hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch'd the vast bulk upon the yellow sand.</l>
<l n="tr">Such Dares was; and such he strode along,</l>
<l n="tr">And drew the wonder of the gazing throng.</l>
<l n="tr">His brawny back and ample breast he shows,</l>
<l n="tr">His lifted arms around his head he throws,</l>
<l n="tr">And deals in whistling air his empty blows.</l>
<l n="tr">His match is sought; but, thro' the trembling band,</l>
<l n="tr">Not one dares answer to the proud demand.</l>
<l n="tr">Presuming of his force, with sparkling eyes</l>
<l n="tr">Already he devours the promis'd prize.</l>
<l n="tr">He claims the bull with awless insolence,</l>
<l n="tr">And having seiz'd his horns, accosts the prince:</l>
<l n="tr">“If none my matchless valor dares oppose,</l>
<l n="tr">How long shall Dares wait his dastard foes?</l>
<l n="tr">Permit me, chief, permit without delay,</l>
<l n="tr">To lead this uncontended gift away.”</l>
<l n="tr">The crowd assents, and with redoubled cries</l>
<l n="tr">For the proud challenger demands the prize.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="387" unit="card"/>Acestes, fir'd with just disdain, to see</l>
<l n="tr">The palm usurp'd without a victory,</l>
<l n="tr">Reproach'd Entellus thus, who sate beside,</l>
<l n="tr">And heard and saw, unmov'd, the Trojan's pride:</l>
<l n="tr">“Once, but in vain, a champion of renown,</l>
<l n="tr">So tamely can you bear the ravish'd crown,</l>
<l n="tr">A prize in triumph borne before your sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And shun, for fear, the danger of the fight?</l>
<l n="tr">Where is our <placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName> now, the boasted name,</l>
<l n="tr">The god who taught your thund'ring arm the game?</l>
<l n="tr">Where now your baffled honor? Where the spoil</l>
<l n="tr">That fill'd your house, and fame that fill'd our isle?”</l>
<l n="tr">Entellus, thus: “My soul is still the same,</l>
<l n="tr">Unmov'd with fear, and mov'd with martial fame;</l>
<l n="tr">But my chill blood is curdled in my veins,</l>
<l n="tr">And scarce the shadow of a man remains.</l>
<l n="tr">O could I turn to that fair prime again,</l>
<l n="tr">That prime of which this boaster is so vain,</l>
<l n="tr">The brave, who this decrepid age defies,</l>
<l n="tr">Should feel my force, without the promis'd prize.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He said; and, rising at the word, he threw</l>
<l n="tr">Two pond'rous gauntlets down in open view;</l>
<l n="tr">Gauntlets which <placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName> wont in fight to wield,</l>
<l n="tr">And sheathe his hands with in the listed field.</l>
<l n="tr">With fear and wonder seiz'd, the crowd beholds</l>
<l n="tr">The gloves of death, with sev'n distinguish'd folds</l>
<l n="tr">Of tough bull hides; the space within is spread</l>
<l n="tr">With iron, or with loads of heavy lead:</l>
<l n="tr">Dares himself was daunted at the sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Renounc'd his challenge, and refus'd to fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Astonish'd at their weight, the hero stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And pois'd the pond'rous engines in his hands.</l>
<l n="tr">“What had your wonder,” said Entellus, “been,</l>
<l n="tr">Had you the gauntlets of Alcides seen,</l>
<l n="tr">Or view'd the stern debate on this unhappy green!</l>
<l n="tr">These which I bear your brother <placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName> bore,</l>
<l n="tr">Still mark'd with batter'd brains and mingled gore.</l>
<l n="tr">With these he long sustain'd  th'  Herculean arm;</l>
<l n="tr">And these I wielded while my blood was warm,</l>
<l n="tr">This languish'd frame while better spirits fed,</l>
<l n="tr">Ere age unstrung my nerves, or time o'ersnow'd my head.</l>
<l n="tr">But if the challenger these arms refuse,</l>
<l n="tr">And cannot wield their weight, or dare not use;</l>
<l n="tr">If great Aeneas and Acestes join</l>
<l n="tr">In his request, these gauntlets I resign;</l>
<l n="tr">Let us with equal arms perform the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">And let him leave to fear, since I resign my right.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="421" unit="card"/>This said, Entellus for the strife prepares;</l>
<l n="tr">Stripp'd of his quilted coat, his body bares;</l>
<l n="tr">Compos'd of mighty bones and brawn he stands,</l>
<l n="tr">A goodly tow'ring object on the sands.</l>
<l n="tr">Then just Aeneas equal arms supplied,</l>
<l n="tr">Which round their shoulders to their wrists they tied.</l>
<l n="tr">Both on the tiptoe stand, at full extent,</l>
<l n="tr">Their arms aloft, their bodies inly bent;</l>
<l n="tr">Their heads from aiming blows they bear afar;</l>
<l n="tr">With clashing gauntlets then provoke the war.</l>
<l n="tr">One on his youth and pliant limbs relies;</l>
<l n="tr">One on his sinews and his giant size.</l>
<l n="tr">The last is stiff with age, his motion slow;</l>
<l n="tr">He heaves for breath, he staggers to and fro,</l>
<l n="tr">And clouds of issuing smoke his nostrils loudly blow.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet equal in success, they ward, they strike;</l>
<l n="tr">Their ways are diff'rent, but their art alike.</l>
<l n="tr">Before, behind, the blows are dealt; around</l>
<l n="tr">Their hollow sides the rattling thumps resound.</l>
<l n="tr">A storm of strokes, well meant, with fury flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And errs about their temples, ears, and eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor always errs; for oft the gauntlet draws</l>
<l n="tr">A sweeping stroke along the crackling jaws.</l>
<l n="tr">Heavy with age, Entellus stands his ground,</l>
<l n="tr">But with his warping body wards the wound.</l>
<l n="tr">His hand and watchful eye keep even pace;</l>
<l n="tr">While Dares traverses and shifts his place,</l>
<l n="tr">And, like a captain who beleaguers round</l>
<l n="tr">Some strong-built castle on a rising ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Views all  th'  approaches with observing eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">This and that other part in vain he tries,</l>
<l n="tr">And more on industry than force relies.</l>
<l n="tr">With hands on high, Entellus threats the foe;</l>
<l n="tr">But Dares watch'd the motion from below,</l>
<l n="tr">And slipp'd aside, and shunn'd the long descending blow.</l>
<l n="tr">Entellus wastes his forces on the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">And, thus deluded of the stroke design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Headlong and heavy fell; his ample breast</l>
<l n="tr">And weighty limbs his ancient mother press'd.</l>
<l n="tr">So falls a hollow pine, that long had stood</l>
<l n="tr">On Ida's height, or Erymanthus' wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Torn from the roots. The diff'ring nations rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And shouts and mingled murmurs rend the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">Acestus runs with eager haste, to raise</l>
<l n="tr">The fall'n companion of his youthful days.</l>
<l n="tr">Dauntless he rose, and to the fight return'd;</l>
<l n="tr">With shame his glowing cheeks, his eyes with fury burn'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Disdain and conscious virtue fir'd his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">And with redoubled force his foe he press'd.</l>
<l n="tr">He lays on load with either hand, amain,</l>
<l n="tr">And headlong drives the Trojan o'er the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor stops, nor stays; nor rest nor breath allows;</l>
<l n="tr">But storms of strokes descend about his brows,</l>
<l n="tr">A rattling tempest, and a hail of blows.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="461" unit="card"/>But now the prince, who saw the wild increase</l>
<l n="tr">Of wounds, commands the combatants to cease,</l>
<l n="tr">And bounds Entellus' wrath, and bids the peace.</l>
<l n="tr">First to the Trojan, spent with toil, he came,</l>
<l n="tr">And sooth'd his sorrow for the suffer'd shame.</l>
<l n="tr">“What fury seiz'd my friend? The gods,” said he,</l>
<l n="tr">“To him propitious, and averse to thee,</l>
<l n="tr">Have giv'n his arm superior force to thine.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is madness to contend with strength divine.”</l>
<l n="tr">The gauntlet fight thus ended, from the shore</l>
<l n="tr">His faithful friends unhappy Dares bore:</l>
<l n="tr">His mouth and nostrils pour'd a purple flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And pounded teeth came rushing with his blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Faintly he stagger'd thro' the hissing throng,</l>
<l n="tr">And hung his head, and trail'd his legs along.</l>
<l n="tr">The sword and casque are carried by his train;</l>
<l n="tr">But with his foe the palm and ox remain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The champion, then, before Aeneas came,</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of his prize, but prouder of his fame:</l>
<l n="tr">“O goddess-born, and you, Dardanian host,</l>
<l n="tr">Mark with attention, and forgive my boast;</l>
<l n="tr">Learn what I was, by what remains; and know</l>
<l n="tr">From what impending fate you sav'd my foe.”</l>
<l n="tr">Sternly he spoke, and then confronts the bull;</l>
<l n="tr">And, on his ample forehead aiming full,</l>
<l n="tr">The deadly stroke, descending, pierc'd the skull.</l>
<l n="tr">Down drops the beast, nor needs a second wound,</l>
<l n="tr">But sprawls in pangs of death, and spurns the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, thus: “In Dares' stead I offer this.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName>, accept a nobler sacrifice;</l>
<l n="tr">Take the last gift my wither'd arms can yield:</l>
<l n="tr">Thy gauntlets I resign, and here renounce the field.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="485" unit="card"/>This done, Aeneas orders, for the close,</l>
<l n="tr">The strife of archers with contending bows.</l>
<l n="tr">The mast Sergesthus' shatter'd galley bore</l>
<l n="tr">With his own hands he raises on the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">A flutt'ring dove upon the top they tie,</l>
<l n="tr">The living mark at which their arrows fly.</l>
<l n="tr">The rival archers in a line advance,</l>
<l n="tr">Their turn of shooting to receive from chance.</l>
<l n="tr">A helmet holds their names; the lots are drawn:</l>
<l n="tr">On the first scroll was read Hippocoon.</l>
<l n="tr">The people shout. Upon the next was found</l>
<l n="tr">Young Mnestheus, late with naval honors crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The third contain'd Eurytion's noble name,</l>
<l n="tr">Thy brother, Pandarus, and next in fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Pallas urg'd the treaty to confound,</l>
<l n="tr">And send among the Greeks a feather'd wound.</l>
<l n="tr">Acestes in the bottom last remain'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom not his age from youthful sports restrain'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon all with vigor bend their trusty bows,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the quiver each his arrow chose.</l>
<l n="tr">Hippocoon's was the first: with forceful sway</l>
<l n="tr">It flew, and, whizzing, cut the liquid way.</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd in the mast the feather'd weapon stands:</l>
<l n="tr">The fearful pigeon flutters in her bands,</l>
<l n="tr">And the tree trembled, and the shouting cries</l>
<l n="tr">Of the pleas'd people rend the vaulted skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Mnestheus to the head his arrow drove,</l>
<l n="tr">With lifted eyes, and took his aim above,</l>
<l n="tr">But made a glancing shot, and missed the dove;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet miss'd so narrow, that he cut the cord</l>
<l n="tr">Which fasten'd by the foot the flitting bird.</l>
<l n="tr">The captive thus releas'd, away she flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And beats with clapping wings the yielding skies.</l>
<l n="tr">His bow already bent, Eurytion stood;</l>
<l n="tr">And, having first invok'd his brother god,</l>
<l n="tr">His winged shaft with eager haste he sped.</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal message reach'd her as she fled:</l>
<l n="tr">She leaves her life aloft; she strikes the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And renders back the weapon in the wound.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="519" unit="card"/>Acestes, grudging at his lot, remains,</l>
<l n="tr">Without a prize to gratify his pains.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, shooting upward, sends his shaft, to show</l>
<l n="tr">An archer's art, and boast his twanging bow.</l>
<l n="tr">The feather'd arrow gave a dire portent,</l>
<l n="tr">And latter augurs judge from this event.</l>
<l n="tr">Chaf'd by the speed, it fir'd; and, as it flew,</l>
<l n="tr">A trail of following flames ascending drew:</l>
<l n="tr">Kindling they mount, and mark the shiny way;</l>
<l n="tr">Across the skies as falling meteors play,</l>
<l n="tr">And vanish into wind, or in a blaze decay.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans and Sicilians wildly stare,</l>
<l n="tr">And, trembling, turn their wonder into pray'r.</l>
<l n="tr">The Dardan prince put on a smiling face,</l>
<l n="tr">And strain'd Acestes with a close embrace;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, hon'ring him with gifts above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Turn'd the bad omen, nor his fears confess'd.</l>
<l n="tr">“The gods,” said he, “this miracle have wrought,</l>
<l n="tr">And order'd you the prize without the lot.</l>
<l n="tr">Accept this goblet, rough with figur'd gold,</l>
<l n="tr">Which Thracian Cisseus gave my sire of old:</l>
<l n="tr">This pledge of ancient amity receive,</l>
<l n="tr">Which to my second sire I justly give.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and, with the trumpets' cheerful sound,</l>
<l n="tr">Proclaim'd him victor, and with laurel-crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor good Eurytion envied him the prize,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' he transfix'd the pigeon in the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Who cut the line, with second gifts was grac'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The third was his whose arrow pierc'd the mast.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="545" unit="card"/>The chief, before the games were wholly done,</l>
<l n="tr">Call'd Periphantes, tutor to his son,</l>
<l n="tr">And whisper'd thus: “With speed Ascanius find;</l>
<l n="tr">And, if his childish troop be ready join'd,</l>
<l n="tr">On horseback let him grace his grandsire's day,</l>
<l n="tr">And lead his equals arm'd in just array.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and, calling out, the cirque he clears.</l>
<l n="tr">The crowd withdrawn, an open plain appears.</l>
<l n="tr">And now the noble youths, of form divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Advance before their fathers, in a line;</l>
<l n="tr">The riders grace the steeds; the steeds with glory shine.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus marching on in military pride,</l>
<l n="tr">Shouts of applause resound from side to side.</l>
<l n="tr">Their casques adorn'd with laurel wreaths they wear,</l>
<l n="tr">Each brandishing aloft a cornel spear.</l>
<l n="tr">Some at their backs their gilded quivers bore;</l>
<l n="tr">Their chains of burnish'd gold hung down before.</l>
<l n="tr">Three graceful troops they form'd upon the green;</l>
<l n="tr">Three graceful leaders at their head were seen;</l>
<l n="tr">Twelve follow'd ev'ry chief, and left a space between.</l>
<l n="tr">The first young Priam led; a lovely boy,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose grandsire was  th'  unhappy king of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>;</l>
<l n="tr">His race in after times was known to fame,</l>
<l n="tr">New honors adding to the Latian name;</l>
<l n="tr">And well the royal boy his Thracian steed became.</l>
<l n="tr">White were the fetlocks of his feet before,</l>
<l n="tr">And on his front a snowy star he bore.</l>
<l n="tr">Then beauteous Atys, with Iulus bred,</l>
<l n="tr">Of equal age, the second squadron led.</l>
<l n="tr">The last in order, but the first in place,</l>
<l n="tr">First in the lovely features of his face,</l>
<l n="tr">Rode fair Ascanius on a fiery steed,</l>
<l n="tr">Queen Dido's gift, and of the Tyrian breed.</l>
<l n="tr">Sure coursers for the rest the king ordains,</l>
<l n="tr">With golden bits adorn'd, and purple reins.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="575" unit="card"/>The pleas'd spectators peals of shouts renew,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the parents in the children view;</l>
<l n="tr">Their make, their motions, and their sprightly grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And hopes and fears alternate in their face.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Th' unfledg'd commanders and their martial train</l>
<l n="tr">First make the circuit of the sandy plain</l>
<l n="tr">Around their sires, and, at  th'  appointed sign,</l>
<l n="tr">Drawn up in beauteous order, form a line.</l>
<l n="tr">The second signal sounds, the troop divides</l>
<l n="tr">In three distinguish'd parts, with three distinguish'd guides</l>
<l n="tr">Again they close, and once again disjoin;</l>
<l n="tr">In troop to troop oppos'd, and line to line.</l>
<l n="tr">They meet; they wheel; they throw their darts afar</l>
<l n="tr">With harmless rage and well-dissembled war.</l>
<l n="tr">Then in a round the mingled bodies run:</l>
<l n="tr">Flying they follow, and pursuing shun;</l>
<l n="tr">Broken, they break; and, rallying, they renew</l>
<l n="tr">In other forms the military shew.</l>
<l n="tr">At last, in order, undiscern'd they join,</l>
<l n="tr">And march together in a friendly line.</l>
<l n="tr">And, as the Cretan labyrinth of old,</l>
<l n="tr">With wand'ring ways and many a winding fold,</l>
<l n="tr">Involv'd the weary feet, without redress,</l>
<l n="tr">In a round error, which denied recess;</l>
<l n="tr">So fought the Trojan boys in warlike play,</l>
<l n="tr">Turn'd and return'd, and still a diff'rent way.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus dolphins in the deep each other chase</l>
<l n="tr">In circles, when they swim around the wat'ry race.</l>
<l n="tr">This game, these carousels, Ascanius taught;</l>
<l n="tr">And, building Alba, to the Latins brought;</l>
<l n="tr">Shew'd what he learn'd: the Latin sires impart</l>
<l n="tr">To their succeeding sons the graceful art;</l>
<l n="tr">From these imperial <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> receiv'd the game,</l>
<l n="tr">Which <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, the youths the Trojan troop, they name.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus far the sacred sports they celebrate.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="604" unit="card"/>But Fortune soon resum'd her ancient hate;</l>
<l n="tr">For, while they pay the dead his annual dues,</l>
<l n="tr">Those envied rites Saturnian Juno views;</l>
<l n="tr">And sends the goddess of the various bow,</l>
<l n="tr">To try new methods of revenge below;</l>
<l n="tr">Supplies the winds to wing her airy way,</l>
<l n="tr">Where in the port secure the navy lay.</l>
<l n="tr">Swiftly fair Iris down her arch descends,</l>
<l n="tr">And, undiscern'd, her fatal voyage ends.</l>
<l n="tr">She saw the gath'ring crowd; and, gliding thence,</l>
<l n="tr">The desart shore, and fleet without defense.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan matrons, on the sands alone,</l>
<l n="tr">With sighs and tears Anchises' death bemoan;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, turning to the sea their weeping eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">Their pity to themselves renews their cries.</l>
<l n="tr">“Alas!” said one, “what oceans yet remain</l>
<l n="tr">For us to sail! what labors to sustain!”</l>
<l n="tr">All take the word, and, with a gen'ral groan,</l>
<l n="tr">Implore the gods for peace, and places of their own.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The goddess, great in mischief, views their pains,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a woman's form her heav'nly limbs restrains.</l>
<l n="tr">In face and shape old <persName>Beroe</persName> she became,</l>
<l n="tr">Doryclus' wife, a venerable dame,</l>
<l n="tr">Once blest with riches, and a mother's name.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus chang'd, amidst the crying crowd she ran,</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd with the matrons, and these words began:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="623" unit="card"/>“O wretched we, whom not the Grecian pow'r,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor flames, destroy'd, in <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s unhappy hour!</l>
<l n="tr">O wretched we, reserv'd by cruel fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Beyond the ruins of the sinking state!</l>
<l n="tr">Now sev'n revolving years are wholly run,</l>
<l n="tr">Since this improsp'rous voyage we begun;</l>
<l n="tr">Since, toss'd from shores to shores, from lands to lands,</l>
<l n="tr">Inhospitable rocks and barren sands,</l>
<l n="tr">Wand'ring in exile thro' the stormy sea,</l>
<l n="tr">We search in vain for flying <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">Now cast by fortune on this kindred land,</l>
<l n="tr">What should our rest and rising walls withstand,</l>
<l n="tr">Or hinder here to fix our banish'd band?</l>
<l n="tr">O country lost, and gods redeem'd in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">If still in endless exile we remain!</l>
<l n="tr">Shall we no more the Trojan walls renew,</l>
<l n="tr">Or streams of some dissembled Simois view!</l>
<l n="tr">Haste, join with me,  th'  unhappy fleet consume!</l>
<l n="tr">Cassandra bids; and I declare her doom.</l>
<l n="tr">In sleep I saw her; she supplied my hands</l>
<l n="tr">(For this I more than dreamt) with flaming brands:</l>
<l n="tr">‘With these,’ said she, ‘these wand'ring ships destroy:</l>
<l n="tr">These are your fatal seats, and this your <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.’</l>
<l n="tr">Time calls you now; the precious hour employ:</l>
<l n="tr">Slack not the good presage, while Heav'n inspires</l>
<l n="tr">Our minds to dare, and gives the ready fires.</l>
<l n="tr">See! Neptune's altars minister their brands:</l>
<l n="tr">The god is pleas'd; the god supplies our hands.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then from the pile a flaming fire she drew,</l>
<l n="tr">And, toss'd in air, amidst the galleys threw.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Wrapp'd in amaze, the matrons wildly stare:</l>
<l n="tr">Then Pyrgo, reverenc'd for her hoary hair,</l>
<l n="tr">Pyrgo, the nurse of Priam's num'rous race:</l>
<l n="tr">“No Beroe this, tho' she belies her face!</l>
<l n="tr">What terrors from her frowning front arise!</l>
<l n="tr">Behold a goddess in her ardent eyes!</l>
<l n="tr">What rays around her heav'nly face are seen!</l>
<l n="tr">Mark her majestic voice, and more than mortal mien!</l>
<l n="tr">Beroe but now I left, whom, pin'd with pain,</l>
<l n="tr">Her age and anguish from these rites detain,”</l>
<l n="tr">She said. The matrons, seiz'd with new amaze,</l>
<l n="tr">Roll their malignant eyes, and on the navy gaze.</l>
<l n="tr">They fear, and hope, and neither part obey:</l>
<l n="tr">They hope the fated land, but fear the fatal way.</l>
<l n="tr">The goddess, having done her task below,</l>
<l n="tr">Mounts up on equal wings, and bends her painted bow.</l>
<l n="tr">Struck with the sight, and seiz'd with rage divine,</l>
<l n="tr">The matrons prosecute their mad design:</l>
<l n="tr">They shriek aloud; they snatch, with impious hands,</l>
<l n="tr">The food of altars; fires and flaming brands.</l>
<l n="tr">Green boughs and saplings, mingled in their haste,</l>
<l n="tr">And smoking torches, on the ships they cast.</l>
<l n="tr">The flame, unstopp'd at first, more fury gains,</l>
<l n="tr">And <persName>Vulcan</persName> rides at large with loosen'd reins:</l>
<l n="tr">Triumphant to the painted sterns he soars,</l>
<l n="tr">And seizes, in this way, the banks and crackling oars.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="664" unit="card"/>Eumelus was the first the news to bear,</l>
<l n="tr">While yet they crowd the rural theater.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, what they hear, is witness'd by their eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">A storm of sparkles and of flames arise.</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius took  th'  alarm, while yet he led</l>
<l n="tr">His early warriors on his prancing steed,</l>
<l n="tr">And, spurring on, his equals soon o'erpass'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor could his frighted friends reclaim his haste.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon as the royal youth appear'd in view,</l>
<l n="tr">He sent his voice before him as he flew:</l>
<l n="tr">“What madness moves you, matrons, to destroy</l>
<l n="tr">The last remainders of unhappy <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>!</l>
<l n="tr">Not hostile fleets, but your own hopes, you burn,</l>
<l n="tr">And on your friends your fatal fury turn.</l>
<l n="tr">Behold your own Ascanius!” While he said,</l>
<l n="tr">He drew his glitt'ring helmet from his head,</l>
<l n="tr">In which the youths to sportful arms he led.</l>
<l n="tr">By this, Aeneas and his train appear;</l>
<l n="tr">And now the women, seiz'd with shame and fear,</l>
<l n="tr">Dispers'd, to woods and caverns take their flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Abhor their actions, and avoid the light;</l>
<l n="tr">Their friends acknowledge, and their error find,</l>
<l n="tr">And shake the goddess from their alter'd mind.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="680" unit="card"/>Not so the raging fires their fury cease,</l>
<l n="tr">But, lurking in the seams, with seeming peace,</l>
<l n="tr">Work on their way amid the smold'ring tow,</l>
<l n="tr">Sure in destruction, but in motion slow.</l>
<l n="tr">The silent plague thro' the green timber eats,</l>
<l n="tr">And vomits out a tardy flame by fits.</l>
<l n="tr">Down to the keels, and upward to the sails,</l>
<l n="tr">The fire descends, or mounts, but still prevails;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor buckets pour'd, nor strength of human hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Can the victorious element withstand.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The pious hero rends his robe, and throws</l>
<l n="tr">To heav'n his hands, and with his hands his vows.</l>
<l n="tr">“O Jove,” he cried, “if pray'rs can yet have place;</l>
<l n="tr">If thou abhorr'st not all the Dardan race;</l>
<l n="tr">If any spark of pity still remain;</l>
<l n="tr">If gods are gods, and not invok'd in vain;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet spare the relics of the Trojan train!</l>
<l n="tr">Yet from the flames our burning vessels free,</l>
<l n="tr">Or let thy fury fall alone on me!</l>
<l n="tr">At this devoted head thy thunder throw,</l>
<l n="tr">And send the willing sacrifice below!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Scarce had he said, when southern storms arise:</l>
<l n="tr">From pole to pole the forky lightning flies;</l>
<l n="tr">Loud rattling shakes the mountains and the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'n bellies downward, and descends in rain.</l>
<l n="tr">Whole sheets of water from the clouds are sent,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, hissing thro' the planks, the flames prevent,</l>
<l n="tr">And stop the fiery pest. Four ships alone</l>
<l n="tr">Burn to the waist, and for the fleet atone.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="700" unit="card"/>But doubtful thoughts the hero's heart divide;</l>
<l n="tr">If he should still in <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> reside,</l>
<l n="tr">Forgetful of his fates, or tempt the main,</l>
<l n="tr">In hope the promis'd <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> to gain.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Nautes, old and wise, to whom alone</l>
<l n="tr">The will of Heav'n by Pallas was foreshown;</l>
<l n="tr">Vers'd in portents, experienc'd, and inspir'd</l>
<l n="tr">To tell events, and what the fates requir'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while he stood, to neither part inclin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With cheerful words reliev'd his lab'ring mind:</l>
<l n="tr">“O goddess-born, resign'd in ev'ry state,</l>
<l n="tr">With patience bear, with prudence push your fate.</l>
<l n="tr">By suff'ring well, our Fortune we subdue;</l>
<l n="tr">Fly when she frowns, and, when she calls, pursue.</l>
<l n="tr">Your friend Acestes is of Trojan kind;</l>
<l n="tr">To him disclose the secrets of your mind:</l>
<l n="tr">Trust in his hands your old and useless train;</l>
<l n="tr">Too num'rous for the ships which yet remain:</l>
<l n="tr">The feeble, old, indulgent of their ease,</l>
<l n="tr">The dames who dread the dangers of the seas,</l>
<l n="tr">With all the dastard crew, who dare not stand</l>
<l n="tr">The shock of battle with your foes by land.</l>
<l n="tr">Here you may build a common town for all,</l>
<l n="tr">And, from Acestes' name, Acesta call.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="719" unit="card"/>The reasons, with his friend's experience join'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Encourag'd much, but more disturb'd his mind.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>'T was dead of night; when to his slumb'ring eyes</l>
<l n="tr">His father's shade descended from the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus he spoke: “O more than vital breath,</l>
<l n="tr">Lov'd while I liv'd, and dear ev'n after death;</l>
<l n="tr">O son, in various toils and troubles toss'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The King of Heav'n employs my careful ghost</l>
<l n="tr">On his commands: the god, who sav'd from fire</l>
<l n="tr">Your flaming fleet, and heard your just desire.</l>
<l n="tr">The wholesome counsel of your friend receive,</l>
<l n="tr">And here the coward train and woman leave:</l>
<l n="tr">The chosen youth, and those who nobly dare,</l>
<l n="tr">Transport, to tempt the dangers of the war.</l>
<l n="tr">The stern Italians will their courage try;</l>
<l n="tr">Rough are their manners, and their minds are high.</l>
<l n="tr">But first to Pluto's palace you shall go,</l>
<l n="tr">And seek my shade among the blest below:</l>
<l n="tr">For not with impious ghosts my soul remains,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor suffers with the damn'd perpetual pains,</l>
<l n="tr">But breathes the living air of soft Elysian plains.</l>
<l n="tr">The chaste Sibylla shall your steps convey,</l>
<l n="tr">And blood of offer'd victims free the way.</l>
<l n="tr">There shall you know what realms the gods assign,</l>
<l n="tr">And learn the fates and fortunes of your line.</l>
<l n="tr">But now, farewell! I vanish with the night,</l>
<l n="tr">And feel the blast of heav'n's approaching light.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and mix'd with shades, and took his airy flight.</l>
<l n="tr">“Whither so fast?” the filial duty cried;</l>
<l n="tr">“And why, ah why, the wish'd embrace denied?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He said, and rose; as holy zeal inspires,</l>
<l n="tr">He rakes hot embers, and renews the fires;</l>
<l n="tr">His country gods and Vesta then adores</l>
<l n="tr">With cakes and incense, and their aid implores.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="746" unit="card"/>Next, for his friends and royal host he sent,</l>
<l n="tr">Reveal'd his vision, and the gods' intent,</l>
<l n="tr">With his own purpose. All, without delay,</l>
<l n="tr">The will of Jove, and his desires obey.</l>
<l n="tr">They list with women each degenerate name,</l>
<l n="tr">Who dares not hazard life for future fame.</l>
<l n="tr">These they cashier: the brave remaining few,</l>
<l n="tr">Oars, banks, and cables, half consum'd, renew.</l>
<l n="tr">The prince designs a city with the plow;</l>
<l n="tr">The lots their sev'ral tenements allow.</l>
<l n="tr">This part is nam'd from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName>, that from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">And the new king ascends the throne with joy;</l>
<l n="tr">A chosen senate from the people draws;</l>
<l n="tr">Appoints the judges, and ordains the laws.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, on the top of <placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName>, they begin</l>
<l n="tr">A rising temple to the Paphian queen.</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises, last, is honor'd as a god;</l>
<l n="tr">A priest is added, annual gifts bestow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And groves are planted round his blest abode.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="762" unit="card"/>Nine days they pass in feasts, their temples crown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And fumes of incense in the fanes abound.</l>
<l n="tr">Then from the south arose a gentle breeze</l>
<l n="tr">That curl'd the smoothness of the glassy seas;</l>
<l n="tr">The rising winds a ruffling gale afford,</l>
<l n="tr">And call the merry mariners aboard.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now loud laments along the shores resound,</l>
<l n="tr">Of parting friends in close embraces bound.</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling women, the degenerate train,</l>
<l n="tr">Who shunn'd the frightful dangers of the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n those desire to sail, and take their share</l>
<l n="tr">Of the rough passage and the promis'd war:</l>
<l n="tr">Whom good Aeneas cheers, and recommends</l>
<l n="tr">To their new master's care his fearful friends.</l>
<l n="tr">On <placeName key="perseus,Eryx" authname="perseus,Eryx">Eryx</placeName>'s altars three fat calves he lays;</l>
<l n="tr">A lamb new-fallen to the stormy seas;</l>
<l n="tr">Then slips his haulsers, and his anchors weighs.</l>
<l n="tr">High on the deck the godlike hero stands,</l>
<l n="tr">With olive crown'd, a charger in his hands;</l>
<l n="tr">Then cast the reeking entrails in the brine,</l>
<l n="tr">And pour'd the sacrifice of purple wine.</l>
<l n="tr">Fresh gales arise; with equal strokes they vie,</l>
<l n="tr">And brush the buxom seas, and o'er the billows fly.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="779" unit="card"/>Meantime the mother goddess, full of fears,</l>
<l n="tr">To Neptune thus address'd, with tender tears:</l>
<l n="tr">“The pride of Jove's imperious queen, the rage,</l>
<l n="tr">The malice which no suff'rings can assuage,</l>
<l n="tr">Compel me to these pray'rs; since neither fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor time, nor pity, can remove her hate:</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n Jove is thwarted by his haughty wife;</l>
<l n="tr">Still vanquish'd, yet she still renews the strife.</l>
<l n="tr">As if 't were little to consume the town</l>
<l n="tr">Which aw'd the world, and wore  th'  imperial crown,</l>
<l n="tr">She prosecutes the ghost of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> with pains,</l>
<l n="tr">And gnaws, ev'n to the bones, the last remains.</l>
<l n="tr">Let her the causes of her hatred tell;</l>
<l n="tr">But you can witness its effects too well.</l>
<l n="tr">You saw the storm she rais'd on Libyan floods,</l>
<l n="tr">That mix'd the mounting billows with the clouds;</l>
<l n="tr">When, bribing Aeolus, she shook the main,</l>
<l n="tr">And mov'd rebellion in your wat'ry reign.</l>
<l n="tr">With fury she possess'd the Dardan dames,</l>
<l n="tr">To burn their fleet with execrable flames,</l>
<l n="tr">And forc'd Aeneas, when his ships were lost,</l>
<l n="tr">To leave his foll'wers on a foreign coast.</l>
<l n="tr">For what remains, your godhead I implore,</l>
<l n="tr">And trust my son to your protecting pow'r.</l>
<l n="tr">If neither Jove's nor Fate's decree withstand,</l>
<l n="tr">Secure his passage to the Latian land.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="799" unit="card"/>Then thus the mighty Ruler of the Main:</l>
<l n="tr">“What may not Venus hope from Neptune's reign?</l>
<l n="tr">My kingdom claims your birth; my late defense</l>
<l n="tr">Of your indanger'd fleet may claim your confidence.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor less by land than sea my deeds declare</l>
<l n="tr">How much your lov'd Aeneas is my care.</l>
<l n="tr">Thee, <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>, and thee, Simois, I attest.</l>
<l n="tr">Your Trojan troops when proud Achilles press'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And drove before him headlong on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">And dash'd against the walls the trembling train;</l>
<l n="tr">When floods were fill'd with bodies of the slain;</l>
<l n="tr">When crimson <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>, doubtful of his way,</l>
<l n="tr">Stood up on ridges to behold the sea;</l>
<l n="tr">(New heaps came tumbling in, and chok'd his way;)</l>
<l n="tr">When your Aeneas fought, but fought with odds</l>
<l n="tr">Of force unequal, and unequal gods;</l>
<l n="tr">I spread a cloud before the victor's sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Sustain'd the vanquish'd, and secur'd his flight;</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n then secur'd him, when I sought with joy</l>
<l n="tr">The vow'd destruction of ungrateful <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">My will's the same: fair goddess, fear no more,</l>
<l n="tr">Your fleet shall safely gain the Latian shore;</l>
<l n="tr">Their lives are giv'n; one destin'd head alone</l>
<l n="tr">Shall perish, and for multitudes atone.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having arm'd with hopes her anxious mind,</l>
<l n="tr">His finny team Saturnian Neptune join'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Then adds the foamy bridle to their jaws,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the loosen'd reins permits the laws.</l>
<l n="tr">High on the waves his azure car he guides;</l>
<l n="tr">Its axles thunder, and the sea subsides,</l>
<l n="tr">And the smooth ocean rolls her silent tides.</l>
<l n="tr">The tempests fly before their father's face,</l>
<l n="tr">Trains of inferior gods his triumph grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And monster whales before their master play,</l>
<l n="tr">And choirs of Tritons crowd the wat'ry way.</l>
<l n="tr">The marshal'd pow'rs in equal troops divide</l>
<l n="tr">To right and left; the gods his better side</l>
<l n="tr">Inclose, and on the worse the Nymphs and Nereids ride.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="827" unit="card"/>Now smiling hope, with sweet vicissitude,</l>
<l n="tr">Within the hero's mind his joys renew'd.</l>
<l n="tr">He calls to raise the masts, the sheets display;</l>
<l n="tr">The cheerful crew with diligence obey;</l>
<l n="tr">They scud before the wind, and sail in open sea.</l>
<l n="tr">Ahead of all the master pilot steers;</l>
<l n="tr">And, as he leads, the following navy veers.</l>
<l n="tr">The steeds of Night had travel'd half the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">The drowsy rowers on their benches lie,</l>
<l n="tr">When the soft God of Sleep, with easy flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Descends, and draws behind a trail of light.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, Palinurus, art his destin'd prey;</l>
<l n="tr">To thee alone he takes his fatal way.</l>
<l n="tr">Dire dreams to thee, and iron sleep, he bears;</l>
<l n="tr">And, lighting on thy prow, the form of Phorbas wears.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus the traitor god began his tale:</l>
<l n="tr">“The winds, my friend, inspire a pleasing gale;</l>
<l n="tr">The ships, without thy care, securely sail.</l>
<l n="tr">Now steal an hour of sweet repose; and I</l>
<l n="tr">Will take the rudder and thy room supply.”</l>
<l n="tr">To whom the yawning pilot, half asleep:</l>
<l n="tr">“Me dost thou bid to trust the treach'rous deep,</l>
<l n="tr">The harlot smiles of her dissembling face,</l>
<l n="tr">And to her faith commit the Trojan race?</l>
<l n="tr">Shall I believe the Siren South again,</l>
<l n="tr">And, oft betray'd, not know the monster main?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="852" unit="card"/>He said: his fasten'd hands the rudder keep,</l>
<l n="tr">And, fix'd on heav'n, his eyes repel invading sleep.</l>
<l n="tr">The god was wroth, and at his temples threw</l>
<l n="tr">A branch in Lethe dipp'd, and drunk with Stygian dew:</l>
<l n="tr">The pilot, vanquish'd by the pow'r divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Soon clos'd his swimming eyes, and lay supine.</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce were his limbs extended at their length,</l>
<l n="tr">The god, insulting with superior strength,</l>
<l n="tr">Fell heavy on him, plung'd him in the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">And, with the stern, the rudder tore away.</l>
<l n="tr">Headlong he fell, and, struggling in the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Cried out for helping hands, but cried in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">The victor daemon mounts obscure in air,</l>
<l n="tr">While the ship sails without the pilot's care.</l>
<l n="tr">On Neptune's faith the floating fleet relies;</l>
<l n="tr">But what the man forsook, the god supplies,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er the dang'rous deep secure the navy flies;</l>
<l n="tr">Glides by the Sirens' cliffs, a shelfy coast,</l>
<l n="tr">Long infamous for ships and sailors lost,</l>
<l n="tr">And white with bones.  Th'  impetuous ocean roars,</l>
<l n="tr">And rocks rebellow from the sounding shores.</l>
<l n="tr">The watchful hero felt the knocks, and found</l>
<l n="tr">The tossing vessel sail'd on shoaly ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Sure of his pilot's loss, he takes himself</l>
<l n="tr">The helm, and steers aloof, and shuns the shelf.</l>
<l n="tr">Inly he griev'd, and, groaning from the breast,</l>
<l n="tr">Deplor'd his death; and thus his pain express'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“For faith repos'd on seas, and on the flatt'ring sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Thy naked corpse is doom'd on shores unknown to lie.”</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>