<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="6" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">He said, and wept; then spread his sails before</l>
<l n="tr">The winds, and reach'd at length the Cumaean shore:</l>
<l n="tr">Their anchors dropp'd, his crew the vessels moor.</l>
<l n="tr">They turn their heads to sea, their sterns to land,</l>
<l n="tr">And greet with greedy joy  th'  Italian strand.</l>
<l n="tr">Some strike from clashing flints their fiery seed;</l>
<l n="tr">Some gather sticks, the kindled flames to feed,</l>
<l n="tr">Or search for hollow trees, and fell the woods,</l>
<l n="tr">Or trace thro' valleys the discover'd floods.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, while their sev'ral charges they fulfil,</l>
<l n="tr">The pious prince ascends the sacred hill</l>
<l n="tr">Where Phoebus is ador'd; and seeks the shade</l>
<l n="tr">Which hides from sight his venerable maid.</l>
<l n="tr">Deep in a cave the Sibyl makes abode;</l>
<l n="tr">Thence full of fate returns, and of the god.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' Trivia's grove they walk; and now behold,</l>
<l n="tr">And enter now, the temple roof'd with gold.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="14" unit="card"/>When Daedalus, to fly the Cretan shore,</l>
<l n="tr">His heavy limbs on jointed pinions bore,</l>
<l n="tr">(The first who sail'd in air,) 't is sung by Fame,</l>
<l n="tr">To the Cumaean coast at length he came,</l>
<l n="tr">And here alighting, built this costly frame.</l>
<l n="tr">Inscrib'd to Phoebus, here he hung on high</l>
<l n="tr">The steerage of his wings, that cut the sky:</l>
<l n="tr">Then o'er the lofty gate his art emboss'd</l>
<l n="tr">Androgeos' death, and off'rings to his ghost;</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n youths from <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> yearly sent, to meet</l>
<l n="tr">The fate appointed by revengeful <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">And next to those the dreadful urn was plac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">In which the destin'd names by lots were cast:</l>
<l n="tr">The mournful parents stand around in tears,</l>
<l n="tr">And rising <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> against their shore appears.</l>
<l n="tr">There too, in living sculpture, might be seen</l>
<l n="tr">The mad affection of the Cretan queen;</l>
<l n="tr">Then how she cheats her bellowing lover's eye;</l>
<l n="tr">The rushing leap, the doubtful progeny,</l>
<l n="tr">The lower part a beast, a man above,</l>
<l n="tr">The monument of their polluted love.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from thence he grav'd the wondrous maze,</l>
<l n="tr">A thousand doors, a thousand winding ways:</l>
<l n="tr">Here dwells the monster, hid from human view,</l>
<l n="tr">Not to be found, but by the faithful clew;</l>
<l n="tr">Till the kind artist, mov'd with pious grief,</l>
<l n="tr">Lent to the loving maid this last relief,</l>
<l n="tr">And all those erring paths describ'd so well</l>
<l n="tr">That Theseus conquer'd and the monster fell.</l>
<l n="tr">Here hapless Icarus had found his part,</l>
<l n="tr">Had not the father's grief restrain'd his art.</l>
<l n="tr">He twice assay'd to cast his son in gold;</l>
<l n="tr">Twice from his hands he dropp'd the forming mold.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>All this with wond'ring eyes Aeneas view'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Each varying object his delight renew'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Eager to read the rest—Achates came,</l>
<l n="tr">And by his side the mad divining dame,</l>
<l n="tr">The priestess of the god, Deiphobe her name.</l>
<l n="tr">“Time suffers not,” she said, “to feed your eyes</l>
<l n="tr">With empty pleasures; haste the sacrifice.</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n bullocks, yet unyok'd, for Phoebus choose,</l>
<l n="tr">And for Diana sev'n unspotted ewes.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, the servants urge the sacred rites,</l>
<l n="tr">While to the temple she the prince invites.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="42" unit="card"/>A spacious cave, within its farmost part,</l>
<l n="tr">Was hew'd and fashion'd by laborious art</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the hill's hollow sides: before the place,</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred doors a hundred entries grace;</l>
<l n="tr">As many voices issue, and the sound</l>
<l n="tr">Of Sybil's words as many times rebound.</l>
<l n="tr">Now to the mouth they come. Aloud she cries:</l>
<l n="tr">“This is the time; enquire your destinies.</l>
<l n="tr">He comes; behold the god!” Thus while she said,</l>
<l n="tr">(And shiv'ring at the sacred entry stay'd,)</l>
<l n="tr">Her color chang'd; her face was not the same,</l>
<l n="tr">And hollow groans from her deep spirit came.</l>
<l n="tr">Her hair stood up; convulsive rage possess'd</l>
<l n="tr">Her trembling limbs, and heav'd her lab'ring breast.</l>
<l n="tr">Greater than humankind she seem'd to look,</l>
<l n="tr">And with an accent more than mortal spoke.</l>
<l n="tr">Her staring eyes with sparkling fury roll;</l>
<l n="tr">When all the god came rushing on her soul.</l>
<l n="tr">Swiftly she turn'd, and, foaming as she spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why this delay?” she cried, “the pow'rs invoke!</l>
<l n="tr">Thy pray'rs alone can open this abode;</l>
<l n="tr">Else vain are my demands, and dumb the god.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said no more. The trembling Trojans hear,</l>
<l n="tr">O'erspread with a damp sweat and holy fear.</l>
<l n="tr">The prince himself, with awful dread possess'd,</l>
<l n="tr">His vows to great Apollo thus address'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“Indulgent god, propitious pow'r to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Swift to relieve, unwilling to destroy,</l>
<l n="tr">Directed by whose hand the Dardan dart</l>
<l n="tr">Pierc'd the proud Grecian's only mortal part:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus far, by fate's decrees and thy commands,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' ambient seas and thro' devouring sands,</l>
<l n="tr">Our exil'd crew has sought  th'  Ausonian ground;</l>
<l n="tr">And now, at length, the flying coast is found.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus far the fate of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, from place to place,</l>
<l n="tr">With fury has pursued her wand'ring race.</l>
<l n="tr">Here cease, ye pow'rs, and let your vengeance end:</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> is no more, and can no more offend.</l>
<l n="tr">And thou, O sacred maid, inspir'd to see</l>
<l n="tr">Th' event of things in dark futurity;</l>
<l n="tr">Give me what Heav'n has promis'd to my fate,</l>
<l n="tr">To conquer and command the Latian state;</l>
<l n="tr">To fix my wand'ring gods, and find a place</l>
<l n="tr">For the long exiles of the Trojan race.</l>
<l n="tr">Then shall my grateful hands a temple rear</l>
<l n="tr">To the twin gods, with vows and solemn pray'r;</l>
<l n="tr">And annual rites, and festivals, and games,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall be perform'd to their auspicious names.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor shalt thou want thy honors in my land;</l>
<l n="tr">For there thy faithful oracles shall stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Preserv'd in shrines; and ev'ry sacred lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, by thy mouth, Apollo shall convey:</l>
<l n="tr">All shall be treasur'd by a chosen train</l>
<l n="tr">Of holy priests, and ever shall remain.</l>
<l n="tr">But O! commit not thy prophetic mind</l>
<l n="tr">To flitting leaves, the sport of ev'ry wind,</l>
<l n="tr">Lest they disperse in air our empty fate;</l>
<l n="tr">Write not, but, what the pow'rs ordain, relate.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="77" unit="card"/>Struggling in vain, impatient of her load,</l>
<l n="tr">And lab'ring underneath the pond'rous god,</l>
<l n="tr">The more she strove to shake him from her breast,</l>
<l n="tr">With more and far superior force he press'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Commands his entrance, and, without control,</l>
<l n="tr">Usurps her organs and inspires her soul.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, with a furious blast, the hundred doors</l>
<l n="tr">Ope of themselves; a rushing whirlwind roars</l>
<l n="tr">Within the cave, and Sibyl's voice restores:</l>
<l n="tr">“Escap'd the dangers of the wat'ry reign,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet more and greater ills by land remain.</l>
<l n="tr">The coast, so long desir'd (nor doubt  th'  event),</l>
<l n="tr">Thy troops shall reach, but, having reach'd, repent.</l>
<l n="tr">Wars, horrid wars, I view—a field of blood,</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> rolling with a purple flood.</l>
<l n="tr">Simois nor <placeName key="perseus,Xanthos" authname="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName> shall be wanting there:</l>
<l n="tr">A new Achilles shall in arms appear,</l>
<l n="tr">And he, too, goddess-born. Fierce Juno's hate,</l>
<l n="tr">Added to hostile force, shall urge thy fate.</l>
<l n="tr">To what strange nations shalt not thou resort,</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n to solicit aid at ev'ry court!</l>
<l n="tr">The cause the same which <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Ilium</placeName> once oppress'd;</l>
<l n="tr">A foreign mistress, and a foreign guest.</l>
<l n="tr">But thou, secure of soul, unbent with woes,</l>
<l n="tr">The more thy fortune frowns, the more oppose.</l>
<l n="tr">The dawnings of thy safety shall be shown</l>
<l n="tr">From whence thou least shalt hope, a Grecian town.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="98" unit="card"/>Thus, from the dark recess, the Sibyl spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">And the resisting air the thunder broke;</l>
<l n="tr">The cave rebellow'd, and the temple shook.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' ambiguous god, who rul'd her lab'ring breast,</l>
<l n="tr">In these mysterious words his mind express'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Some truths reveal'd, in terms involv'd the rest.</l>
<l n="tr">At length her fury fell, her foaming ceas'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, ebbing in her soul, the god decreas'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus the chief: “No terror to my view,</l>
<l n="tr">No frightful face of danger can be new.</l>
<l n="tr">Inur'd to suffer, and resolv'd to dare,</l>
<l n="tr">The Fates, without my pow'r, shall be without my care.</l>
<l n="tr">This let me crave, since near your grove the road</l>
<l n="tr">To hell lies open, and the dark abode</l>
<l n="tr">Which Acheron surrounds,  th'  innavigable flood;</l>
<l n="tr">Conduct me thro' the regions void of light,</l>
<l n="tr">And lead me longing to my father's sight.</l>
<l n="tr">For him, a thousand dangers I have sought,</l>
<l n="tr">And, rushing where the thickest Grecians fought,</l>
<l n="tr">Safe on my back the sacred burthen brought.</l>
<l n="tr">He, for my sake, the raging ocean tried,</l>
<l n="tr">And wrath of Heav'n, my still auspicious guide,</l>
<l n="tr">And bore beyond the strength decrepid age supplied.</l>
<l n="tr">Oft, since he breath'd his last, in dead of night</l>
<l n="tr">His reverend image stood before my sight;</l>
<l n="tr">Enjoin'd to seek, below, his holy shade;</l>
<l n="tr">Conducted there by your unerring aid.</l>
<l n="tr">But you, if pious minds by pray'rs are won,</l>
<l n="tr">Oblige the father, and protect the son.</l>
<l n="tr">Yours is the pow'r; nor Proserpine in vain</l>
<l n="tr">Has made you priestess of her nightly reign.</l>
<l n="tr">If Orpheus, arm'd with his enchanting lyre,</l>
<l n="tr">The ruthless king with pity could inspire,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the shades below redeem his wife;</l>
<l n="tr">If Pollux, off'ring his alternate life,</l>
<l n="tr">Could free his brother, and can daily go</l>
<l n="tr">By turns aloft, by turns descend below—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Why name I Theseus, or his greater friend,</l>
<l n="tr">Who trod the downward path, and upward could ascend?</l>
<l n="tr">Not less than theirs from Jove my lineage came;</l>
<l n="tr">My mother greater, my descent the same.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="124" unit="card"/>So pray'd the Trojan prince, and, while he pray'd,</l>
<l n="tr">His hand upon the holy altar laid.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus replied the prophetess divine:</l>
<l n="tr">“O goddess-born of great Anchises' line,</l>
<l n="tr">The gates of hell are open night and day;</l>
<l n="tr">Smooth the descent, and easy is the way:</l>
<l n="tr">But to return, and view the cheerful skies,</l>
<l n="tr">In this the task and mighty labor lies.</l>
<l n="tr">To few great <persName>Jupiter</persName> imparts this grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And those of shining worth and heav'nly race.</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt those regions and our upper light,</l>
<l n="tr">Deep forests and impenetrable night</l>
<l n="tr">Possess the middle space:  th'  infernal bounds</l>
<l n="tr">Cocytus, with his sable waves, surrounds.</l>
<l n="tr">But if so dire a love your soul invades,</l>
<l n="tr">As twice below to view the trembling shades;</l>
<l n="tr">If you so hard a toil will undertake,</l>
<l n="tr">As twice to pass  th'  innavigable lake;</l>
<l n="tr">Receive my counsel. In the neighb'ring grove</l>
<l n="tr">There stands a tree; the queen of Stygian Jove</l>
<l n="tr">Claims it her own; thick woods and gloomy night</l>
<l n="tr">Conceal the happy plant from human sight.</l>
<l n="tr">One bough it bears; but (wondrous to behold!)</l>
<l n="tr">The ductile rind and leaves of radiant gold:</l>
<l n="tr">This from the vulgar branches must be torn,</l>
<l n="tr">And to fair Proserpine the present borne,</l>
<l n="tr">Ere leave be giv'n to tempt the nether skies.</l>
<l n="tr">The first thus rent a second will arise,</l>
<l n="tr">And the same metal the same room supplies.</l>
<l n="tr">Look round the wood, with lifted eyes, to see</l>
<l n="tr">The lurking gold upon the fatal tree:</l>
<l n="tr">Then rend it off, as holy rites command;</l>
<l n="tr">The willing metal will obey thy hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Following with ease, if favor'd by thy fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou art foredoom'd to view the Stygian state:</l>
<l n="tr">If not, no labor can the tree constrain;</l>
<l n="tr">And strength of stubborn arms and steel are vain.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, you know not, while you here attend,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unworthy fate of your unhappy friend:</l>
<l n="tr">Breathless he lies; and his unburied ghost,</l>
<l n="tr">Depriv'd of fun'ral rites, pollutes your host.</l>
<l n="tr">Pay first his pious dues; and, for the dead,</l>
<l n="tr">Two sable sheep around his hearse be led;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, living turfs upon his body lay:</l>
<l n="tr">This done, securely take the destin'd way,</l>
<l n="tr">To find the regions destitute of day.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said, and held her peace.<milestone ed="p" n="156" unit="card"/>Aeneas went</l>
<l n="tr">Sad from the cave, and full of discontent,</l>
<l n="tr">Unknowing whom the sacred Sibyl meant.</l>
<l n="tr">Achates, the companion of his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">Goes grieving by his side, with equal cares oppress'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Walking, they talk'd, and fruitlessly divin'd</l>
<l n="tr">What friend the priestess by those words design'd.</l>
<l n="tr">But soon they found an object to deplore:</l>
<l n="tr">Misenus lay extended the shore;</l>
<l n="tr">Son of the God of Winds: none so renown'd</l>
<l n="tr">The warrior trumpet in the field to sound;</l>
<l n="tr">With breathing brass to kindle fierce alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">And rouse to dare their fate in honorable arms.</l>
<l n="tr">He serv'd great Hector, and was ever near,</l>
<l n="tr">Not with his trumpet only, but his spear.</l>
<l n="tr">But by Pelides' arms when Hector fell,</l>
<l n="tr">He chose Aeneas; and he chose as well.</l>
<l n="tr">Swoln with applause, and aiming still at more,</l>
<l n="tr">He now provokes the sea gods from the shore;</l>
<l n="tr">With envy Triton heard the martial sound,</l>
<l n="tr">And the bold champion, for his challenge, drown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Then cast his mangled carcass on the strand:</l>
<l n="tr">The gazing crowd around the body stand.</l>
<l n="tr">All weep; but most Aeneas mourns his fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And hastens to perform the funeral state.</l>
<l n="tr">In altar-wise, a stately pile they rear;</l>
<l n="tr">The basis broad below, and top advanc'd in air.</l>
<l n="tr">An ancient wood, fit for the work design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">(The shady covert of the salvage kind,)</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans found: the sounding ax is plied;</l>
<l n="tr">Firs, pines, and pitch trees, and the tow'ring pride</l>
<l n="tr">Of forest ashes, feel the fatal stroke,</l>
<l n="tr">And piercing wedges cleave the stubborn oak.</l>
<l n="tr">Huge trunks of trees, fell'd from the steepy crown</l>
<l n="tr">Of the bare mountains, roll with ruin down.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="183" unit="card"/>Arm'd like the rest the Trojan prince appears,</l>
<l n="tr">And by his pious labor urges theirs.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus while he wrought, revolving in his mind</l>
<l n="tr">The ways to compass what his wish design'd,</l>
<l n="tr">He cast his eyes upon the gloomy grove,</l>
<l n="tr">And then with vows implor'd the Queen of Love:</l>
<l n="tr">“O may thy pow'r, propitious still to me,</l>
<l n="tr">Conduct my steps to find the fatal tree,</l>
<l n="tr">In this deep forest; since the Sibyl's breath</l>
<l n="tr">Foretold, alas! too true, Misenus' death.”</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had he said, when, full before his sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Two doves, descending from their airy flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Secure upon the grassy plain alight.</l>
<l n="tr">He knew his mother's birds; and thus he pray'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“Be you my guides, with your auspicious aid,</l>
<l n="tr">And lead my footsteps, till the branch be found,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose glitt'ring shadow gilds the sacred ground.</l>
<l n="tr">And thou, great parent, with celestial care,</l>
<l n="tr">In this distress be present to my pray'r!”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, he stopp'd with watchful sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Observing still the motions of their flight,</l>
<l n="tr">What course they took, what happy signs they shew.</l>
<l n="tr">They fed, and, flutt'ring, by degrees withdrew</l>
<l n="tr">Still farther from the place, but still in view:</l>
<l n="tr">Hopping and flying, thus they led him on</l>
<l n="tr">To the slow lake, whose baleful stench to shun</l>
<l n="tr">They wing'd their flight aloft; then, stooping low,</l>
<l n="tr">Perch'd on the double tree that bears the golden bough.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the green leafs the glitt'ring shadows glow;</l>
<l n="tr">As, on the sacred oak, the wintry mistletoe,</l>
<l n="tr">Where the proud mother views her precious brood,</l>
<l n="tr">And happier branches, which she never sow'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Such was the glitt'ring; such the ruddy rind,</l>
<l n="tr">And dancing leaves, that wanton'd in the wind.</l>
<l n="tr">He seiz'd the shining bough with griping hold,</l>
<l n="tr">And rent away, with ease, the ling'ring gold;</l>
<l n="tr">Then to the Sibyl's palace bore the prize.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="212" unit="card"/>Meantime the Trojan troops, with weeping eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">To dead Misenus pay his obsequies.</l>
<l n="tr">First, from the ground a lofty pile they rear,</l>
<l n="tr">Of pitch trees, oaks, and pines, and unctuous fir:</l>
<l n="tr">The fabric's front with cypress twigs they strew,</l>
<l n="tr">And stick the sides with boughs of baleful yew.</l>
<l n="tr">The topmost part his glitt'ring arms adorn;</l>
<l n="tr">Warm waters, then, in brazen caldrons borne,</l>
<l n="tr">Are pour'd to wash his body, joint by joint,</l>
<l n="tr">And fragrant oils the stiffen'd limbs anoint.</l>
<l n="tr">With groans and cries Misenus they deplore:</l>
<l n="tr">Then on a bier, with purple cover'd o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">The breathless body, thus bewail'd, they lay,</l>
<l n="tr">And fire the pile, their faces turn'd away—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Such reverend rites their fathers us'd to pay.</l>
<l n="tr">Pure oil and incense on the fire they throw,</l>
<l n="tr">And fat of victims, which his friends bestow.</l>
<l n="tr">These gifts the greedy flames to dust devour;</l>
<l n="tr">Then on the living coals red wine they pour;</l>
<l n="tr">And, last, the relics by themselves dispose,</l>
<l n="tr">Which in a brazen urn the priests inclose.</l>
<l n="tr">Old Corynaeus compass'd thrice the crew,</l>
<l n="tr">And dipp'd an olive branch in holy dew;</l>
<l n="tr">Which thrice he sprinkled round, and thrice aloud</l>
<l n="tr">Invok'd the dead, and then dismissed the crowd.</l>
<l n="tr">But good Aeneas order'd on the shore</l>
<l n="tr">A stately tomb, whose top a trumpet bore,</l>
<l n="tr">A soldier's fauchion, and a seaman's oar.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus was his friend interr'd; and deathless fame</l>
<l n="tr">Still to the lofty cape consigns his name.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="236" unit="card"/>These rites perform'd, the prince, without delay,</l>
<l n="tr">Hastes to the nether world his destin'd way.</l>
<l n="tr">Deep was the cave; and, downward as it went</l>
<l n="tr">From the wide mouth, a rocky rough descent;</l>
<l n="tr">And here  th'  access a gloomy grove defends,</l>
<l n="tr">And there  th'  unnavigable lake extends,</l>
<l n="tr">O'er whose unhappy waters, void of light,</l>
<l n="tr">No bird presumes to steer his airy flight;</l>
<l n="tr">Such deadly stenches from the depths arise,</l>
<l n="tr">And steaming sulphur, that infects the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">From hence the Grecian bards their legends make,</l>
<l n="tr">And give the name Avernus to the lake.</l>
<l n="tr">Four sable bullocks, in the yoke untaught,</l>
<l n="tr">For sacrifice the pious hero brought.</l>
<l n="tr">The priestess pours the wine betwixt their horns;</l>
<l n="tr">Then cuts the curling hair; that first oblation burns,</l>
<l n="tr">Invoking Hecate hither to repair:</l>
<l n="tr">A pow'rful name in hell and upper air.</l>
<l n="tr">The sacred priests with ready knives bereave</l>
<l n="tr">The beasts of life, and in full bowls receive</l>
<l n="tr">The streaming blood: a lamb to Hell and Night</l>
<l n="tr">(The sable wool without a streak of white)</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas offers; and, by fate's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">A barren heifer, Proserpine, to thee,</l>
<l n="tr">With holocausts he Pluto's altar fills;</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n brawny bulls with his own hand he kills;</l>
<l n="tr">Then on the broiling entrails oil he pours;</l>
<l n="tr">Which, ointed thus, the raging flame devours.</l>
<l n="tr">Late the nocturnal sacrifice begun,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor ended till the next returning sun.</l>
<l n="tr">Then earth began to bellow, trees to dance,</l>
<l n="tr">And howling dogs in glimm'ring light advance,</l>
<l n="tr">Ere Hecate came. “Far hence be souls profane!”</l>
<l n="tr">The Sibyl cried, “and from the grove abstain!</l>
<l n="tr">Now, Trojan, take the way thy fates afford;</l>
<l n="tr">Assume thy courage, and unsheathe thy sword.”</l>
<l n="tr">She said, and pass'd along the gloomy space;</l>
<l n="tr">The prince pursued her steps with equal pace.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="264" unit="card"/>Ye realms, yet unreveal'd to human sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Ye gods who rule the regions of the night,</l>
<l n="tr">Ye gliding ghosts, permit me to relate</l>
<l n="tr">The mystic wonders of your silent state!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="268" unit="card"/>Obscure they went thro' dreary shades, that led</l>
<l n="tr">Along the waste dominions of the dead.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus wander travelers in woods by night,</l>
<l n="tr">By the moon's doubtful and malignant light,</l>
<l n="tr">When Jove in dusky clouds involves the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And the faint crescent shoots by fits before their eyes.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Just in the gate and in the jaws of hell,</l>
<l n="tr">Revengeful Cares and sullen Sorrows dwell,</l>
<l n="tr">And pale Diseases, and repining Age,</l>
<l n="tr">Want, Fear, and Famine's unresisted rage;</l>
<l n="tr">Here Toils, and Death, and Death's half-brother, Sleep,</l>
<l n="tr">Forms terrible to view, their sentry keep;</l>
<l n="tr">With anxious Pleasures of a guilty mind,</l>
<l n="tr">Deep Frauds before, and open Force behind;</l>
<l n="tr">The Furies' iron beds; and Strife, that shakes</l>
<l n="tr">Her hissing tresses and unfolds her snakes.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="282" unit="card"/>Full in the midst of this infernal road,</l>
<l n="tr">An elm displays her dusky arms abroad:</l>
<l n="tr">The God of Sleep there hides his heavy head,</l>
<l n="tr">And empty dreams on ev'ry leaf are spread.</l>
<l n="tr">Of various forms unnumber'd specters more,</l>
<l n="tr">Centaurs, and double shapes, besiege the door.</l>
<l n="tr">Before the passage, horrid Hydra stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And Briareus with all his hundred hands;</l>
<l n="tr">Gorgons, Geryon with his triple frame;</l>
<l n="tr">And vain Chimaera vomits empty flame.</l>
<l n="tr">The chief unsheath'd his shining steel, prepar'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' seiz'd with sudden fear, to force the guard,</l>
<l n="tr">Off'ring his brandish'd weapon at their face;</l>
<l n="tr">Had not the Sibyl stopp'd his eager pace,</l>
<l n="tr">And told him what those empty phantoms were:</l>
<l n="tr">Forms without bodies, and impassive air.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="295" unit="card"/>Hence to deep Acheron they take their way,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose troubled eddies, thick with ooze and clay,</l>
<l n="tr">Are whirl'd aloft, and in Cocytus lost.</l>
<l n="tr">There Charon stands, who rules the dreary coasT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">A sordid god: down from his hoary chin</l>
<l n="tr">A length of beard descends, uncomb'd, unclean;</l>
<l n="tr">His eyes, like hollow furnaces on fire;</l>
<l n="tr">A girdle, foul with grease, binds his obscene attire.</l>
<l n="tr">He spreads his canvas; with his pole he steers;</l>
<l n="tr">The freights of flitting ghosts in his thin bottom bears.</l>
<l n="tr">He look'd in years; yet in his years were seen</l>
<l n="tr">A youthful vigor and autumnal green.</l>
<l n="tr">An airy crowd came rushing where he stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Which fill'd the margin of the fatal flood:</l>
<l n="tr">Husbands and wives, boys and unmarried maids,</l>
<l n="tr">And mighty heroes' more majestic shades,</l>
<l n="tr">And youths, intomb'd before their fathers' eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">With hollow groans, and shrieks, and feeble cries.</l>
<l n="tr">Thick as the leaves in autumn strow the woods,</l>
<l n="tr">Or fowls, by winter forc'd, forsake the floods,</l>
<l n="tr">And wing their hasty flight to happier lands;</l>
<l n="tr">Such, and so thick, the shiv'ring army stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And press for passage with extended hands.</l>
<l n="tr">Now these, now those, the surly boatman bore:</l>
<l n="tr">The rest he drove to distance from the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">The hero, who beheld with wond'ring eyes</l>
<l n="tr">The tumult mix'd with shrieks, laments, and cries,</l>
<l n="tr">Ask'd of his guide, what the rude concourse meant;</l>
<l n="tr">Why to the shore the thronging people bent;</l>
<l n="tr">What forms of law among the ghosts were us'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Why some were ferried o'er, and some refus'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Son of Anchises, offspring of the gods,”</l>
<l n="tr">The Sibyl said, “you see the Stygian floods,</l>
<l n="tr">The sacred stream which heav'n's imperial state</l>
<l n="tr">Attests in oaths, and fears to violate.</l>
<l n="tr">The ghosts rejected are  th'  unhappy crew</l>
<l n="tr">Depriv'd of sepulchers and fun'ral due:</l>
<l n="tr">The boatman, Charon; those, the buried host,</l>
<l n="tr">He ferries over to the farther coast;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor dares his transport vessel cross the waves</l>
<l n="tr">With such whose bones are not compos'd in graves.</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred years they wander on the shore;</l>
<l n="tr">At length, their penance done, are wafted o'er.”</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan chief his forward pace repress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Revolving anxious thoughts within his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">He saw his friends, who, whelm'd beneath the waves,</l>
<l n="tr">Their fun'ral honors claim'd, and ask'd their quiet graves.</l>
<l n="tr">The lost Leucaspis in the crowd he knew,</l>
<l n="tr">And the brave leader of the Lycian crew,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom, on the Tyrrhene seas, the tempests met;</l>
<l n="tr">The sailors master'd, and the ship o'erset.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="337" unit="card"/>Amidst the spirits, Palinurus press'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet fresh from life, a new-admitted guest,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, while he steering view'd the stars, and bore</l>
<l n="tr">His course from Afric to the Latian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Fell headlong down. The Trojan fix'd his view,</l>
<l n="tr">And scarcely thro' the gloom the sullen shadow knew.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus the prince: “What envious pow'r, O friend,</l>
<l n="tr">Brought your lov'd life to this disastrous end?</l>
<l n="tr">For Phoebus, ever true in all he said,</l>
<l n="tr">Has in your fate alone my faith betray'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The god foretold you should not die, before</l>
<l n="tr">You reach'd, secure from seas,  th'  Italian shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Is this  th'  unerring pow'r?” The ghost replied;</l>
<l n="tr">“Nor Phoebus flatter'd, nor his answers lied;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor envious gods have sent me to the deep:</l>
<l n="tr">But, while the stars and course of heav'n I keep,</l>
<l n="tr">My wearied eyes were seiz'd with fatal sleep.</l>
<l n="tr">I fell; and, with my weight, the helm constrain'd</l>
<l n="tr">Was drawn along, which yet my gripe retain'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Now by the winds and raging waves I swear,</l>
<l n="tr">Your safety, more than mine, was then my care;</l>
<l n="tr">Lest, of the guide bereft, the rudder lost,</l>
<l n="tr">Your ship should run against the rocky coast.</l>
<l n="tr">Three blust'ring nights, borne by the southern blast,</l>
<l n="tr">I floated, and discover'd land at last:</l>
<l n="tr">High on a mounting wave my head I bore,</l>
<l n="tr">Forcing my strength, and gath'ring to the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">Panting, but past the danger, now I seiz'd</l>
<l n="tr">The craggy cliffs, and my tir'd members eas'd.</l>
<l n="tr">While, cumber'd with my dropping clothes, I lay,</l>
<l n="tr">The cruel nation, covetous of prey,</l>
<l n="tr">Stain'd with my blood  th'  unhospitable coast;</l>
<l n="tr">And now, by winds and waves, my lifeless limbs are toss'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Which O avert, by yon ethereal light,</l>
<l n="tr">Which I have lost for this eternal night!</l>
<l n="tr">Or, if by dearer ties you may be won,</l>
<l n="tr">By your dead sire, and by your living son,</l>
<l n="tr">Redeem from this reproach my wand'ring ghost;</l>
<l n="tr">Or with your navy seek the Velin coast,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a peaceful grave my corpse compose;</l>
<l n="tr">Or, if a nearer way your mother shows,</l>
<l n="tr">Without whose aid you durst not undertake</l>
<l n="tr">This frightful passage o'er the Stygian lake,</l>
<l n="tr">Lend to this wretch your hand, and waft him o'er</l>
<l n="tr">To the sweet banks of yon forbidden shore.”</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had he said, the prophetess began:</l>
<l n="tr">“What hopes delude thee, miserable man?</l>
<l n="tr">Think'st thou, thus unintomb'd, to cross the floods,</l>
<l n="tr">To view the Furies and infernal gods,</l>
<l n="tr">And visit, without leave, the dark abodes?</l>
<l n="tr">Attend the term of long revolving years;</l>
<l n="tr">Fate, and the dooming gods, are deaf to tears.</l>
<l n="tr">This comfort of thy dire misfortune take:</l>
<l n="tr">The wrath of Heav'n, inflicted for thy sake,</l>
<l n="tr">With vengeance shall pursue  th'  inhuman coast,</l>
<l n="tr">Till they propitiate thy offended ghost,</l>
<l n="tr">And raise a tomb, with vows and solemn pray'r;</l>
<l n="tr">And Palinurus' name the place shall bear.”</l>
<l n="tr">This calm'd his cares; sooth'd with his future fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And pleas'd to hear his propagated name.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="384" unit="card"/>Now nearer to the Stygian lake they draw:</l>
<l n="tr">Whom, from the shore, the surly boatman saw;</l>
<l n="tr">Observ'd their passage thro' the shady wood,</l>
<l n="tr">And mark'd their near approaches to the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus he call'd aloud, inflam'd with wrath:</l>
<l n="tr">“Mortal, whate'er, who this forbidden path</l>
<l n="tr">In arms presum'st to tread, I charge thee, stand,</l>
<l n="tr">And tell thy name, and bus'ness in the land.</l>
<l n="tr">Know this, the realm of nighT'mdash;the Stygian shore:</l>
<l n="tr">My boat conveys no living bodies o'er;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor was I pleas'd great Theseus once to bear,</l>
<l n="tr">Who forc'd a passage with his pointed spear,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor strong Alcides—men of mighty fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And from  th'  immortal gods their lineage came.</l>
<l n="tr">In fetters one the barking porter tied,</l>
<l n="tr">And took him trembling from his sov'reign's side:</l>
<l n="tr">Two sought by force to seize his beauteous bride.”</l>
<l n="tr">To whom the Sibyl thus: “Compose thy mind;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor frauds are here contriv'd, nor force design'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Still may the dog the wand'ring troops constrain</l>
<l n="tr">Of airy ghosts, and vex the guilty train,</l>
<l n="tr">And with her grisly lord his lovely queen remain.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan chief, whose lineage is from Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">Much fam'd for arms, and more for filial love,</l>
<l n="tr">Is sent to seek his sire in your Elysian grove.</l>
<l n="tr">If neither piety, nor Heav'n's command,</l>
<l n="tr">Can gain his passage to the Stygian strand,</l>
<l n="tr">This fatal present shall prevail at least.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then shew'd the shining bough, conceal'd within her vest.</l>
<l n="tr">No more was needful: for the gloomy god</l>
<l n="tr">Stood mute with awe, to see the golden rod;</l>
<l n="tr">Admir'd the destin'd off'ring to his queen—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">A venerable gift, so rarely seen.</l>
<l n="tr">His fury thus appeas'd, he puts to land;</l>
<l n="tr">The ghosts forsake their seats at his command:</l>
<l n="tr">He clears the deck, receives the mighty freight;</l>
<l n="tr">The leaky vessel groans beneath the weight.</l>
<l n="tr">Slowly she sails, and scarcely stems the tides;</l>
<l n="tr">The pressing water pours within her sides.</l>
<l n="tr">His passengers at length are wafted o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">Expos'd, in muddy weeds, upon the miry shore.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="417" unit="card"/>No sooner landed, in his den they found</l>
<l n="tr">The triple porter of the Stygian sound,</l>
<l n="tr">Grim Cerberus, who soon began to rear</l>
<l n="tr">His crested snakes, and arm'd his bristling hair.</l>
<l n="tr">The prudent Sibyl had before prepar'd</l>
<l n="tr">A sop, in honey steep'd, to charm the guard;</l>
<l n="tr">Which, mix'd with pow'rful drugs, she cast before</l>
<l n="tr">His greedy grinning jaws, just op'd to roar.</l>
<l n="tr">With three enormous mouths he gapes; and straight,</l>
<l n="tr">With hunger press'd, devours the pleasing bait.</l>
<l n="tr">Long draughts of sleep his monstrous limbs enslave;</l>
<l n="tr">He reels, and, falling, fills the spacious cave.</l>
<l n="tr">The keeper charm'd, the chief without delay</l>
<l n="tr">Pass'd on, and took  th'  irremeable way.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="426" unit="card"/>Before the gates, the cries of babes new born,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom fate had from their tender mothers torn,</l>
<l n="tr">Assault his ears: then those, whom form of laws</l>
<l n="tr">Condemn'd to die, when traitors judg'd their cause.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor want they lots, nor judges to review</l>
<l n="tr">The wrongful sentence, and award a new.</l>
<l n="tr">Minos, the strict inquisitor, appears;</l>
<l n="tr">And lives and crimes, with his assessors, hears.</l>
<l n="tr">Round in his urn the blended balls he rolls,</l>
<l n="tr">Absolves the just, and dooms the guilty souls.</l>
<l n="tr">The next, in place and punishment, are they</l>
<l n="tr">Who prodigally throw their souls away;</l>
<l n="tr">Fools, who, repining at their wretched state,</l>
<l n="tr">And loathing anxious life, suborn'd their fate.</l>
<l n="tr">With late repentance now they would retrieve</l>
<l n="tr">The bodies they forsook, and wish to live;</l>
<l n="tr">Their pains and poverty desire to bear,</l>
<l n="tr">To view the light of heav'n, and breathe the vital air:</l>
<l n="tr">But fate forbids; the Stygian floods oppose,</l>
<l n="tr">And with circling streams the captive souls inclose.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Not far from thence, the Mournful Fields appear</l>
<l n="tr">So call'd from lovers that inhabit there.</l>
<l n="tr">The souls whom that unhappy flame invades,</l>
<l n="tr">In secret solitude and myrtle shades</l>
<l n="tr">Make endless moans, and, pining with desire,</l>
<l n="tr">Lament too late their unextinguish'd fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Here Procris, Eriphyle here he found,</l>
<l n="tr">Baring her breast, yet bleeding with the wound</l>
<l n="tr">Made by her son. He saw Pasiphae there,</l>
<l n="tr">With Phaedra's ghost, a foul incestuous pair.</l>
<l n="tr">There Laodamia, with Evadne, moves,</l>
<l n="tr">Unhappy both, but loyal in their loves:</l>
<l n="tr">Caeneus, a woman once, and once a man,</l>
<l n="tr">But ending in the sex she first began.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from these Phoenician Dido stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Fresh from her wound, her bosom bath'd in blood;</l>
<l n="tr">Whom when the Trojan hero hardly knew,</l>
<l n="tr">Obscure in shades, and with a doubtful view,</l>
<l n="tr">(Doubtful as he who sees, thro' dusky night,</l>
<l n="tr">Or thinks he sees, the moon's uncertain light,)</l>
<l n="tr">With tears he first approach'd the sullen shade;</l>
<l n="tr">And, as his love inspir'd him, thus he said:</l>
<l n="tr">“Unhappy queen! then is the common breath</l>
<l n="tr">Of rumor true, in your reported death,</l>
<l n="tr">And I, alas! the cause? By Heav'n, I vow,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the pow'rs that rule the realms below,</l>
<l n="tr">Unwilling I forsook your friendly state,</l>
<l n="tr">Commanded by the gods, and forc'd by fate—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Those gods, that fate, whose unresisted might</l>
<l n="tr">Have sent me to these regions void of light,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the vast empire of eternal night.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor dar'd I to presume, that, press'd with grief,</l>
<l n="tr">My flight should urge you to this dire relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Stay, stay your steps, and listen to my vows:</l>
<l n="tr">'T is the last interview that fate allows!”</l>
<l n="tr">In vain he thus attempts her mind to move</l>
<l n="tr">With tears, and pray'rs, and late-repenting love.</l>
<l n="tr">Disdainfully she look'd; then turning round,</l>
<l n="tr">But fix'd her eyes unmov'd upon the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And what he says and swears, regards no more</l>
<l n="tr">Than the deaf rocks, when the loud billows roar;</l>
<l n="tr">But whirl'd away, to shun his hateful sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Hid in the forest and the shades of night;</l>
<l n="tr">Then sought Sichaeus thro' the shady grove,</l>
<l n="tr">Who answer'd all her cares, and equal'd all her love.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Some pious tears the pitying hero paid,</l>
<l n="tr">And follow'd with his eyes the flitting shade,</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="477" unit="card"/>Then took the forward way, by fate ordain'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, with his guide, the farther fields attain'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Where, sever'd from the rest, the warrior souls remain'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Tydeus he met, with Meleager's race,</l>
<l n="tr">The pride of armies, and the soldiers' grace;</l>
<l n="tr">And pale Adrastus with his ghastly face.</l>
<l n="tr">Of Trojan chiefs he view'd a num'rous train,</l>
<l n="tr">All much lamented, all in battle slain;</l>
<l n="tr">Glaucus and <persName>Medon</persName>, high above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Antenor's sons, and <persName>Ceres</persName>' sacred priest.</l>
<l n="tr">And proud Idaeus, Priam's charioteer,</l>
<l n="tr">Who shakes his empty reins, and aims his airy spear.</l>
<l n="tr">The gladsome ghosts, in circling troops, attend</l>
<l n="tr">And with unwearied eyes behold their friend;</l>
<l n="tr">Delight to hover near, and long to know</l>
<l n="tr">What bus'ness brought him to the realms below.</l>
<l n="tr">But <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> chiefs, and Agamemnon's train,</l>
<l n="tr">When his refulgent arms flash'd thro' the shady plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Fled from his well-known face, with wonted fear,</l>
<l n="tr">As when his thund'ring sword and pointed spear</l>
<l n="tr">Drove headlong to their ships, and glean'd the routed rear.</l>
<l n="tr">They rais'd a feeble cry, with trembling notes;</l>
<l n="tr">But the weak voice deceiv'd their gasping throats.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="494" unit="card"/>Here Priam's son, Deiphobus, he found,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose face and limbs were one continued wound:</l>
<l n="tr">Dishonest, with lopp'd arms, the youth appears,</l>
<l n="tr">Spoil'd of his nose, and shorten'd of his ears.</l>
<l n="tr">He scarcely knew him, striving to disown</l>
<l n="tr">His blotted form, and blushing to be known;</l>
<l n="tr">And therefore first began: “O Teucer's race,</l>
<l n="tr">Who durst thy faultless figure thus deface?</l>
<l n="tr">What heart could wish, what hand inflict, this dire disgrace?</l>
<l n="tr">'T was fam'd, that in our last and fatal night</l>
<l n="tr">Your single prowess long sustain'd the fight,</l>
<l n="tr">Till tir'd, not forc'd, a glorious fate you chose,</l>
<l n="tr">And fell upon a heap of slaughter'd foes.</l>
<l n="tr">But, in remembrance of so brave a deed,</l>
<l n="tr">A tomb and fun'ral honors I decreed;</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice call'd your manes on the Trojan plains:</l>
<l n="tr">The place your armor and your name retains.</l>
<l n="tr">Your body too I sought, and, had I found,</l>
<l n="tr">Design'd for burial in your native ground.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The ghost replied: “Your piety has paid</l>
<l n="tr">All needful rites, to rest my wand'ring shade;</l>
<l n="tr">But cruel fate, and my more cruel wife,</l>
<l n="tr">To Grecian swords betray'd my sleeping life.</l>
<l n="tr">These are the monuments of Helen's love:</l>
<l n="tr">The shame I bear below, the marks I bore above.</l>
<l n="tr">You know in what deluding joys we pass'd</l>
<l n="tr">The night that was by Heav'n decreed our last:</l>
<l n="tr">For, when the fatal horse, descending down,</l>
<l n="tr">Pregnant with arms, o'erwhelm'd  th'  unhappy town</l>
<l n="tr">She feign'd nocturnal orgies; left my bed,</l>
<l n="tr">And, mix'd with Trojan dames, the dances led</l>
<l n="tr">Then, waving high her torch, the signal made,</l>
<l n="tr">Which rous'd the Grecians from their ambuscade.</l>
<l n="tr">With watching overworn, with cares oppress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Unhappy I had laid me down to rest,</l>
<l n="tr">And heavy sleep my weary limbs possess'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Meantime my worthy wife our arms mislaid,</l>
<l n="tr">And from beneath my head my sword convey'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The door unlatch'd, and, with repeated calls,</l>
<l n="tr">Invites her former lord within my walls.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus in her crime her confidence she plac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And with new treasons would redeem the past.</l>
<l n="tr">What need I more? Into the room they ran,</l>
<l n="tr">And meanly murther'd a defenseless man.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Ulysses</persName>, basely born, first led the way.</l>
<l n="tr">Avenging pow'rs! with justice if I pray,</l>
<l n="tr">That fortune be their own another day!</l>
<l n="tr">But answer you; and in your turn relate,</l>
<l n="tr">What brought you, living, to the Stygian state:</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n by the winds and errors of the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">Or did you Heav'n's superior doom obey?</l>
<l n="tr">Or tell what other chance conducts your way,</l>
<l n="tr">To view with mortal eyes our dark retreats,</l>
<l n="tr">Tumults and torments of  th'  infernal seats.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="535" unit="card"/>While thus in talk the flying hours they pass,</l>
<l n="tr">The sun had finish'd more than half his race:</l>
<l n="tr">And they, perhaps, in words and tears had spent</l>
<l n="tr">The little time of stay which Heav'n had lent;</l>
<l n="tr">But thus the Sibyl chides their long delay:</l>
<l n="tr">“Night rushes down, and headlong drives the day:</l>
<l n="tr">'T is here, in different paths, the way divides;</l>
<l n="tr">The right to <persName>Pluto</persName>'s golden palace guides;</l>
<l n="tr">The left to that unhappy region tends,</l>
<l n="tr">Which to the depth of Tartarus descends;</l>
<l n="tr">The seat of night profound, and punish'd fiends.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus Deiphobus: “O sacred maid,</l>
<l n="tr">Forbear to chide, and be your will obey'd!</l>
<l n="tr">Lo! to the secret shadows I retire,</l>
<l n="tr">To pay my penance till my years expire.</l>
<l n="tr">Proceed, auspicious prince, with glory crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And born to better fates than I have found.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and, while he said, his steps he turn'd</l>
<l n="tr">To secret shadows, and in silence mourn'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="548" unit="card"/>The hero, looking on the left, espied</l>
<l n="tr">A lofty tow'r, and strong on ev'ry side</l>
<l n="tr">With treble walls, which Phlegethon surrounds,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose fiery flood the burning empire bounds;</l>
<l n="tr">And, press'd betwixt the rocks, the bellowing noise resounds</l>
<l n="tr">Wide is the fronting gate, and, rais'd on high</l>
<l n="tr">With adamantine columns, threats the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">Vain is the force of man, and Heav'n's as vain,</l>
<l n="tr">To crush the pillars which the pile sustain.</l>
<l n="tr">Sublime on these a tow'r of steel is rear'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And dire Tisiphone there keeps the ward,</l>
<l n="tr">Girt in her sanguine gown, by night and day,</l>
<l n="tr">Observant of the souls that pass the downward way.</l>
<l n="tr">From hence are heard the groans of ghosts, the pains</l>
<l n="tr">Of sounding lashes and of dragging chains.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan stood astonish'd at their cries,</l>
<l n="tr">And ask'd his guide from whence those yells arise;</l>
<l n="tr">And what the crimes, and what the tortures were,</l>
<l n="tr">And loud laments that rent the liquid air.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She thus replied: “The chaste and holy race</l>
<l n="tr">Are all forbidden this polluted place.</l>
<l n="tr">But Hecate, when she gave to rule the woods,</l>
<l n="tr">Then led me trembling thro' these dire abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">And taught the tortures of  th'  avenging gods.</l>
<l n="tr">These are the realms of unrelenting fate;</l>
<l n="tr">And awful Rhadamanthus rules the state.</l>
<l n="tr">He hears and judges each committed crime;</l>
<l n="tr">Enquires into the manner, place, and time.</l>
<l n="tr">The conscious wretch must all his acts reveal,</l>
<l n="tr">(Loth to confess, unable to conceal),</l>
<l n="tr">From the first moment of his vital breath,</l>
<l n="tr">To his last hour of unrepenting death.</l>
<l n="tr">Straight, o'er the guilty ghost, the Fury shakes</l>
<l n="tr">The sounding whip and brandishes her snakes,</l>
<l n="tr">And the pale sinner, with her sisters, takes.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, of itself, unfolds  th'  eternal door;</l>
<l n="tr">With dreadful sounds the brazen hinges roar.</l>
<l n="tr">You see, before the gate, what stalking ghost</l>
<l n="tr">Commands the guard, what sentries keep the post.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="576" unit="card"/>More formidable Hydra stands within,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose jaws with iron teeth severely grin.</l>
<l n="tr">The gaping gulf low to the center lies,</l>
<l n="tr">And twice as deep as earth is distant from the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">The rivals of the gods, the Titan race,</l>
<l n="tr">Here, sing'd with lightning, roll within  th'  unfathom'd space.</l>
<l n="tr">Here lie  th'  Alaean twins, (I saw them both,)</l>
<l n="tr">Enormous bodies, of gigantic growth,</l>
<l n="tr">Who dar'd in fight the Thund'rer to defy,</l>
<l n="tr">Affect his heav'n, and force him from the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">Salmoneus, suff'ring cruel pains, I found,</l>
<l n="tr">For emulating Jove; the rattling sound</l>
<l n="tr">Of mimic thunder, and the glitt'ring blaze</l>
<l n="tr">Of pointed lightnings, and their forky rays.</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' Elis and the Grecian towns he flew;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' audacious wretch four fiery coursers drew:</l>
<l n="tr">He wav'd a torch aloft, and, madly vain,</l>
<l n="tr">Sought godlike worship from a servile train.</l>
<l n="tr">Ambitious fool! with horny hoofs to pass</l>
<l n="tr">O'er hollow arches of resounding brass,</l>
<l n="tr">To rival thunder in its rapid course,</l>
<l n="tr">And imitate inimitable force!</l>
<l n="tr">But he, the King of Heav'n, obscure on high,</l>
<l n="tr">Bar'd his red arm, and, launching from the sky</l>
<l n="tr">His writhen bolt, not shaking empty smoke,</l>
<l n="tr">Down to the deep abyss the flaming felon strook.</l>
<l n="tr">There Tityus was to see, who took his birth</l>
<l n="tr">From heav'n, his nursing from the foodful earth.</l>
<l n="tr">Here his gigantic limbs, with large embrace,</l>
<l n="tr">Infold nine acres of infernal space.</l>
<l n="tr">A rav'nous vulture, in his open'd side,</l>
<l n="tr">Her crooked beak and cruel talons tried;</l>
<l n="tr">Still for the growing liver digg'd his breast;</l>
<l n="tr">The growing liver still supplied the feast;</l>
<l n="tr">Still are his entrails fruitful to their pains:</l>
<l n="tr">Th' immortal hunger lasts,  th'  immortal food remains.</l>
<l n="tr">Ixion and Perithous I could name,</l>
<l n="tr">And more Thessalian chiefs of mighty fame.</l>
<l n="tr">High o'er their heads a mold'ring rock is plac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">That promises a fall, and shakes at ev'ry blast.</l>
<l n="tr">They lie below, on golden beds display'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And genial feasts with regal pomp are made.</l>
<l n="tr">The Queen of Furies by their sides is set,</l>
<l n="tr">And snatches from their mouths  th'  untasted meat,</l>
<l n="tr">Which if they touch, her hissing snakes she rears,</l>
<l n="tr">Tossing her torch, and thund'ring in their ears.</l>
<l n="tr">Then they, who brothers' better claim disown,</l>
<l n="tr">Expel their parents, and usurp the throne;</l>
<l n="tr">Defraud their clients, and, to lucre sold,</l>
<l n="tr">Sit brooding on unprofitable gold;</l>
<l n="tr">Who dare not give, and ev'n refuse to lend</l>
<l n="tr">To their poor kindred, or a wanting friend.</l>
<l n="tr">Vast is the throng of these; nor less the train</l>
<l n="tr">Of lustful youths, for foul adult'ry slain:</l>
<l n="tr">Hosts of deserters, who their honor sold,</l>
<l n="tr">And basely broke their faith for bribes of gold.</l>
<l n="tr">All these within the dungeon's depth remain,</l>
<l n="tr">Despairing pardon, and expecting pain.</l>
<l n="tr">Ask not what pains; nor farther seek to know</l>
<l n="tr">Their process, or the forms of law below.</l>
<l n="tr">Some roll a weighty stone; some, laid along,</l>
<l n="tr">And bound with burning wires, on spokes of wheels are hung</l>
<l n="tr">Unhappy Theseus, doom'd for ever there,</l>
<l n="tr">Is fix'd by fate on his eternal chair;</l>
<l n="tr">And wretched Phlegyas warns the world with cries</l>
<l n="tr">(Could warning make the world more just or wise):</l>
<l n="tr">‘Learn righteousness, and dread  th'  avenging deities.’</l>
<l n="tr">To tyrants others have their country sold,</l>
<l n="tr">Imposing foreign lords, for foreign gold;</l>
<l n="tr">Some have old laws repeal'd, new statutes made,</l>
<l n="tr">Not as the people pleas'd, but as they paid;</l>
<l n="tr">With incest some their daughters' bed profan'd:</l>
<l n="tr">All dar'd the worst of ills, and, what they dar'd, attain'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Had I a hundred mouths, a hundred tongues,</l>
<l n="tr">And throats of brass, inspir'd with iron lungs,</l>
<l n="tr">I could not half those horrid crimes repeat,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor half the punishments those crimes have met.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="628" unit="card"/>But let us haste our voyage to pursue:</l>
<l n="tr">The walls of <persName>Pluto</persName>'s palace are in view;</l>
<l n="tr">The gate, and iron arch above it, stands</l>
<l n="tr">On anvils labor'd by the Cyclops' hands.</l>
<l n="tr">Before our farther way the Fates allow,</l>
<l n="tr">Here must we fix on high the golden bough.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>She said: and thro' the gloomy shades they pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And chose the middle path. Arriv'd at last,</l>
<l n="tr">The prince with living water sprinkled o'er</l>
<l n="tr">His limbs and body; then approach'd the door,</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd the porch, and on the front above</l>
<l n="tr">He fix'd the fatal bough requir'd by <persName>Pluto</persName>'s love.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="637" unit="card"/>These holy rites perform'd, they took their way</l>
<l n="tr">Where long extended plains of pleasure lay:</l>
<l n="tr">The verdant fields with those of heav'n may vie,</l>
<l n="tr">With ether vested, and a purple sky;</l>
<l n="tr">The blissful seats of happy souls below.</l>
<l n="tr">Stars of their own, and their own suns, they know;</l>
<l n="tr">Their airy limbs in sports they exercise,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the green contend the wrestler's prize.</l>
<l n="tr">Some in heroic verse divinely sing;</l>
<l n="tr">Others in artful measures led the ring.</l>
<l n="tr">The Thracian bard, surrounded by the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">There stands conspicuous in his flowing vest;</l>
<l n="tr">His flying fingers, and harmonious quill,</l>
<l n="tr">Strikes sev'n distinguish'd notes, and sev'n at once they fill.</l>
<l n="tr">Here found they Teucer's old heroic race,</l>
<l n="tr">Born better times and happier years to grace.</l>
<l n="tr">Assaracus and Ilus here enjoy</l>
<l n="tr">Perpetual fame, with him who founded <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">The chief beheld their chariots from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Their shining arms, and coursers train'd to war:</l>
<l n="tr">Their lances fix'd in earth, their steeds around,</l>
<l n="tr">Free from their harness, graze the flow'ry ground.</l>
<l n="tr">The love of horses which they had, alive,</l>
<l n="tr">And care of chariots, after death survive.</l>
<l n="tr">Some cheerful souls were feasting on the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">Some did the song, and some the choir maintain,</l>
<l n="tr">Beneath a laurel shade, where mighty Po</l>
<l n="tr">Mounts up to woods above, and hides his head below.</l>
<l n="tr">Here patriots live, who, for their country's good,</l>
<l n="tr">In fighting fields, were prodigal of blood:</l>
<l n="tr">Priests of unblemish'd lives here make abode,</l>
<l n="tr">And poets worthy their inspiring god;</l>
<l n="tr">And searching wits, of more mechanic parts,</l>
<l n="tr">Who grac'd their age with new-invented arts:</l>
<l n="tr">Those who to worth their bounty did extend,</l>
<l n="tr">And those who knew that bounty to commend.</l>
<l n="tr">The heads of these with holy fillets bound,</l>
<l n="tr">And all their temples were with garlands crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To these the Sibyl thus her speech address'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And first to him surrounded by the rest</l>
<l n="tr">(Tow'ring his height, and ample was his breast):</l>
<l n="tr">“Say, happy souls, divine Musaeus, say,</l>
<l n="tr">Where lives Anchises, and where lies our way</l>
<l n="tr">To find the hero, for whose only sake</l>
<l n="tr">We sought the dark abodes, and cross'd the bitter lake?”</l>
<l n="tr">To this the sacred poet thus replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“In no fix'd place the happy souls reside.</l>
<l n="tr">In groves we live, and lie on mossy beds,</l>
<l n="tr">By crystal streams, that murmur thro' the meads:</l>
<l n="tr">But pass yon easy hill, and thence descend;</l>
<l n="tr">The path conducts you to your journey's end.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, he led them up the mountain's brow,</l>
<l n="tr">And shews them all the shining fields below.</l>
<l n="tr">They wind the hill, and thro' the blissful meadows go.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="679" unit="card"/>But old Anchises, in a flow'ry vale,</l>
<l n="tr">Review'd his muster'd race, and took the tale:</l>
<l n="tr">Those happy spirits, which, ordain'd by fate,</l>
<l n="tr">For future beings and new bodies waiT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">With studious thought observ'd  th'  illustrious throng,</l>
<l n="tr">In nature's order as they pass'd along:</l>
<l n="tr">Their names, their fates, their conduct, and their care,</l>
<l n="tr">In peaceful senates and successful war.</l>
<l n="tr">He, when Aeneas on the plain appears,</l>
<l n="tr">Meets him with open arms, and falling tears.</l>
<l n="tr">“Welcome,” he said, “the gods' undoubted race!</l>
<l n="tr">O long expected to my dear embrace!</l>
<l n="tr">Once more 't is giv'n me to behold your face!</l>
<l n="tr">The love and pious duty which you pay</l>
<l n="tr">Have pass'd the perils of so hard a way.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is true, computing times, I now believ'd</l>
<l n="tr">The happy day approach'd; nor are my hopes deceiv'd.</l>
<l n="tr">What length of lands, what oceans have you pass'd;</l>
<l n="tr">What storms sustain'd, and on what shores been cast?</l>
<l n="tr">How have I fear'd your fate! but fear'd it most,</l>
<l n="tr">When love assail'd you, on the Libyan coast.”</l>
<l n="tr">To this, the filial duty thus replies:</l>
<l n="tr">“Your sacred ghost before my sleeping eyes</l>
<l n="tr">Appear'd, and often urg'd this painful enterprise.</l>
<l n="tr">After long tossing on the Tyrrhene sea,</l>
<l n="tr">My navy rides at anchor in the bay.</l>
<l n="tr">But reach your hand, O parent shade, nor shun</l>
<l n="tr">The dear embraces of your longing son!”</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and falling tears his face bedew:</l>
<l n="tr">Then thrice around his neck his arms he threw;</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice the flitting shadow slipp'd away,</l>
<l n="tr">Like winds, or empty dreams that fly the day.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="703" unit="card"/>Now, in a secret vale, the Trojan sees</l>
<l n="tr">A sep'rate grove, thro' which a gentle breeze</l>
<l n="tr">Plays with a passing breath, and whispers thro' the trees;</l>
<l n="tr">And, just before the confines of the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">The gliding Lethe leads her silent flood.</l>
<l n="tr">About the boughs an airy nation flew,</l>
<l n="tr">Thick as the humming bees, that hunt the golden dew;</l>
<l n="tr">In summer's heat on tops of lilies feed,</l>
<l n="tr">And creep within their bells, to suck the balmy seed:</l>
<l n="tr">The winged army roams the fields around;</l>
<l n="tr">The rivers and the rocks remurmur to the sound.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas wond'ring stood, then ask'd the cause</l>
<l n="tr">Which to the stream the crowding people draws.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus the sire: “The souls that throng the flood</l>
<l n="tr">Are those to whom, by fate, are other bodies ow'd:</l>
<l n="tr">In Lethe's lake they long oblivion taste,</l>
<l n="tr">Of future life secure, forgetful of the past.</l>
<l n="tr">Long has my soul desir'd this time and place,</l>
<l n="tr">To set before your sight your glorious race,</l>
<l n="tr">That this presaging joy may fire your mind</l>
<l n="tr">To seek the shores by destiny design'd.”—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">“O father, can it be, that souls sublime</l>
<l n="tr">Return to visit our terrestrial clime,</l>
<l n="tr">And that the gen'rous mind, releas'd by death,</l>
<l n="tr">Can covet lazy limbs and mortal breath?”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Anchises then, in order, thus begun</l>
<l n="tr">To clear those wonders to his godlike son:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="724" unit="card"/>“Know, first, that heav'n, and earth's compacted frame,</l>
<l n="tr">And flowing waters, and the starry flame,</l>
<l n="tr">And both the radiant lights, one common soul</l>
<l n="tr">Inspires and feeds, and animates the whole.</l>
<l n="tr">This active mind, infus'd thro' all the space,</l>
<l n="tr">Unites and mingles with the mighty mass.</l>
<l n="tr">Hence men and beasts the breath of life obtain,</l>
<l n="tr">And birds of air, and monsters of the main.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' ethereal vigor is in all the same,</l>
<l n="tr">And every soul is fill'd with equal flame;</l>
<l n="tr">As much as earthy limbs, and gross allay</l>
<l n="tr">Of mortal members, subject to decay,</l>
<l n="tr">Blunt not the beams of heav'n and edge of day.</l>
<l n="tr">From this coarse mixture of terrestrial parts,</l>
<l n="tr">Desire and fear by turns possess their hearts,</l>
<l n="tr">And grief, and joy; nor can the groveling mind,</l>
<l n="tr">In the dark dungeon of the limbs confin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Assert the native skies, or own its heav'nly kind:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor death itself can wholly wash their stains;</l>
<l n="tr">But long-contracted filth ev'n in the soul remains.</l>
<l n="tr">The relics of inveterate vice they wear,</l>
<l n="tr">And spots of sin obscene in ev'ry face appear.</l>
<l n="tr">For this are various penances enjoin'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And some are hung to bleach upon the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">Some plung'd in waters, others purg'd in fires,</l>
<l n="tr">Till all the dregs are drain'd, and all the rust expires.</l>
<l n="tr">All have their manes, and those manes bear:</l>
<l n="tr">The few, so cleans'd, to these abodes repair,</l>
<l n="tr">And breathe, in ample fields, the soft Elysian air.</l>
<l n="tr">Then are they happy, when by length of time</l>
<l n="tr">The scurf is worn away of each committed crime;</l>
<l n="tr">No speck is left of their habitual stains,</l>
<l n="tr">But the pure ether of the soul remains.</l>
<l n="tr">But, when a thousand rolling years are past,</l>
<l n="tr">(So long their punishments and penance last,)</l>
<l n="tr">Whole droves of minds are, by the driving god,</l>
<l n="tr">Compell'd to drink the deep Lethaean flood,</l>
<l n="tr">In large forgetful draughts to steep the cares</l>
<l n="tr">Of their past labors, and their irksome years,</l>
<l n="tr">That, unrememb'ring of its former pain,</l>
<l n="tr">The soul may suffer mortal flesh again.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="752" unit="card"/>Thus having said, the father spirit leads</l>
<l n="tr">The priestess and his son thro' swarms of shades,</l>
<l n="tr">And takes a rising ground, from thence to see</l>
<l n="tr">The long procession of his progeny.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="756" unit="card"/>“Survey,” pursued the sire, “this airy throng,</l>
<l n="tr">As, offer'd to thy view, they pass along.</l>
<l n="tr">These are  th'  Italian names, which fate will join</l>
<l n="tr">With ours, and graff upon the Trojan line.</l>
<l n="tr">Observe the youth who first appears in sight,</l>
<l n="tr">And holds the nearest station to the light,</l>
<l n="tr">Already seems to snuff the vital air,</l>
<l n="tr">And leans just forward, on a shining spear:</l>
<l n="tr">Silvius is he, thy last-begotten race,</l>
<l n="tr">But first in order sent, to fill thy place;</l>
<l n="tr">An Alban name, but mix'd with Dardan blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Born in the covert of a shady wood:</l>
<l n="tr">Him fair Lavinia, thy surviving wife,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall breed in groves, to lead a solitary life.</l>
<l n="tr">In Alba he shall fix his royal seat,</l>
<l n="tr">And, born a king, a race of kings beget.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Procas, honor of the Trojan name,</l>
<l n="tr">Capys, and Numitor, of endless fame.</l>
<l n="tr">A second Silvius after these appears;</l>
<l n="tr">Silvius Aeneas, for thy name he bears;</l>
<l n="tr">For arms and justice equally renown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, late restor'd, in Alba shall be crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">How great they look! how vig'rously they wield</l>
<l n="tr">Their weighty lances, and sustain the shield!</l>
<l n="tr">But they, who crown'd with oaken wreaths appear,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall Gabian walls and strong Fidena rear;</l>
<l n="tr">Nomentum, Bola, with Pometia, found;</l>
<l n="tr">And raise Collatian tow'rs on rocky ground.</l>
<l n="tr">All these shall then be towns of mighty fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' now they lie obscure, and lands without a name.</l>
<l n="tr">See <persName>Romulus</persName> the great, born to restore</l>
<l n="tr">The crown that once his injur'd grandsire wore.</l>
<l n="tr">This prince a priestess of your blood shall bear,</l>
<l n="tr">And like his sire in arms he shall appear.</l>
<l n="tr">Two rising crests, his royal head adorn;</l>
<l n="tr">Born from a god, himself to godhead born:</l>
<l n="tr">His sire already signs him for the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And marks the seat amidst the deities.</l>
<l n="tr">Auspicious chief! thy race, in times to come,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall spread the conquests of imperial <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, whose ascending tow'rs shall heav'n invade,</l>
<l n="tr">Involving earth and ocean in her shade;</l>
<l n="tr">High as the Mother of the Gods in place,</l>
<l n="tr">And proud, like her, of an immortal race.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, when in pomp she makes the Phrygian round,</l>
<l n="tr">With golden turrets on her temples crown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred gods her sweeping train supply;</l>
<l n="tr">Her offspring all, and all command the sky.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Now fix your sight, and stand intent, to see</l>
<l n="tr">Your Roman race, and Julian progeny.</l>
<l n="tr">The mighty Caesar waits his vital hour,</l>
<l n="tr">Impatient for the world, and grasps his promis'd pow'r.</l>
<l n="tr">But next behold the youth of form divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Ceasar himself, exalted in his line;</l>
<l n="tr">Augustus, promis'd oft, and long foretold,</l>
<l n="tr">Sent to the realm that <persName>Saturn</persName> rul'd of old;</l>
<l n="tr">Born to restore a better age of gold.</l>
<l n="tr">Afric and <placeName key="tgn,7000198" authname="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> shall his pow'r obey;</l>
<l n="tr">He shall extend his propagated sway</l>
<l n="tr">Beyond the solar year, without the starry way,</l>
<l n="tr">Where Atlas turns the rolling heav'ns around,</l>
<l n="tr">And his broad shoulders with their lights are crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">At his foreseen approach, already quake</l>
<l n="tr">The Caspian kingdoms and Maeotian lake:</l>
<l n="tr">Their seers behold the tempest from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">And threat'ning oracles denounce the war.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,1127805" authname="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> hears him knocking at his sev'nfold gates,</l>
<l n="tr">And seeks his hidden spring, and fears his nephew's fates.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="801" unit="card"/>Nor Hercules more lands or labors knew,</l>
<l n="tr">Not tho' the brazen-footed hind he slew,</l>
<l n="tr">Freed Erymanthus from the foaming boar,</l>
<l n="tr">And dipp'd his arrows in Lernaean gore;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor Bacchus, turning from his Indian war,</l>
<l n="tr">By tigers drawn triumphant in his car,</l>
<l n="tr">From Nisus' top descending on the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">With curling vines around his purple reins.</l>
<l n="tr">And doubt we yet thro' dangers to pursue</l>
<l n="tr">The paths of honor, and a crown in view?</l>
<l n="tr">But what's the man, who from afar appears?</l>
<l n="tr">His head with olive crown'd, his hand a censer bears,</l>
<l n="tr">His hoary beard and holy vestments bring</l>
<l n="tr">His lost idea back: I know the Roman king.</l>
<l n="tr">He shall to peaceful <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> new laws ordain,</l>
<l n="tr">Call'd from his mean abode a scepter to sustain.</l>
<l n="tr">Him Tullus next in dignity succeeds,</l>
<l n="tr">An active prince, and prone to martial deeds.</l>
<l n="tr">He shall his troops for fighting fields prepare,</l>
<l n="tr">Disus'd to toils, and triumphs of the war.</l>
<l n="tr">By dint of sword his crown he shall increase,</l>
<l n="tr">And scour his armor from the rust of peace.</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Ancus follows, with a fawning air,</l>
<l n="tr">But vain within, and proudly popular.</l>
<l n="tr">Next view the Tarquin kings,  th'  avenging sword</l>
<l n="tr">Of Brutus, justly drawn, and <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> restor'd.</l>
<l n="tr">He first renews the rods and ax severe,</l>
<l n="tr">And gives the consuls royal robes to wear.</l>
<l n="tr">His sons, who seek the tyrant to sustain,</l>
<l n="tr">And long for arbitrary lords again,</l>
<l n="tr">With ignominy scourg'd, in open sight,</l>
<l n="tr">He dooms to death deserv'd, asserting public right.</l>
<l n="tr">Unhappy man, to break the pious laws</l>
<l n="tr">Of nature, pleading in his children's cause!</l>
<l n="tr">Howeer the doubtful fact is understood,</l>
<l n="tr">'T is love of honor, and his country's good:</l>
<l n="tr">The consul, not the father, sheds the blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Behold Torquatus the same track pursue;</l>
<l n="tr">And, next, the two devoted Decii view:</l>
<l n="tr">The Drusian line, Camillus loaded home</l>
<l n="tr">With standards well redeem'd, and foreign foes o'ercome</l>
<l n="tr">The pair you see in equal armor shine,</l>
<l n="tr">Now, friends below, in close embraces join;</l>
<l n="tr">But, when they leave the shady realms of night,</l>
<l n="tr">And, cloth'd in bodies, breathe your upper light,</l>
<l n="tr">With mortal hate each other shall pursue:</l>
<l n="tr">What wars, what wounds, what slaughter shall ensue!</l>
<l n="tr">From Alpine heights the father first descends;</l>
<l n="tr">His daughter's husband in the plain attends:</l>
<l n="tr">His daughter's husband arms his eastern friends.</l>
<l n="tr">Embrace again, my sons, be foes no more;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor stain your country with her children's gore!</l>
<l n="tr">And thou, the first, lay down thy lawless claim,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, of my blood, who bearist the Julian name!</l>
<l n="tr">Another comes, who shall in triumph ride,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the Capitol his chariot guide,</l>
<l n="tr">From conquer'd <placeName key="tgn,7010734" authname="tgn,7010734">Corinth</placeName>, rich with Grecian spoils.</l>
<l n="tr">And yet another, fam'd for warlike toils,</l>
<l n="tr">On <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> shall impose the Roman laws,</l>
<l n="tr">And on the Greeks revenge the Trojan cause;</l>
<l n="tr">Shall drag in chains their Achillean race;</l>
<l n="tr">Shall vindicate his ancestors' disgrace,</l>
<l n="tr">And Pallas, for her violated place.</l>
<l n="tr">Great Cato there, for gravity renown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And conqu'ring Cossus goes with laurels crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Who can omit the Gracchi? who declare</l>
<l n="tr">The Scipios' worth, those thunderbolts of war,</l>
<l n="tr">The double bane of <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>? Who can see</l>
<l n="tr">Without esteem for virtuous poverty,</l>
<l n="tr">Severe Fabricius, or can cease T' admire</l>
<l n="tr">The plowman consul in his coarse attire?</l>
<l n="tr">Tir'd as I am, my praise the Fabii claim;</l>
<l n="tr">And thou, great hero, greatest of thy name,</l>
<l n="tr">Ordain'd in war to save the sinking state,</l>
<l n="tr">And, by delays, to put a stop to fate!</l>
<l n="tr">Let others better mold the running mass</l>
<l n="tr">Of metals, and inform the breathing brass,</l>
<l n="tr">And soften into flesh a marble face;</l>
<l n="tr">Plead better at the bar; describe the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And when the stars descend, and when they rise.</l>
<l n="tr">But, <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, 't is thine alone, with awful sway,</l>
<l n="tr">To rule mankind, and make the world obey,</l>
<l n="tr">Disposing peace and war by thy own majestic way;</l>
<l n="tr">To tame the proud, the fetter'd slave to free:</l>
<l n="tr">These are imperial arts, and worthy thee.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="854" unit="card"/>He paus'd; and, while with wond'ring eyes they view'd</l>
<l n="tr">The passing spirits, thus his speech renew'd:</l>
<l n="tr">“See great Marcellus! how, untir'd in toils,</l>
<l n="tr">He moves with manly grace, how rich with regal spoils!</l>
<l n="tr">He, when his country, threaten'd with alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">Requires his courage and his conqu'ring arms,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall more than once the Punic bands affright;</l>
<l n="tr">Shall kill the Gaulish king in single fight;</l>
<l n="tr">Then to the Capitol in triumph move,</l>
<l n="tr">And the third spoils shall grace Feretrian Jove.”</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas here beheld, of form divine,</l>
<l n="tr">A godlike youth in glitt'ring armor shine,</l>
<l n="tr">With great Marcellus keeping equal pace;</l>
<l n="tr">But gloomy were his eyes, dejected was his face.</l>
<l n="tr">He saw, and, wond'ring, ask'd his airy guide,</l>
<l n="tr">What and of whence was he, who press'd the hero's side:</l>
<l n="tr">“His son, or one of his illustrious name?</l>
<l n="tr">How like the former, and almost the same!</l>
<l n="tr">Observe the crowds that compass him around;</l>
<l n="tr">All gaze, and all admire, and raise a shouting sound:</l>
<l n="tr">But hov'ring mists around his brows are spread,</l>
<l n="tr">And night, with sable shades, involves his head.”</l>
<l n="tr">“Seek not to know,” the ghost replied with tears,</l>
<l n="tr">“The sorrows of thy sons in future years.</l>
<l n="tr">This youth (the blissful vision of a day)</l>
<l n="tr">Shall just be shown on earth, and snatch'd away.</l>
<l n="tr">The gods too high had rais'd the Roman state,</l>
<l n="tr">Were but their gifts as permanent as great.</l>
<l n="tr">What groans of men shall fill the Martian field!</l>
<l n="tr">How fierce a blaze his flaming pile shall yield!</l>
<l n="tr">What fun'ral pomp shall floating <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> see,</l>
<l n="tr">When, rising from his bed, he views the sad solemnity!</l>
<l n="tr">No youth shall equal hopes of glory give,</l>
<l n="tr">No youth afford so great a cause to grieve;</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan honor, and the Roman boast,</l>
<l n="tr">Admir'd when living, and ador'd when lost!</l>
<l n="tr">Mirror of ancient faith in early youth!</l>
<l n="tr">Undaunted worth, inviolable truth!</l>
<l n="tr">No foe, unpunish'd, in the fighting field</l>
<l n="tr">Shall dare thee, foot to foot, with sword and shield;</l>
<l n="tr">Much less in arms oppose thy matchless force,</l>
<l n="tr">When thy sharp spurs shall urge thy foaming horse.</l>
<l n="tr">Ah! couldst thou break thro' fate's severe decree,</l>
<l n="tr">A new Marcellus shall arise in thee!</l>
<l n="tr">Full canisters of fragrant lilies bring,</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd with the purple roses of the spring;</l>
<l n="tr">Let me with fun'ral flow'rs his body strow;</l>
<l n="tr">This gift which parents to their children owe,</l>
<l n="tr">This unavailing gift, at least, I may bestow!”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, he led the hero round</l>
<l n="tr">The confines of the blest Elysian ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Which when Anchises to his son had shown,</l>
<l n="tr">And fir'd his mind to mount the promis'd throne,</l>
<l n="tr">He tells the future wars, ordain'd by fate;</l>
<l n="tr">The strength and customs of the Latian state;</l>
<l n="tr">The prince, and people; and forearms his care</l>
<l n="tr">With rules, to push his fortune, or to bear.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="893" unit="card"/>Two gates the silent house of Sleep adorn;</l>
<l n="tr">Of polish'd ivory this, that of transparent horn:</l>
<l n="tr">True visions thro' transparent horn arise;</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' polish'd ivory pass deluding lies.</l>
<l n="tr">Of various things discoursing as he pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises hither bends his steps at last.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, thro' the gate of iv'ry, he dismiss'd</l>
<l n="tr">His valiant offspring and divining guest.</l>
<l n="tr">Straight to the ships Aeneas his way,</l>
<l n="tr">Embark'd his men, and skimm'd along the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">Still coasting, till he gain'd <placeName key="perseus,Caieta" authname="perseus,Caieta">Caieta</placeName>'s bay.</l>
<l n="tr">At length on oozy ground his galleys moor;</l>
<l n="tr">Their heads are turn'd to sea, their sterns to shore.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>