<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="7" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">And thou, O matron of immortal fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Here dying, to the shore hast left thy name;</l>
<l n="tr">Cajeta still the place is call'd from thee,</l>
<l n="tr">The nurse of great Aeneas' infancy.</l>
<l n="tr">Here rest thy bones in rich Hesperia's plains;</l>
<l n="tr">Thy name ('t is all a ghost can have) remains.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="5" unit="card"/>Now, when the prince her fun'ral rites had paid,</l>
<l n="tr">He plow'd the Tyrrhene seas with sails display'd.</l>
<l n="tr">From land a gentle breeze arose by night,</l>
<l n="tr">Serenely shone the stars, the moon was bright,</l>
<l n="tr">And the sea trembled with her silver light.</l>
<l n="tr">Now near the shelves of Circe's shores they run,</l>
<l n="tr">(Circe the rich, the daughter of the Sun,)</l>
<l n="tr">A dang'rous coast: the goddess wastes her days</l>
<l n="tr">In joyous songs; the rocks resound her lays:</l>
<l n="tr">In spinning, or the loom, she spends the night,</l>
<l n="tr">And cedar brands supply her father's light.</l>
<l n="tr">From hence were heard, rebellowing to the main,</l>
<l n="tr">The roars of lions that refuse the chain,</l>
<l n="tr">The grunts of bristled boars, and groans of bears,</l>
<l n="tr">And herds of howling wolves that stun the sailors' ears.</l>
<l n="tr">These from their caverns, at the close of night,</l>
<l n="tr">Fill the sad isle with horror and affright.</l>
<l n="tr">Darkling they mourn their fate, whom Circe's pow'r,</l>
<l n="tr">(That watch'd the moon and planetary hour,)</l>
<l n="tr">With words and wicked herbs from humankind</l>
<l n="tr">Had alter'd, and in brutal shapes confin'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Which monsters lest the Trojans' pious host</l>
<l n="tr">Should bear, or touch upon  th'  inchanted coast,</l>
<l n="tr">Propitious Neptune steer'd their course by night</l>
<l n="tr">With rising gales that sped their happy flight.</l>
<l n="tr">Supplied with these, they skim the sounding shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And hear the swelling surges vainly roar.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="25" unit="card"/>Now, when the rosy morn began to rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And wav'd her saffron streamer thro' the skies;</l>
<l n="tr">When Thetis blush'd in purple not her own,</l>
<l n="tr">And from her face the breathing winds were blown,</l>
<l n="tr">A sudden silence sate upon the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">And sweeping oars, with struggling, urge their way.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan, from the main, beheld a wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Which thick with shades and a brown horror stood:</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the trees the <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> took his course,</l>
<l n="tr">With whirlpools dimpled; and with downward force,</l>
<l n="tr">That drove the sand along, he took his way,</l>
<l n="tr">And roll'd his yellow billows to the sea.</l>
<l n="tr">About him, and above, and round the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">The birds that haunt the borders of his flood,</l>
<l n="tr">That bath'd within, or basked upon his side,</l>
<l n="tr">To tuneful songs their narrow throats applied.</l>
<l n="tr">The captain gives command; the joyful train</l>
<l n="tr">Glide thro' the gloomy shade, and leave the main.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="37" unit="card"/>Now, Erato, thy poet's mind inspire,</l>
<l n="tr">And fill his soul with thy celestial fire!</l>
<l n="tr">Relate what <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> was; her ancient kings;</l>
<l n="tr">Declare the past and state of things,</l>
<l n="tr">When first the Trojan fleet Ausonia sought,</l>
<l n="tr">And how the rivals lov'd, and how they fought.</l>
<l n="tr">These are my theme, and how the war began,</l>
<l n="tr">And how concluded by the godlike man:</l>
<l n="tr">For I shall sing of battles, blood, and rage,</l>
<l n="tr">Which princes and their people did engage;</l>
<l n="tr">And haughty souls, that, mov'd with mutual hate,</l>
<l n="tr">In fighting fields pursued and found their fate;</l>
<l n="tr">That rous'd the Tyrrhene realm with loud alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">And peaceful <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> involv'd in arms.</l>
<l n="tr">A larger scene of action is display'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And, rising hence, a greater work is weigh'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="45" unit="card"/>Latinus, old and mild, had long possess'd</l>
<l n="tr">The Latin scepter, and his people blest:</l>
<l n="tr">His father Faunus; a Laurentian dame</l>
<l n="tr">His mother; fair <persName>Marica</persName> was her name.</l>
<l n="tr">But Faunus came from Picus: Picus drew</l>
<l n="tr">His birth from Saturn, if records be true.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus King Latinus, in the third degree,</l>
<l n="tr">Had Saturn author of his family.</l>
<l n="tr">But this old peaceful prince, as Heav'n decreed,</l>
<l n="tr">Was blest with no male issue to succeed:</l>
<l n="tr">His sons in blooming youth were snatch'd by fate;</l>
<l n="tr">One only daughter heir'd the royal state.</l>
<l n="tr">Fir'd with her love, and with ambition led,</l>
<l n="tr">The neighb'ring princes court her nuptial bed.</l>
<l n="tr">Among the crowd, but far above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">Young Turnus to the beauteous maid address'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Turnus, for high descent and graceful mien,</l>
<l n="tr">Was first, and favor'd by the Latian queen;</l>
<l n="tr">With him she strove to join <persName>Lavinia</persName>'s hand,</l>
<l n="tr">But dire portents the purpos'd match withstand.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Deep in the palace, of long growth, there stood</l>
<l n="tr">A laurel's trunk, a venerable wood;</l>
<l n="tr">Where rites divine were paid; whose holy hair</l>
<l n="tr">Was kept and cut with superstitious care.</l>
<l n="tr">This plant Latinus, when his town he wall'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Then found, and from the tree Laurentum call'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And last, in honor of his new abode,</l>
<l n="tr">He vow'd the laurel to the laurel's god.</l>
<l n="tr">It happen'd once (a boding prodigy!)</l>
<l n="tr">A swarm of bees, that cut the liquid sky,</l>
<l n="tr">(Unknown from whence they took their airy flight,)</l>
<l n="tr">Upon the topmost branch in clouds alight;</l>
<l n="tr">There with their clasping feet together clung,</l>
<l n="tr">And a long cluster from the laurel hung.</l>
<l n="tr">An ancient augur prophesied from hence:</l>
<l n="tr">“Behold on Latian shores a foreign prince!</l>
<l n="tr">From the same parts of heav'n his navy stands,</l>
<l n="tr">To the same parts on earth; his army lands;</l>
<l n="tr">The town he conquers, and the tow'r commands.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yet more, when fair Lavinia fed the fire</l>
<l n="tr">Before the gods, and stood beside her sire,</l>
<l n="tr">(Strange to relate!) the flames, involv'd in smoke</l>
<l n="tr">Of incense, from the sacred altar broke,</l>
<l n="tr">Caught her dishevel'd hair and rich attire;</l>
<l n="tr">Her crown and jewels crackled in the fire:</l>
<l n="tr">From thence the fuming trail began to spread</l>
<l n="tr">And lambent glories danc'd about her head.</l>
<l n="tr">This new portent the seer with wonder views,</l>
<l n="tr">Then pausing, thus his prophecy renews:</l>
<l n="tr">“The nymph, who scatters flaming fires around,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall shine with honor, shall herself be crown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">But, caus'd by her irrevocable fate,</l>
<l n="tr">War shall the country waste, and change the state.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="81" unit="card"/>Latinus, frighted with this dire ostent,</l>
<l n="tr">For counsel to his father Faunus went,</l>
<l n="tr">And sought the shades renown'd for prophecy</l>
<l n="tr">Which near Albunea's sulph'rous fountain lie.</l>
<l n="tr">To these the Latian and the Sabine land</l>
<l n="tr">Fly, when distress'd, and thence relief demand.</l>
<l n="tr">The priest on skins of off'rings takes his ease,</l>
<l n="tr">And nightly visions in his slumber sees;</l>
<l n="tr">A swarm of thin aerial shapes appears,</l>
<l n="tr">And, flutt'ring round his temples, deafs his ears:</l>
<l n="tr">These he consults, the future fates to know,</l>
<l n="tr">From pow'rs above, and from the fiends below.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, for the gods' advice, Latinus flies,</l>
<l n="tr">Off'ring a hundred sheep for sacrifice:</l>
<l n="tr">Their woolly fleeces, as the rites requir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">He laid beneath him, and to rest retir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">No sooner were his eyes in slumber bound,</l>
<l n="tr">When, from above, a more than mortal sound</l>
<l n="tr">Invades his ears; and thus the vision spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“Seek not, my seed, in Latian bands to yoke</l>
<l n="tr">Our fair <persName>Lavinia</persName>, nor the gods provoke.</l>
<l n="tr">A foreign son upon thy shore descends,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose martial fame from pole to pole extends.</l>
<l n="tr">His race, in arms and arts of peace renown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Not <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> shall contain, nor <placeName key="tgn,1000003" authname="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> bound:</l>
<l n="tr">'T is theirs whate'er the sun surveys around.”</l>
<l n="tr">These answers, in the silent night receiv'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The king himself divulg'd, the land believ'd:</l>
<l n="tr">The fame thro' all the neighb'ring nations flew,</l>
<l n="tr">When now the Trojan navy was in view.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="107" unit="card"/>Beneath a shady tree, the hero spread</l>
<l n="tr">His table on the turf, with cakes of bread;</l>
<l n="tr">And, with his chiefs, on forest fruits he fed.</l>
<l n="tr">They sate; and, (not without the god's command,)</l>
<l n="tr">Their homely fare dispatch'd, the hungry band</l>
<l n="tr">Invade their trenchers next, and soon devour,</l>
<l n="tr">To mend the scanty meal, their cakes of flour.</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius this observ'd, and smiling said:</l>
<l n="tr">“See, we devour the plates on which we fed.”</l>
<l n="tr">The speech had omen, that the Trojan race</l>
<l n="tr">Should find repose, and this the time and place.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas took the word, and thus replies,</l>
<l n="tr">Confessing fate with wonder in his eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">“All hail, O earth! all hail, my household gods!</l>
<l n="tr">Behold the destin'd place of your abodes!</l>
<l n="tr">For thus Anchises prophesied of old,</l>
<l n="tr">And this our fatal place of rest foretold:</l>
<l n="tr">‘When, on a foreign shore, instead of meat,</l>
<l n="tr">By famine forc'd, your trenchers you shall eat,</l>
<l n="tr">Then ease your weary Trojans will attend,</l>
<l n="tr">And the long labors of your voyage end.</l>
<l n="tr">Remember on that happy coast to build,</l>
<l n="tr">And with a trench inclose the fruitful field.’</l>
<l n="tr">This was that famine, this the fatal place</l>
<l n="tr">Which ends the wand'ring of our exil'd race.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, on to-morrow's dawn, your care employ,</l>
<l n="tr">To search the land, and where the cities lie,</l>
<l n="tr">And what the men; but give this day to joy.</l>
<l n="tr">Now pour to Jove; and, after Jove is blest,</l>
<l n="tr">Call great Anchises to the genial feast:</l>
<l n="tr">Crown high the goblets with a cheerful draught;</l>
<l n="tr">Enjoy the present hour; adjourn the future thought.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="135" unit="card"/>Thus having said, the hero bound his brows</l>
<l n="tr">With leafy branches, then perform'd his vows;</l>
<l n="tr">Adoring first the genius of the place,</l>
<l n="tr">Then Earth, the mother of the heav'nly race,</l>
<l n="tr">The nymphs, and native godheads yet unknown,</l>
<l n="tr">And Night, and all the stars that gild her sable throne,</l>
<l n="tr">And ancient Cybel, and Idaean Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">And last his sire below, and mother queen above.</l>
<l n="tr">Then heav'n's high monarch thunder'd thrice aloud,</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice he shook aloft a golden cloud.</l>
<l n="tr">Soon thro' the joyful camp a rumor flew,</l>
<l n="tr">The time was come their city to renew.</l>
<l n="tr">Then ev'ry brow with cheerful green is crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The feasts are doubled, and the bowls go round.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="148" unit="card"/>When next the rosy morn disclos'd the day,</l>
<l n="tr">The scouts to sev'ral parts divide their way,</l>
<l n="tr">To learn the natives' names, their towns explore,</l>
<l n="tr">The coasts and trendings of the crooked shore:</l>
<l n="tr">Here <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> flows, and here Numicus stands;</l>
<l n="tr">Here warlike Latins hold the happy lands.</l>
<l n="tr">The pious chief, who sought by peaceful ways</l>
<l n="tr">To found his empire, and his town to raise,</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred youths from all his train selects,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the Latian court their course directs,</l>
<l n="tr">(The spacious palace where their prince resides,)</l>
<l n="tr">And all their heads with wreaths of olive hides.</l>
<l n="tr">They go commission'd to require a peace,</l>
<l n="tr">And carry presents to procure access.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while they speed their pace, the prince designs</l>
<l n="tr">His new-elected seat, and draws the lines.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans round the place a rampire cast,</l>
<l n="tr">And palisades about the trenches plac'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Meantime the train, proceeding on their way,</l>
<l n="tr">From far the town and lofty tow'rs survey;</l>
<l n="tr">At length approach the walls. Without the gate,</l>
<l n="tr">They see the boys and Latian youth debate</l>
<l n="tr">The martial prizes on the dusty plain:</l>
<l n="tr">Some drive the cars, and some the coursers rein;</l>
<l n="tr">Some bend the stubborn bow for victory,</l>
<l n="tr">And some with darts their active sinews try.</l>
<l n="tr">A posting messenger, dispatch'd from hence,</l>
<l n="tr">Of this fair troop advis'd their aged prince,</l>
<l n="tr">That foreign men of mighty stature came;</l>
<l n="tr">Uncouth their habit, and unknown their name.</l>
<l n="tr">The king ordains their entrance, and ascends</l>
<l n="tr">His regal seat, surrounded by his friends.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="170" unit="card"/>The palace built by Picus, vast and proud,</l>
<l n="tr">Supported by a hundred pillars stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And round incompass'd with a rising wood.</l>
<l n="tr">The pile o'erlook'd the town, and drew the sight;</l>
<l n="tr">Surpris'd at once with reverence and delight.</l>
<l n="tr">There kings receiv'd the marks of sov'reign pow'r;</l>
<l n="tr">In state the monarchs march'd; the lictors bore</l>
<l n="tr">Their awful axes and the rods before.</l>
<l n="tr">Here the tribunal stood, the house of pray'r,</l>
<l n="tr">And here the sacred senators repair;</l>
<l n="tr">All at large tables, in long order set,</l>
<l n="tr">A ram their off'ring, and a ram their meat.</l>
<l n="tr">Above the portal, carv'd in cedar wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Plac'd in their ranks, their godlike grandsires stood;</l>
<l n="tr">Old Saturn, with his crooked scythe, on high;</l>
<l n="tr">And Italus, that led the colony;</l>
<l n="tr">And ancient Janus, with his double face,</l>
<l n="tr">And bunch of keys, the porter of the place.</l>
<l n="tr">There good Sabinus, planter of the vines,</l>
<l n="tr">On a short pruning hook his head reclines,</l>
<l n="tr">And studiously surveys his gen'rous wines;</l>
<l n="tr">Then warlike kings, who for their country fought,</l>
<l n="tr">And honorable wounds from battle brought.</l>
<l n="tr">Around the posts hung helmets, darts, and spears,</l>
<l n="tr">And captive chariots, axes, shields, and bars,</l>
<l n="tr">And broken beaks of ships, the trophies of their wars.</l>
<l n="tr">Above the rest, as chief of all the band,</l>
<l n="tr">Was Picus plac'd, a buckler in his hand;</l>
<l n="tr">His other wav'd a long divining wand.</l>
<l n="tr">Girt in his Gabin gown the hero sate,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet could not with his art avoid his fate:</l>
<l n="tr">For Circe long had lov'd the youth in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">Till love, refus'd, converted to disdain:</l>
<l n="tr">Then, mixing pow'rful herbs, with magic art,</l>
<l n="tr">She chang'd his form, who could not change his heart;</l>
<l n="tr">Constrain'd him in a bird, and made him fly,</l>
<l n="tr">With party-color'd plumes, a chatt'ring pie.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="192" unit="card"/>In this high temple, on a chair of state,</l>
<l n="tr">The seat of audience, old Latinus sate;</l>
<l n="tr">Then gave admission to the Trojan train;</l>
<l n="tr">And thus with pleasing accents he began:</l>
<l n="tr">“Tell me, ye Trojans, for that name you own,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor is your course upon our coasts unknown—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Say what you seek, and whither were you bound:</l>
<l n="tr">Were you by stress of weather cast aground?</l>
<l n="tr">(Such dangers as on seas are often seen,</l>
<l n="tr">And oft befall to miserable men,)</l>
<l n="tr">Or come, your shipping in our ports to lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Spent and disabled in so long a way?</l>
<l n="tr">Say what you want: the Latians you shall find</l>
<l n="tr">Not forc'd to goodness, but by will inclin'd;</l>
<l n="tr">For, since the time of Saturn's holy reign,</l>
<l n="tr">His hospitable customs we retain.</l>
<l n="tr">I call to mind (but time the tale has worn)</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Arunci told, that Dardanus, tho' born</l>
<l n="tr">On Latian plains, yet sought the Phrygian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="perseus,Samothrace City" authname="perseus,Samothrace City">Samothracia</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Samos City" authname="perseus,Samos City">Samos</placeName> call'd before.</l>
<l n="tr">From Tuscan Coritum he claim'd his birth;</l>
<l n="tr">But after, when exempt from mortal earth,</l>
<l n="tr">From thence ascended to his kindred skies,</l>
<l n="tr">A god, and, as a god, augments their sacrifice,”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="212" unit="card"/>He said. Ilioneus made this reply:</l>
<l n="tr">“O king, of Faunus' royal family!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor wintry winds to <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> forc'd our way,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did the stars our wand'ring course betray.</l>
<l n="tr">Willing we sought your shores; and, hither bound,</l>
<l n="tr">The port, so long desir'd, at length we found;</l>
<l n="tr">From our sweet homes and ancient realms expell'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Great as the greatest that the sun beheld.</l>
<l n="tr">The god began our line, who rules above;</l>
<l n="tr">And, as our race, our king descends from Jove:</l>
<l n="tr">And hither are we come, by his command,</l>
<l n="tr">To crave admission in your happy land.</l>
<l n="tr">How dire a tempest, from <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> pour'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Our plains, our temples, and our town devour'd;</l>
<l n="tr">What was the waste of war, what fierce alarms</l>
<l n="tr">Shook <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s crown with European arms;</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n such have heard, if any such there be,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose earth is bounded by the frozen sea;</l>
<l n="tr">And such as, born beneath the burning sky</l>
<l n="tr">And sultry sun, betwixt the tropics lie.</l>
<l n="tr">From that dire deluge, thro' the wat'ry waste,</l>
<l n="tr">Such length of years, such various perils past,</l>
<l n="tr">At last escap'd, to <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> we repair,</l>
<l n="tr">To beg what you without your want may spare:</l>
<l n="tr">The common water, and the common air;</l>
<l n="tr">Sheds which ourselves will build, and mean abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">Fit to receive and serve our banish'd gods.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor our admission shall your realm disgrace,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor length of time our gratitude efface.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, what endless honor you shall gain,</l>
<l n="tr">To save and shelter <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s unhappy train!</l>
<l n="tr">Now, by my sov'reign, and his fate, I swear,</l>
<l n="tr">Renown'd for faith in peace, for force in war;</l>
<l n="tr">Oft our alliance other lands desir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, what we seek of you, of us requir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Despite not then, that in our hands we bear</l>
<l n="tr">These holy boughs, sue with words of pray'r.</l>
<l n="tr">Fate and the gods, by their supreme command,</l>
<l n="tr">Have doom'd our ships to seek the Latian land.</l>
<l n="tr">To these abodes our fleet Apollo sends;</l>
<l n="tr">Here Dardanus was born, and hither tends;</l>
<l n="tr">Where Tuscan Tiber rolls with rapid force,</l>
<l n="tr">And where Numicus opes his holy source.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, our prince presents, with his request,</l>
<l n="tr">Some small remains of what his sire possess'd.</l>
<l n="tr">This golden charger, snatch'd from burning <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Anchises did in sacrifice employ;</l>
<l n="tr">This royal robe and this tiara wore</l>
<l n="tr">Old Priam, and this golden scepter bore</l>
<l n="tr">In full assemblies, and in solemn games;</l>
<l n="tr">These purple vests were weav'd by Dardan dames.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="249" unit="card"/>Thus while he spoke, Latinus roll'd around</l>
<l n="tr">His eyes, and fix'd a while upon the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Intent he seem'd, and anxious in his breast;</l>
<l n="tr">Not by the scepter mov'd, or kingly vest,</l>
<l n="tr">But pond'ring future things of wondrous weight;</l>
<l n="tr">Succession, empire, and his daughter's fate.</l>
<l n="tr">On these he mus'd within his thoughtful mind,</l>
<l n="tr">And then revolv'd what Faunus had divin'd.</l>
<l n="tr">This was the foreign prince, by fate decreed</l>
<l n="tr">To share his scepter, and Lavinia's bed;</l>
<l n="tr">This was the race that sure portents foreshew</l>
<l n="tr">To sway the world, and land and sea subdue.</l>
<l n="tr">At length he rais'd his cheerful head, and spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“The pow'rs,” said he, “the pow'rs we both invoke,</l>
<l n="tr">To you, and yours, and mine, propitious be,</l>
<l n="tr">And firm our purpose with their augury!</l>
<l n="tr">Have what you ask; your presents I receive;</l>
<l n="tr">Land, where and when you please, with ample leave;</l>
<l n="tr">Partake and use my kingdom as your own;</l>
<l n="tr">All shall be yours, while I command the crown:</l>
<l n="tr">And, if my wish'd alliance please your king,</l>
<l n="tr">Tell him he should not send the peace, but bring.</l>
<l n="tr">Then let him not a friend's embraces fear;</l>
<l n="tr">The peace is made when I behold him here.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides this answer, tell my royal guest,</l>
<l n="tr">I add to his commands my own request:</l>
<l n="tr">One only daughter heirs my crown and state,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom not our oracles, nor Heav'n, nor fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor frequent prodigies, permit to join</l>
<l n="tr">With any native of  th'  Ausonian line.</l>
<l n="tr">A foreign son-in-law shall come from far</l>
<l n="tr">(Such is our doom), a chief renown'd in war,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose race shall bear aloft the Latian name,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro' the conquer'd world diffuse our fame.</l>
<l n="tr">Himself to be the man the fates require,</l>
<l n="tr">I firmly judge, and, what I judge, desire.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He said, and then on each bestow'd a steed.</l>
<l n="tr">Three hundred horses, in high stables fed,</l>
<l n="tr">Stood ready, shining all, and smoothly dress'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Of these he chose the fairest and the best,</l>
<l n="tr">To mount the Trojan troop. At his command</l>
<l n="tr">The steeds caparison'd with purple stand,</l>
<l n="tr">With golden trappings, glorious to behold,</l>
<l n="tr">And champ betwixt their teeth the foaming gold.</l>
<l n="tr">Then to his absent guest the king decreed</l>
<l n="tr">A pair of coursers born of heav'nly breed,</l>
<l n="tr">Who from their nostrils breath'd ethereal fire;</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Circe stole from her celestial sire,</l>
<l n="tr">By substituting mares produc'd on earth,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose wombs conceiv'd a more than mortal birth.</l>
<l n="tr">These draw the chariot which Latinus sends,</l>
<l n="tr">And the rich present to the prince commends.</l>
<l n="tr">Sublime on stately steeds the Trojans borne,</l>
<l n="tr">To their expecting lord with peace return.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="286" unit="card"/>But jealous Juno, from Pachynus' height,</l>
<l n="tr">As she from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> took her airy flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Beheld with envious eyes this hateful sight.</l>
<l n="tr">She saw the Trojan and his joyful train</l>
<l n="tr">Descend upon the shore, desert the main,</l>
<l n="tr">Design a town, and, with unhop'd success,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' embassadors return with promis'd peace.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, pierc'd with pain, she shook her haughty head,</l>
<l n="tr">Sigh'd from her inward soul, and thus she said:</l>
<l n="tr">“O hated offspring of my Phrygian foes!</l>
<l n="tr">O fates of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, which Juno's fates oppose!</l>
<l n="tr">Could they not fall unpitied on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">But slain revive, and, taken, scape again?</l>
<l n="tr">When execrable <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> in ashes lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' fires and swords and seas they forc'd their way.</l>
<l n="tr">Then vanquish'd Juno must in vain contend,</l>
<l n="tr">Her rage disarm'd, her empire at an end.</l>
<l n="tr">Breathless and tir'd, is all my fury spent?</l>
<l n="tr">Or does my glutted spleen at length relent?</l>
<l n="tr">As if 't were little from their town to chase,</l>
<l n="tr">I thro' the seas pursued their exil'd race;</l>
<l n="tr">Ingag'd the heav'ns, oppos'd the stormy main;</l>
<l n="tr">But billows roar'd, and tempests rag'd in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">What have my Scyllas and my Syrtes done,</l>
<l n="tr">When these they overpass, and those they shun?</l>
<l n="tr">On <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s shores they land, secure of fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Triumphant o'er the storms and Juno's hate.</l>
<l n="tr">Mars could in mutual blood the Centaurs bathe,</l>
<l n="tr">And Jove himself gave way to Cynthia's wrath,</l>
<l n="tr">Who sent the tusky boar to Calydon;</l>
<l n="tr">(What great offense had either people done?)</l>
<l n="tr">But I, the consort of the Thunderer,</l>
<l n="tr">Have wag'd a long and unsuccessful war,</l>
<l n="tr">With various arts and arms in vain have toil'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And by a mortal man at length am foil'd.</l>
<l n="tr">If native pow'r prevail not, shall I doubt</l>
<l n="tr">To seek for needful succor from without?</l>
<l n="tr">If Jove and Heav'n my just desires deny,</l>
<l n="tr">Hell shall the pow'r of Heav'n and Jove supply.</l>
<l n="tr">Grant that the Fates have firm'd, by their decree,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan race to reign in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>;</l>
<l n="tr">At least I can defer the nuptial day,</l>
<l n="tr">And with protracted wars the peace delay:</l>
<l n="tr">With blood the dear alliance shall be bought,</l>
<l n="tr">And both the people near destruction brought;</l>
<l n="tr">So shall the son-in-law and father join,</l>
<l n="tr">With ruin, war, and waste of either line.</l>
<l n="tr">O fatal maid, thy marriage is endow'd</l>
<l n="tr">With Phrygian, Latian, andRutulian blood!</l>
<l n="tr">Bellona leads thee to thy lover's hand;</l>
<l n="tr">Another queen brings forth another brand,</l>
<l n="tr">To burn with foreign fires another land!</l>
<l n="tr">A second <persName>Paris</persName>, diff'ring but in name,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall fire his country with a second flame.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="323" unit="card"/>Thus having said, she sinks beneath the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">With furious haste, and shoots the Stygian sound,</l>
<l n="tr">To rouse Alecto from  th'  infernal seat</l>
<l n="tr">Of her dire sisters, and their dark retreat.</l>
<l n="tr">This Fury, fit for her intent, she chose;</l>
<l n="tr">One who delights in wars and human woes.</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n Pluto hates his own misshapen race;</l>
<l n="tr">Her sister Furies fly her hideous face;</l>
<l n="tr">So frightful are the forms the monster takes,</l>
<l n="tr">So fierce the hissings of her speckled snakes.</l>
<l n="tr">Her Juno finds, and thus inflames her spite:</l>
<l n="tr">“O virgin daughter of eternal Night,</l>
<l n="tr">Give me this once thy labor, to sustain</l>
<l n="tr">My right, and execute my just disdain.</l>
<l n="tr">Let not the Trojans, with a feign'd pretense</l>
<l n="tr">Of proffer'd peace, delude the Latian prince.</l>
<l n="tr">Expel from <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> that odious name,</l>
<l n="tr">And let not Juno suffer in her fame.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is thine to ruin realms, o'erturn a state,</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the dearest friends to raise debate,</l>
<l n="tr">And kindle kindred blood to mutual hate.</l>
<l n="tr">Thy hand o'er towns the fun'ral torch displays,</l>
<l n="tr">And forms a thousand ills ten thousand ways.</l>
<l n="tr">Now shake, out thy fruitful breast, the seeds</l>
<l n="tr">Of envy, discord, and of cruel deeds:</l>
<l n="tr">Confound the peace establish'd, and prepare</l>
<l n="tr">Their souls to hatred, and their hands to war.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="341" unit="card"/>Smear'd as she was with black Gorgonian blood,</l>
<l n="tr">The Fury sprang above the Stygian flood;</l>
<l n="tr">And on her wicker wings, sublime thro' night,</l>
<l n="tr">She to the Latian palace took her flight:</l>
<l n="tr">There sought the queen's apartment, stood before</l>
<l n="tr">The peaceful threshold, and besieg'd the door.</l>
<l n="tr">Restless Amata lay, her swelling breast</l>
<l n="tr">Fir'd with disdain for Turnus dispossess'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And the new nuptials of the Trojan guest.</l>
<l n="tr">From her black bloody locks the Fury shakes</l>
<l n="tr">Her darling plague, the fav'rite of her snakes;</l>
<l n="tr">With her full force she threw the poisonous dart,</l>
<l n="tr">And fix'd it deep within Amata's heart,</l>
<l n="tr">That, thus envenom'd, she might kindle rage,</l>
<l n="tr">And sacrifice to strife her house husband's age.</l>
<l n="tr">Unseen, unfelt, the fiery serpent skims</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt her linen and her naked limbs;</l>
<l n="tr">His baleful breath inspiring, as he glides,</l>
<l n="tr">Now like a chain around her neck he rides,</l>
<l n="tr">Now like a fillet to her head repairs,</l>
<l n="tr">And with his circling volumes folds her hairs.</l>
<l n="tr">At first the silent venom slid with ease,</l>
<l n="tr">And seiz'd her cooler senses by degrees;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, ere  th'  infected mass was fir'd too far,</l>
<l n="tr">In plaintive accents she began the war,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus bespoke her husband: “Shall,” she said,</l>
<l n="tr">“A wand'ring prince enjoy Lavinia's bed?</l>
<l n="tr">If nature plead not in a parent's heart,</l>
<l n="tr">Pity my tears, and pity her desert.</l>
<l n="tr">I know, my dearest lord, the time will come,</l>
<l n="tr">You in vain, reverse your cruel doom;</l>
<l n="tr">The faithless pirate soon will set to sea,</l>
<l n="tr">And bear the royal virgin far away!</l>
<l n="tr">A guest like him, a Trojan guest before,</l>
<l n="tr">In shew of friendship sought the Spartan shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And ravish'd Helen from her husband bore.</l>
<l n="tr">Think on a king's inviolable word;</l>
<l n="tr">And think on Turnus, her once plighted lord:</l>
<l n="tr">To this false foreigner you give your throne,</l>
<l n="tr">And wrong a friend, a kinsman, and a son.</l>
<l n="tr">Resume your ancient care; and, if the god</l>
<l n="tr">Your sire, and you, resolve on foreign blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Know all are foreign, in a larger sense,</l>
<l n="tr">Not born your subjects, or deriv'd from hence.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, if the line of Turnus you retrace,</l>
<l n="tr">He springs from Inachus of <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> race.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="373" unit="card"/>But when she saw her reasons idly spent,</l>
<l n="tr">And could not move him from his fix'd intent,</l>
<l n="tr">She flew to rage; for now the snake possess'd</l>
<l n="tr">Her vital parts, and poison'd all her breast;</l>
<l n="tr">She raves, she runs with a distracted pace,</l>
<l n="tr">And fills with horrid howls the public place.</l>
<l n="tr">And, as young striplings whip the top for sport,</l>
<l n="tr">On the smooth pavement of an empty court;</l>
<l n="tr">The wooden engine flies and whirls about,</l>
<l n="tr">Admir'd, with clamors, of the beardless rout;</l>
<l n="tr">They lash aloud; each other they provoke,</l>
<l n="tr">And lend their little souls at ev'ry stroke:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus fares the queen; and thus her fury blows</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the crowd, and kindles as she goes.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor yet content, she strains her malice more,</l>
<l n="tr">And adds new ills to those contriv'd before:</l>
<l n="tr">She flies the town, and, mixing with a throng</l>
<l n="tr">Of madding matrons, bears the bride along,</l>
<l n="tr">Wand'ring thro' woods and wilds, and devious ways,</l>
<l n="tr">And with these arts the Trojan match delays.</l>
<l n="tr">She feign'd the rites of Bacchus; cried aloud,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the buxom god the virgin vow'd.</l>
<l n="tr">“Evoe! O Bacchus!” thus began the song;</l>
<l n="tr">And “Evoe!” answer'd all the female throng.</l>
<l n="tr">“O virgin! worthy thee alone!” she cried;</l>
<l n="tr">“O worthy thee alone!” the crew replied.</l>
<l n="tr">“For thee she feeds her hair, she leads thy dance,</l>
<l n="tr">And with thy winding ivy wreathes her lance.”</l>
<l n="tr">Like fury seiz'd the rest; the progress known,</l>
<l n="tr">All seek the mountains, and forsake the town:</l>
<l n="tr">All, clad in skins of beasts, the jav'lin bear,</l>
<l n="tr">Give to the wanton winds their flowing hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And shrieks and shoutings rend the suff'ring air.</l>
<l n="tr">The queen herself, inspir'd with rage divine,</l>
<l n="tr">Shook high above her head a flaming pine;</l>
<l n="tr">Then roll'd her haggard eyes around the throng,</l>
<l n="tr">And sung, in Turnus' name, the nuptial song:</l>
<l n="tr">“Io, ye Latian dames! if any here</l>
<l n="tr">Hold your unhappy queen, Amata, dear;</l>
<l n="tr">If there be here,” she said, who dare maintain</l>
<l n="tr">My right, nor think the name of mother vain;</l>
<l n="tr">Unbind your fillets, loose your flowing hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And orgies and nocturnal rites prepare.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="406" unit="card"/>Amata's breast the Fury thus invades,</l>
<l n="tr">And fires with rage, amid the sylvan shades;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, when she found her venom spread so far,</l>
<l n="tr">The royal house embroil'd in civil war,</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd on her dusky wings, she cleaves the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And seeks the palace where young Turnus lies.</l>
<l n="tr">His town, as fame reports, was built of old</l>
<l n="tr">By Danae, pregnant with almighty gold,</l>
<l n="tr">Who fled her father's rage, and, with a train</l>
<l n="tr">Of following Argives, thro' the stormy main,</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n by the southern blasts, was fated here to reign.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was Ardua once; now <placeName key="perseus,Ardea" authname="perseus,Ardea">Ardea</placeName>'s name it bears;</l>
<l n="tr">Once a fair city, now consum'd with years.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, in his lofty palace, Turnus lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the confines of the night and day,</l>
<l n="tr">Secure in sleep. The Fury laid aside</l>
<l n="tr">Her looks and limbs, and with new methods tried</l>
<l n="tr">The foulness of  th'  infernal form to hide.</l>
<l n="tr">Propp'd on a staff, she takes a trembling mien:</l>
<l n="tr">Her face is furrow'd, and her front obscene;</l>
<l n="tr">Deep-dinted wrinkles on her cheek she draws;</l>
<l n="tr">Sunk are her eyes, and toothless are her jaws;</l>
<l n="tr">Her hoary hair with holy fillets bound,</l>
<l n="tr">Her temples with an olive wreath are crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Old Chalybe, who kept the sacred fane</l>
<l n="tr">Of Juno, now she seem'd, and thus began,</l>
<l n="tr">Appearing in a dream, to rouse the careless man:</l>
<l n="tr">“Shall Turnus then such endless toil sustain</l>
<l n="tr">In fighting fields, and conquer towns in vain?</l>
<l n="tr">Win, for a Trojan head to wear the prize,</l>
<l n="tr">Usurp thy crown, enjoy thy victories?</l>
<l n="tr">The bride and scepter which thy blood has bought,</l>
<l n="tr">The king transfers; and foreign heirs are sought.</l>
<l n="tr">Go now, deluded man, and seek again</l>
<l n="tr">New toils, new dangers, on the dusty plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Repel the Tuscan foes; their city seize;</l>
<l n="tr">Protect the Latians in luxurious ease.</l>
<l n="tr">This dream all-pow'rful Juno sends; I bear</l>
<l n="tr">Her mighty mandates, and her words you hear.</l>
<l n="tr">Haste; arm your Ardeans; issue to the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">With fate to friend, assault the Trojan train:</l>
<l n="tr">Their thoughtless chiefs, their painted ships, that lie</l>
<l n="tr">In <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s mouth, with fire and sword destroy.</l>
<l n="tr">The Latian king, unless he shall submit,</l>
<l n="tr">Own his old promise, and his new forgeT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Let him, in arms, the pow'r of Turnus prove,</l>
<l n="tr">And learn to fear whom he disdains to love.</l>
<l n="tr">For such is Heav'n's command.”<milestone ed="p" n="435" unit="card"/>The youthful prince</l>
<l n="tr">With scorn replied, and made this bold defense:</l>
<l n="tr">“You tell me, mother, what I knew before:</l>
<l n="tr">The Phrygian fleet is landed on the shore.</l>
<l n="tr">I neither fear nor will provoke the war;</l>
<l n="tr">My fate is <persName>Juno</persName>'s most peculiar care.</l>
<l n="tr">But time has made you dote, and vainly tell</l>
<l n="tr">Of arms imagin'd in your lonely cell.</l>
<l n="tr">Go; be the temple and the gods your care;</l>
<l n="tr">Permit to men the thought of peace and war.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="445" unit="card"/>These haughty words Alecto's rage provoke,</l>
<l n="tr">And frighted Turnus trembled as she spoke.</l>
<l n="tr">Her eyes grow stiffen'd, and with sulphur burn;</l>
<l n="tr">Her hideous looks and hellish form return;</l>
<l n="tr">Her curling snakes with hissings fill the place,</l>
<l n="tr">And open all the furies of her face:</l>
<l n="tr">Then, darting fire from her malignant eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">She cast him backward as he strove to rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And, ling'ring, sought to frame some new replies.</l>
<l n="tr">High on her head she rears two twisted snakes,</l>
<l n="tr">Her chains she rattles, and her whip she shakes;</l>
<l n="tr">And, churning bloody foam, thus loudly speaks:</l>
<l n="tr">“Behold whom time has made to dote, and tell</l>
<l n="tr">Of arms imagin'd in her lonely cell!</l>
<l n="tr">Behold the Fates' infernal minister!</l>
<l n="tr">War, death, destruction, in my hand I bear.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus having said, her smold'ring torch, impress'd</l>
<l n="tr">With her full force, she plung'd into his breast.</l>
<l n="tr">Aghast he wak'd; and, starting from his bed,</l>
<l n="tr">Cold sweat, in clammy drops, his limbs o'erspread.</l>
<l n="tr">“Arms! arms!” he cries: “my sword and shield prepare!”</l>
<l n="tr">He breathes defiance, blood, and mortal war.</l>
<l n="tr">So, when with crackling flames a caldron fries,</l>
<l n="tr">The bubbling waters from the bottom rise:</l>
<l n="tr">Above the brims they force their fiery way;</l>
<l n="tr">Black vapors climb aloft, and cloud the day.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The peace polluted thus, a chosen band</l>
<l n="tr">He first commissions to the Latian land,</l>
<l n="tr">In threat'ning embassy; then rais'd the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">To meet in arms  th'  intruding Trojan guest,</l>
<l n="tr">To force the foes from the Lavinian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>'s indanger'd peace restore.</l>
<l n="tr">Himself alone an equal match he boasts,</l>
<l n="tr">To fight the Phrygian and Ausonian hosts.</l>
<l n="tr">The gods invok'd, the Rutuli prepare</l>
<l n="tr">Their arms, and warn each other to the war.</l>
<l n="tr">His beauty these, and those his blooming age,</l>
<l n="tr">The rest his house and his own fame ingage.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="475" unit="card"/>While Turnus urges thus his enterprise,</l>
<l n="tr">The Stygian Fury to the Trojans flies;</l>
<l n="tr">New frauds invents, and takes a steepy stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Which overlooks the vale with wide command;</l>
<l n="tr">Where fair Ascanius and his youthful train,</l>
<l n="tr">With horns and hounds, a hunting match ordain,</l>
<l n="tr">And pitch their toils around the shady plain.</l>
<l n="tr">The Fury fires the pack; they snuff, they vent,</l>
<l n="tr">And feed their hungry nostrils with the scent.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was of a well-grown stag, whose antlers rise</l>
<l n="tr">High o'er his front; his beams invade the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">From this light cause  th'  infernal maid prepares</l>
<l n="tr">The country churls to mischief, hate, and wars.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The stately beast the two Tyrrhidae bred,</l>
<l n="tr">Snatch'd from his dams, and the tame youngling fed.</l>
<l n="tr">Their father Tyrrheus did his fodder bring,</l>
<l n="tr">Tyrrheus, chief ranger to the Latian king:</l>
<l n="tr">Their sister Silvia cherish'd with her care</l>
<l n="tr">The little wanton, and did wreaths prepare</l>
<l n="tr">To hang his budding horns, with ribbons tied</l>
<l n="tr">His tender neck, and comb'd his silken hide,</l>
<l n="tr">And bathed his body. Patient of command</l>
<l n="tr">In time he grew, and, growing us'd to hand,</l>
<l n="tr">He waited at his master's board for food;</l>
<l n="tr">Then sought his salvage kindred in the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Where grazing all the day, at night he came</l>
<l n="tr">To his known lodgings, and his country dame.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This household beast, that us'd the woodland grounds,</l>
<l n="tr">Was view'd at first by the young hero's hounds,</l>
<l n="tr">As down the stream he swam, to seek retreat</l>
<l n="tr">In the cool waters, and to quench his heat.</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius young, and eager of his game,</l>
<l n="tr">Soon bent his bow, uncertain in his aim;</l>
<l n="tr">But the dire fiend the fatal arrow guides,</l>
<l n="tr">Which pierc'd his bowels thro' his panting sides.</l>
<l n="tr">The bleeding creature issues from the floods,</l>
<l n="tr">Possess'd with fear, and seeks his known abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">His old familiar hearth and household gods.</l>
<l n="tr">He falls; he fills the house with heavy groans,</l>
<l n="tr">Implores their pity, and his pain bemoans.</l>
<l n="tr">Young Silvia beats her breast, and cries aloud</l>
<l n="tr">For succor from the clownish neighborhood:</l>
<l n="tr">The churls assemble; for the fiend, who lay</l>
<l n="tr">In the close woody covert, urg'd their way.</l>
<l n="tr">One with a brand yet burning from the flame,</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd with a knotty club another came:</l>
<l n="tr">Whate'er they catch or find, without their care,</l>
<l n="tr">Their fury makes an instrument of war.</l>
<l n="tr">Tyrrheus, the foster father of the beast,</l>
<l n="tr">Then clench'd a hatchet in his horny fist,</l>
<l n="tr">But held his hand from the descending stroke,</l>
<l n="tr">And left his wedge within the cloven oak,</l>
<l n="tr">To whet their courage and their rage provoke.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="511" unit="card"/>And now the goddess, exercis'd in ill,</l>
<l n="tr">Who watch'd an hour to work her impious will,</l>
<l n="tr">Ascends the roof, and to her crooked horn,</l>
<l n="tr">Such as was then by Latian shepherds borne,</l>
<l n="tr">Adds all her breath: the rocks and woods around,</l>
<l n="tr">And mountains, tremble at  th'  infernal sound.</l>
<l n="tr">The sacred lake of Trivia from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">The Veline fountains, and sulphureous Nar,</l>
<l n="tr">Shake at the baleful blast, the signal of the war.</l>
<l n="tr">Young mothers wildly stare, with fear possess'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And strain their helpless infants to their breast.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The clowns, a boist'rous, rude, ungovern'd crew,</l>
<l n="tr">With furious haste to the loud summons flew.</l>
<l n="tr">The pow'rs of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, then issuing on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">With fresh recruits their youthful chief sustain:</l>
<l n="tr">Not theirs a raw and unexperienc'd train,</l>
<l n="tr">But a firm body of embattled men.</l>
<l n="tr">At first, while fortune favor'd neither side,</l>
<l n="tr">The fight with clubs and burning brands was tried;</l>
<l n="tr">But now, both parties reinforc'd, the fields</l>
<l n="tr">Are bright with flaming swords and brazen shields.</l>
<l n="tr">A shining harvest either host displays,</l>
<l n="tr">And shoots against the sun with equal rays.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, when a black-brow'd gust begins to rise,</l>
<l n="tr">White foam at first on the curl'd ocean fries;</l>
<l n="tr">Then roars the main, the billows mount the skies;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, by the fury of the storm full blown,</l>
<l n="tr">The muddy bottom o'er the clouds is thrown.</l>
<l n="tr">First Almon falls, old Tyrrheus' eldest care,</l>
<l n="tr">Pierc'd with an arrow from the distant war:</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd in his throat the flying weapon stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And stopp'd his breath, and drank his vital blood</l>
<l n="tr">Huge heaps of slain around the body rise:</l>
<l n="tr">Among the rest, the rich Galesus lies;</l>
<l n="tr">A good old man, while peace he preach'd in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the madness of  th'  unruly train:</l>
<l n="tr">Five herds, five bleating flocks, his pastures fill'd;</l>
<l n="tr">His lands a hundred yoke of oxen till'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="540" unit="card"/>Thus, while in equal scales their fortune stood</l>
<l n="tr">The Fury bath'd them in each other's blood;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, having fix'd the fight, exulting flies,</l>
<l n="tr">And bears fulfill'd her promise to the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">To Juno thus she speaks: “Behold! It is done,</l>
<l n="tr">The blood already drawn, the war begun;</l>
<l n="tr">The discord is complete; nor can they cease</l>
<l n="tr">The dire debate, nor you command the peace.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, since the Latian and the Trojan brood</l>
<l n="tr">Have tasted vengeance and the sweets of blood;</l>
<l n="tr">Speak, and my pow'r shall add this office more:</l>
<l n="tr">The neighb'ing nations of  th'  Ausonian shore</l>
<l n="tr">Shall hear the dreadful rumor, from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Of arm'd invasion, and embrace the war.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then Juno thus: “The grateful work is done,</l>
<l n="tr">The seeds of discord sow'd, the war begun;</l>
<l n="tr">Frauds, fears, and fury have possess'd the state,</l>
<l n="tr">And fix'd the causes of a lasting hate.</l>
<l n="tr">A bloody Hymen shall  th'  alliance join</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the Trojan and Ausonian line:</l>
<l n="tr">But thou with speed to night and hell repair;</l>
<l n="tr">For not the gods, nor angry Jove, will bear</l>
<l n="tr">Thy lawless wand'ring walks in upper air.</l>
<l n="tr">Leave what remains to me.” <placeName key="tgn,6005278" authname="tgn,6005278">Saturnia</placeName> said:</l>
<l n="tr">The sullen fiend her sounding wings display'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Unwilling left the light, and sought the nether shade.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In midst of <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, well known to fame,</l>
<l n="tr">There lies a lake (Amsanctus is the name)</l>
<l n="tr">Below the lofty mounts: on either side</l>
<l n="tr">Thick forests the forbidden entrance hide.</l>
<l n="tr">Full in the center of the sacred wood</l>
<l n="tr">An arm arises of the Stygian flood,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, breaking from beneath with bellowing sound,</l>
<l n="tr">Whirls the black waves and rattling stones around.</l>
<l n="tr">Here Pluto pants for breath from out his cell,</l>
<l n="tr">And opens wide the grinning jaws of hell.</l>
<l n="tr">To this infernal lake the Fury flies;</l>
<l n="tr">Here hides her hated head, and frees the lab'ring skies.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="572" unit="card"/>Saturnian Juno now, with double care,</l>
<l n="tr">Attends the fatal process of the war.</l>
<l n="tr">The clowns, return'd, from battle bear the slain,</l>
<l n="tr">Implore the gods, and to their king complain.</l>
<l n="tr">The corps of Almon and the rest are shown;</l>
<l n="tr">Shrieks, clamors, murmurs, fill the frighted town.</l>
<l n="tr">Ambitious Turnus in the press appears,</l>
<l n="tr">And, aggravating crimes, augments their fears;</l>
<l n="tr">Proclaims his private injuries aloud,</l>
<l n="tr">A solemn promise made, and disavow'd;</l>
<l n="tr">A foreign son is sought, and a mix'd mungril brood.</l>
<l n="tr">Then they, whose mothers, frantic with their fear,</l>
<l n="tr">In woods and wilds the flags of Bacchus bear,</l>
<l n="tr">And lead his dances with dishevel'd hair,</l>
<l n="tr">Increase the clamor, and the war demand,</l>
<l n="tr">(Such was Amata's interest in the land,)</l>
<l n="tr">Against the public sanctions of the peace,</l>
<l n="tr">Against all omens of their ill success.</l>
<l n="tr">With fates averse, the rout in arms resort,</l>
<l n="tr">To force their monarch, and insult the court.</l>
<l n="tr">But, like a rock unmov'd, a rock that braves</l>
<l n="tr">The raging tempest and the rising waves—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Propp'd on himself he stands; his solid sides</l>
<l n="tr">Wash off the seaweeds, and the sounding tides—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">So stood the pious prince, unmov'd, and long</l>
<l n="tr">Sustain'd the madness of the noisy throng.</l>
<l n="tr">But, when he found that Juno's pow'r prevail'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the methods of cool counsel fail'd,</l>
<l n="tr">He calls the gods to witness their offense,</l>
<l n="tr">Disclaims the war, asserts his innocence.</l>
<l n="tr">“Hurried by fate,” he cries, “and borne before</l>
<l n="tr">A furious wind, we have the faithful shore.</l>
<l n="tr">O more than madmen! you yourselves shall bear</l>
<l n="tr">The guilt of blood and sacrilegious war:</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, Turnus, shalt atone it by thy fate,</l>
<l n="tr">And pray to Heav'n for peace, but pray too late.</l>
<l n="tr">For me, my stormy voyage at an end,</l>
<l n="tr">I to the port of death securely tend.</l>
<l n="tr">The fun'ral pomp which to your kings you pay,</l>
<l n="tr">Is all I want, and all you take away.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said no more, but, in his walls confin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Shut out the woes which he too well divin'd</l>
<l n="tr">Nor with the rising storm would vainly strive,</l>
<l n="tr">But left the helm, and let the vessel drive.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="601" unit="card"/>A solemn custom was observ'd of old,</l>
<l n="tr">Which <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> held, and now the Romans hold,</l>
<l n="tr">Their standard when in fighting fields they rear</l>
<l n="tr">Against the fierce Hyrcanians, or declare</l>
<l n="tr">The Scythian, Indian, or Arabian war;</l>
<l n="tr">Or from the boasting Parthians would regain</l>
<l n="tr">Their eagles, lost in <placeName key="perseus,Carrhae" authname="perseus,Carrhae">Carrhae</placeName>'s bloody plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Two gates of steel (the name of Mars they bear,</l>
<l n="tr">And still are worship'd with religious fear)</l>
<l n="tr">Before his temple stand: the dire abode,</l>
<l n="tr">And the fear'd issues of the furious god,</l>
<l n="tr">Are fenc'd with brazen bolts; without the gates,</l>
<l n="tr">The wary guardian Janus doubly waits.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, when the sacred senate votes the wars,</l>
<l n="tr">The Roman consul their decree declares,</l>
<l n="tr">And in his robes the sounding gates unbars.</l>
<l n="tr">The youth in military shouts arise,</l>
<l n="tr">And the loud trumpets break the yielding skies.</l>
<l n="tr">These rites, of old by sov'reign princes us'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Were the king's office; but the king refus'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Deaf to their cries, nor would the gates unbar</l>
<l n="tr">Of sacred peace, or loose  th'  imprison'd war;</l>
<l n="tr">But hid his head, and, safe from loud alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">Abhorr'd the wicked ministry of arms.</l>
<l n="tr">Then heav'n's imperious queen shot down from high:</l>
<l n="tr">At her approach the brazen hinges fly;</l>
<l n="tr">The gates are forc'd, and ev'ry falling bar;</l>
<l n="tr">And, like a tempest, issues out the war.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The peaceful cities of  th'  Ausonian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Lull'd in their ease, and undisturb'd before,</l>
<l n="tr">Are all on fire; and some, with studious care,</l>
<l n="tr">Their restiff steeds in sandy plains prepare;</l>
<l n="tr">Some their soft limbs in painful marches try,</l>
<l n="tr">And war is all their wish, and arms the gen'ral cry.</l>
<l n="tr">Part scour the rusty shields with seam; and part</l>
<l n="tr">New grind the blunted ax, and point the dart:</l>
<l n="tr">With joy they view the waving ensigns fly,</l>
<l n="tr">And hear the trumpet's clangor pierce the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">Five cities forge their arms:  th'  Atinian pow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">Antemnae, <placeName key="perseus,Tibur" authname="perseus,Tibur">Tibur</placeName> with her lofty tow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Ardea" authname="perseus,Ardea">Ardea</placeName> the proud, the Crustumerian town:</l>
<l n="tr">All these of old were places of renown.</l>
<l n="tr">Some hammer helmets for the fighting field;</l>
<l n="tr">Some twine young sallows to support the shield;</l>
<l n="tr">The croslet some, and some the cuishes mold,</l>
<l n="tr">With silver plated, and with ductile gold.</l>
<l n="tr">The rustic honors of the scythe and share</l>
<l n="tr">Give place to swords and plumes, the pride of war.</l>
<l n="tr">Old fauchions are new temper'd in the fires;</l>
<l n="tr">The sounding trumpet ev'ry soul inspires.</l>
<l n="tr">The word is giv'n; with eager speed they lace</l>
<l n="tr">The shining headpiece, and the shield embrace.</l>
<l n="tr">The neighing steeds are to the chariot tied;</l>
<l n="tr">The trusty weapon sits on ev'ry side.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="641" unit="card"/>And now the mighty labor is begun,</l>
<l n="tr">Ye Muses, open all your Helicon.</l>
<l n="tr">Sing you the chiefs that sway'd  th'  Ausonian land,</l>
<l n="tr">Their arms, and armies under their command;</l>
<l n="tr">What warriors in our ancient clime were bred;</l>
<l n="tr">What soldiers follow'd, and what heroes led.</l>
<l n="tr">For well you know, and can record alone,</l>
<l n="tr">What fame to future times conveys but darkly down.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="647" unit="card"/>Mezentius first appear'd upon the plain:</l>
<l n="tr">Scorn sate upon his brows, and sour disdain,</l>
<l n="tr">Defying earth and heav'n. Etruria lost,</l>
<l n="tr">He brings to Turnus' aid his baffled host.</l>
<l n="tr">The charming Lausus, full of youthful fire,</l>
<l n="tr">Rode in the rank, and next his sullen sire;</l>
<l n="tr">To Turnus only second in the grace</l>
<l n="tr">Of manly mien, and features of the face.</l>
<l n="tr">A skilful horseman, and a huntsman bred,</l>
<l n="tr">With fates averse a thousand men he led:</l>
<l n="tr">His sire unworthy of so brave a son;</l>
<l n="tr">Himself well worthy of a happier throne.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="655" unit="card"/>Next Aventinus drives his chariot round</l>
<l n="tr">The Latian plains, with palms and laurels crown'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of his steeds, he smokes along the field;</l>
<l n="tr">His father's hydra fills his ample shield:</l>
<l n="tr">A hundred serpents hiss about the brims;</l>
<l n="tr">The son of Hercules he justly seems</l>
<l n="tr">By his broad shoulders and gigantic limbs;</l>
<l n="tr">Of heav'nly part, and part of earthly blood,</l>
<l n="tr">A mortal woman mixing with a god.</l>
<l n="tr">For strong Alcides, after he had slain</l>
<l n="tr">The triple Geryon, drove from conquer'd <placeName key="tgn,1000095" authname="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">His captive herds; and, thence in triumph led,</l>
<l n="tr">On Tuscan Tiber's flow'ry banks they fed.</l>
<l n="tr">Then on Mount Aventine the son of Jove</l>
<l n="tr">The priestess Rhea found, and forc'd to love.</l>
<l n="tr">For arms, his men long piles and jav'lins bore;</l>
<l n="tr">And poles with pointed steel their foes in battle gore.</l>
<l n="tr">Like <persName>Hercules</persName> himself his son appears,</l>
<l n="tr">In salvage pomp; a lion's hide he wears;</l>
<l n="tr">About his shoulders hangs the shaggy skin;</l>
<l n="tr">The teeth and gaping jaws severely grin.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, like the god his father, homely dress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">He strides into the hall, a horrid guest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="670" unit="card"/>Then two twin brothers from fair Tibur came,</l>
<l n="tr">(Which from their brother Tiburs took the name,)</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Coras and Catillus, void of fear:</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd Argive horse they led, and in the front appear.</l>
<l n="tr">Like cloud-born Centaurs, from the mountain's height</l>
<l n="tr">With rapid course descending to the fight;</l>
<l n="tr">They rush along; the rattling woods give way;</l>
<l n="tr">The branches bend before their sweepy sway.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="678" unit="card"/>Nor was Praeneste's founder wanting there,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom fame reports the son of Mulciber:</l>
<l n="tr">Found in the fire, and foster'd in the plains,</l>
<l n="tr">A shepherd and a king at once he reigns,</l>
<l n="tr">And leads to Turnus' aid his country swains.</l>
<l n="tr">His own Praeneste sends a chosen band,</l>
<l n="tr">With those who plow Saturnia's Gabine land;</l>
<l n="tr">Besides the succor which cold Anien yields,</l>
<l n="tr">The rocks of Hernicus, and dewy fields,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Anagnia" authname="perseus,Anagnia">Anagnia</placeName> fat, and Father Amasene—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">A num'rous rout, but all of naked men:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor arms they wear, nor swords and bucklers wield,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor drive the chariot thro' the dusty field,</l>
<l n="tr">But whirl from leathern slings huge balls of lead,</l>
<l n="tr">And spoils of yellow wolves adorn their head;</l>
<l n="tr">The left foot naked, when they march to fight,</l>
<l n="tr">But in a bull's raw hide they sheathe the right.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="691" unit="card"/>Messapus next, (great Neptune was his sire,)</l>
<l n="tr">Secure of steel, and fated from the fire,</l>
<l n="tr">In pomp appears, and with his ardor warms</l>
<l n="tr">A heartless train, unexercis'd in arms:</l>
<l n="tr">The just Faliscans he to battle brings,</l>
<l n="tr">And those who live where Lake Ciminia springs;</l>
<l n="tr">And where Feronia's grove and temple stands,</l>
<l n="tr">Who till Fescennian or Flavinian lands.</l>
<l n="tr">All these in order march, and marching sing</l>
<l n="tr">The warlike actions of their sea-born king;</l>
<l n="tr">Like a long team of snowy swans on high,</l>
<l n="tr">Which clap their wings, and cleave the liquid sky,</l>
<l n="tr">When, homeward from their wat'ry pastures borne,</l>
<l n="tr">They sing, and <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s lakes their notes return.</l>
<l n="tr">Not one who heard their music from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Would think these troops an army train'd to war,</l>
<l n="tr">But flocks of fowl, that, when the tempests roar,</l>
<l n="tr">With their hoarse gabbling seek the silent shore.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="706" unit="card"/>Then Clausus came, who led a num'rous band</l>
<l n="tr">Of troops embodied from the Sabine land,</l>
<l n="tr">And, in himself alone, an army brought.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was he, the noble Claudian race begot,</l>
<l n="tr">The Claudian race, ordain'd, in times to come,</l>
<l n="tr">To share the greatness of imperial <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">He led the Cures forth, of old renown,</l>
<l n="tr">Mutuscans from their olive-bearing town,</l>
<l n="tr">And all  th'  Eretian pow'rs; besides a band</l>
<l n="tr">That follow'd from Velinum's dewy land,</l>
<l n="tr">And Amiternian troops, of mighty fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And mountaineers, that from Severus came,</l>
<l n="tr">And from the craggy cliffs of Tetrica,</l>
<l n="tr">And those where yellow <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> takes his way,</l>
<l n="tr">And where Himella's wanton waters play.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,5002335" authname="tgn,5002335">Casperia</placeName> sends her arms, with those that lie</l>
<l n="tr">By Fabaris, and fruitful Foruli:</l>
<l n="tr">The warlike aids of <placeName>Horta</placeName> next appear,</l>
<l n="tr">And the cold Nursians come to close the rear,</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd with the natives born of Latine blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Allia washes with her fatal flood.</l>
<l n="tr">Not thicker billows beat the Libyan main,</l>
<l n="tr">When pale Orion sets in wintry rain;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thicker harvests on rich Hermus rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Or Lycian fields, when Phoebus burns the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">Than stand these troops: their bucklers ring around;</l>
<l n="tr">Their trampling turns the turf, and shakes the solid ground.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="723" unit="card"/>High in his chariot then Halesus came,</l>
<l n="tr">A foe by birth to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s unhappy name:</l>
<l n="tr">From Agamemnon born—to Turnus' aid</l>
<l n="tr">A thousand men the youthful hero led,</l>
<l n="tr">Who till the Massic soil, for wine renown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And fierce Auruncans from their hilly ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And those who live by Sidicinian shores,</l>
<l n="tr">And where with shoaly fords Vulturnus roars,</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Cales" authname="perseus,Cales">Cales</placeName>' and <placeName key="tgn,7007785" authname="tgn,7007785">Osca</placeName>'s old inhabitants,</l>
<l n="tr">And rough Saticulans, inur'd to wants:</l>
<l n="tr">Light demi-lances from afar they throw,</l>
<l n="tr">Fasten'd with leathern thongs, to gall the foe.</l>
<l n="tr">Short crooked swords in closer fight they wear;</l>
<l n="tr">And on their warding arm light bucklers bear.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="733" unit="card"/>Nor Oebalus, shalt thou be left unsung,</l>
<l n="tr">From nymph Semethis and old Telon sprung,</l>
<l n="tr">Who then in Teleboan Capri reign'd;</l>
<l n="tr">But that short isle  th'  ambitious youth disdain'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er <placeName key="tgn,7003005" authname="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName> stretch'd his ample sway,</l>
<l n="tr">Where swelling Sarnus seeks the Tyrrhene sea;</l>
<l n="tr">O'er Batulum, and where Abella sees,</l>
<l n="tr">From her high tow'rs, the harvest of her trees.</l>
<l n="tr">And these (as was the Teuton use of old)</l>
<l n="tr">Wield brazen swords, and brazen bucklers hold;</l>
<l n="tr">Sling weighty stones, when from afar they fight;</l>
<l n="tr">Their casques are cork, a covering thick and light.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="744" unit="card"/>Next these in rank, the warlike Ufens went,</l>
<l n="tr">And led the mountain troops that <placeName key="perseus,Nursia" authname="perseus,Nursia">Nursia</placeName> sent.</l>
<l n="tr">The rude Equicolae his rule obey'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Hunting their sport, and plund'ring was their trade.</l>
<l n="tr">In arms they plow'd, to battle still prepar'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Their soil was barren, and their hearts were hard.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="750" unit="card"/>Umbro the priest the proud Marrubians led,</l>
<l n="tr">By King Archippus sent to Turnus' aid,</l>
<l n="tr">And peaceful olives crown'd his hoary head.</l>
<l n="tr">His wand and holy words, the viper's rage,</l>
<l n="tr">And venom'd wounds of serpents could assuage.</l>
<l n="tr">He, when he pleas'd with powerful juice to steep</l>
<l n="tr">Their temples, shut their eyes in pleasing sleep.</l>
<l n="tr">But vain were Marsian herbs, and magic art,</l>
<l n="tr">To cure the wound giv'n by the Dardan dart:</l>
<l n="tr">Yet his untimely fate  th'  Angitian woods</l>
<l n="tr">In sighs remurmur'd to the <placeName key="tgn,1044713" authname="tgn,1044713">Fucine</placeName> floods.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="761" unit="card"/>The son of fam'd Hippolytus was there,</l>
<l n="tr">Fam'd as his sire, and, as his mother, fair;</l>
<l n="tr">Whom in Egerian groves <placeName key="perseus,Aricia" authname="perseus,Aricia">Aricia</placeName> bore,</l>
<l n="tr">And nurs'd his youth along the marshy shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Where great Diana's peaceful altars flame,</l>
<l n="tr">In fruitful fields; and Virbius was his name.</l>
<l n="tr">Hippolytus, as old records have said,</l>
<l n="tr">Was by his stepdam sought to share her bed;</l>
<l n="tr">But, when no female arts his mind could move,</l>
<l n="tr">She turn'd to furious hate her impious love.</l>
<l n="tr">Torn by wild horses on the sandy shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Another's crimes  th'  unhappy hunter bore,</l>
<l n="tr">Glutting his father's eyes with guiltless gore.</l>
<l n="tr">But chaste Diana, who his death deplor'd,</l>
<l n="tr">With Aesculapian herbs his life restor'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Jove, who saw from high, with just disdain,</l>
<l n="tr">The dead inspir'd with vital breath again,</l>
<l n="tr">Struck to the center, with his flaming dart,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unhappy founder of the godlike art.</l>
<l n="tr">But Trivia kept in secret shades alone</l>
<l n="tr">Her care, Hippolytus, to fate unknown;</l>
<l n="tr">And call'd him Virbius in  th'  Egerian grove,</l>
<l n="tr">Where then he liv'd obscure, but safe from Jove.</l>
<l n="tr">For this, from Trivia's temple and her wood</l>
<l n="tr">Are coursers driv'n, who shed their master's blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Affrighted by the monsters of the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">His son, the second Virbius, yet retain'd</l>
<l n="tr">His father's art, and warrior steeds he rein'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="783" unit="card"/>Amid the troops, and like the leading god,</l>
<l n="tr">High o'er the rest in arms the graceful Turnus rode:</l>
<l n="tr">A triple of plumes his crest adorn'd,</l>
<l n="tr">On which with belching flames Chimaera burn'd:</l>
<l n="tr">The more the kindled combat rises high'r,</l>
<l n="tr">The more with fury burns the blazing fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Fair Io grac'd his shield; but Io now</l>
<l n="tr">With horns exalted stands, and seems to low—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">A noble charge! Her keeper by her side,</l>
<l n="tr">To watch her walks, his hundred eyes applied;</l>
<l n="tr">And on the brims her sire, the wat'ry god,</l>
<l n="tr">Roll'd from a silver urn his crystal flood.</l>
<l n="tr">A cloud of foot succeeds, and fills the fields</l>
<l n="tr">With swords, and pointed spears, and clatt'ring shields;</l>
<l n="tr">Of Argives, and of old Sicanian bands,</l>
<l n="tr">And those who plow the rich Rutulian lands;</l>
<l n="tr">Auruncan youth, and those Sacrana yields,</l>
<l n="tr">And the proud Labicans, with painted shields,</l>
<l n="tr">And those who near Numician streams reside,</l>
<l n="tr">And those whom <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s holy forests hide,</l>
<l n="tr">Or Circe's hills from the main land divide;</l>
<l n="tr">Where Ufens glides along the lowly lands,</l>
<l n="tr">Or the black water of Pomptina stands.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="803" unit="card"/>Last, from the Volscians fair Camilla came,</l>
<l n="tr">And led her warlike troops, a warrior dame;</l>
<l n="tr">Unbred to spinning, in the loom unskill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">She chose the nobler Pallas of the field.</l>
<l n="tr">Mix'd with the first, the fierce virago fought,</l>
<l n="tr">Sustain'd the toils of arms, the danger sought,</l>
<l n="tr">Outstripp'd the winds in speed upon the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Flew o'er the fields, nor hurt the bearded grain:</l>
<l n="tr">She swept the seas, and, as she skimm'd along,</l>
<l n="tr">Her flying feet unbath'd on billows hung.</l>
<l n="tr">Men, boys, and women, stupid with surprise,</l>
<l n="tr">Where'er she passes, fix their wond'ring eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">Longing they look, and, gaping at the sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Devour her o'er and o'er with vast delight;</l>
<l n="tr">Her purple habit sits with such a grace</l>
<l n="tr">On her smooth shoulders, and so suits her face;</l>
<l n="tr">Her head with ringlets of her hair is crown'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a golden caul the curls are bound.</l>
<l n="tr">She shakes her myrtle jav'lin; and, behind,</l>
<l n="tr">Her Lycian quiver dances in the wind.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>