<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="8" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">When Turnus had assembled all his pow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">His standard planted on Laurentum's tow'rs;</l>
<l n="tr">When now the sprightly trumpet, from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Had giv'n the signal of approaching war,</l>
<l n="tr">Had rous'd the neighing steeds to scour the fields,</l>
<l n="tr">While the fierce riders clatter'd on their shields;</l>
<l n="tr">Trembling with rage, the Latian youth prepare</l>
<l n="tr">To join  th'  allies, and headlong rush to war.</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Ufens, and Messapus, led the crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">With bold Mezentius, who blasphem'd aloud.</l>
<l n="tr">These thro' the country took their wasteful course,</l>
<l n="tr">The fields to forage, and to gather force.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Venulus to Diomede they send,</l>
<l n="tr">To beg his aid Ausonia to defend,</l>
<l n="tr">Declare the common danger, and inform</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian leader of the growing storm:</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, landed on the Latian coast,</l>
<l n="tr">With banish'd gods, and with a baffled host,</l>
<l n="tr">Yet now aspir'd to conquest of the state,</l>
<l n="tr">And claim'd a title from the gods and fate;</l>
<l n="tr">What num'rous nations in his quarrel came,</l>
<l n="tr">And how they spread his formidable name.</l>
<l n="tr">What he design'd, what mischief might arise,</l>
<l n="tr">If fortune favor'd his first enterprise,</l>
<l n="tr">Was left for him to weigh, whose equal fears,</l>
<l n="tr">And common interest, was involv'd in theirs.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="18" unit="card"/>While Turnus and  th'  allies thus urge the war,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan, floating in a flood of care,</l>
<l n="tr">Beholds the tempest which his foes prepare.</l>
<l n="tr">This way and that he turns his anxious mind;</l>
<l n="tr">Thinks, and rejects the counsels he design'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Explores himself in vain, in ev'ry part,</l>
<l n="tr">And gives no rest to his distracted heart.</l>
<l n="tr">So, when the sun by day, or moon by night,</l>
<l n="tr">Strike on the polish'd brass their trembling light,</l>
<l n="tr">The glitt'ring species here and there divide,</l>
<l n="tr">And cast their dubious beams from side to side;</l>
<l n="tr">Now on the walls, now on the pavement play,</l>
<l n="tr">And to the ceiling flash the glaring day.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>'T was night; and weary nature lull'd asleep</l>
<l n="tr">The birds of air, and fishes of the deep,</l>
<l n="tr">And beasts, and mortal men. The Trojan chief</l>
<l n="tr">Was laid on <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s banks, oppress'd with grief,</l>
<l n="tr">And found in silent slumber late relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, thro' the shadows of the poplar wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Arose the father of the Roman flood;</l>
<l n="tr">An azure robe was o'er his body spread,</l>
<l n="tr">A wreath of shady reeds adorn'd his head:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus, manifest to sight, the god appear'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And with these pleasing words his sorrow cheer'd:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="36" unit="card"/>“Undoubted offspring of ethereal race,</l>
<l n="tr">O long expected in this promis'd place!</l>
<l n="tr">Who thro' the foes hast borne thy banish'd gods,</l>
<l n="tr">Restor'd them to their hearths, and old abodes;</l>
<l n="tr">This is thy happy home, the clime where fate</l>
<l n="tr">Ordains thee to restore the Trojan state.</l>
<l n="tr">Fear not! The war shall end in lasting peace,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the rage of haughty <persName>Juno</persName> cease.</l>
<l n="tr">And that this nightly vision may not seem</l>
<l n="tr">Th' effect of fancy, or an idle dream,</l>
<l n="tr">A sow beneath an oak shall lie along,</l>
<l n="tr">All white herself, and white her thirty young.</l>
<l n="tr">When thirty rolling years have run their race,</l>
<l n="tr">Thy son Ascanius, on this empty space,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall build a royal town, of lasting fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Which from this omen shall receive the name.</l>
<l n="tr">Time shall approve the truth. For what remains,</l>
<l n="tr">And how with sure success to crown thy pains,</l>
<l n="tr">With patience next attend. A banish'd band,</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n with <persName>Evander</persName> from  th' Arcadian land,</l>
<l n="tr">Have planted here, and plac'd on high their walls;</l>
<l n="tr">Their town the founder Pallanteum calls,</l>
<l n="tr">Deriv'd from <persName>Pallas</persName>, his great-grandsire's name:</l>
<l n="tr">But the fierce Latians old possession claim,</l>
<l n="tr">With war infesting the new colony.</l>
<l n="tr">These make thy friends, and on their aid rely.</l>
<l n="tr">To thy free passage I submit my streams.</l>
<l n="tr">Wake, son of <persName>Venus</persName>, from thy pleasing dreams;</l>
<l n="tr">And, when the setting stars are lost in day,</l>
<l n="tr">To <persName>Juno</persName>'s pow'r thy just devotion pay;</l>
<l n="tr">With sacrifice the wrathful queen appease:</l>
<l n="tr">Her pride at length shall fall, her fury cease.</l>
<l n="tr">When thou return'st victorious from the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Perform thy vows to me with grateful care.</l>
<l n="tr">The god am I, whose yellow water flows</l>
<l n="tr">Around these fields, and fattens as it goes:</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> my name; among the rolling floods</l>
<l n="tr">Renown'd on earth, esteem'd among the gods.</l>
<l n="tr">This is my certain seat. In times to come,</l>
<l n="tr">My waves shall wash the walls of mighty <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="66" unit="card"/>He said, and plung'd below. While yet he spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">His dream Aeneas and his sleep forsook.</l>
<l n="tr">He rose, and looking up, beheld the skies</l>
<l n="tr">With purple blushing, and the day arise.</l>
<l n="tr">Then water in his hollow palm he took</l>
<l n="tr">From <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s flood, and thus the pow'rs bespoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“Laurentian nymphs, by whom the streams are fed,</l>
<l n="tr">And Father Tiber, in thy sacred bed</l>
<l n="tr">Receive Aeneas, and from danger keep.</l>
<l n="tr">Whatever fount, whatever holy deep,</l>
<l n="tr">Conceals thy wat'ry stores; where'er they rise,</l>
<l n="tr">And, bubbling from below, salute the skies;</l>
<l n="tr">Thou, king of horned floods, whose plenteous urn</l>
<l n="tr">Suffices fatness to the fruitful corn,</l>
<l n="tr">For this thy kind compassion of our woes,</l>
<l n="tr">Shalt share my morning song and ev'ning vows.</l>
<l n="tr">But, O be present to thy people's aid,</l>
<l n="tr">And firm the gracious promise thou hast made!”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, two galleys from his stores,</l>
<l n="tr">With care he chooses, mans, and fits with oars.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="81" unit="card"/>Now on the shore the fatal swine is found.</l>
<l n="tr">Wondrous to tell!—She lay along the ground:</l>
<l n="tr">Her well-fed offspring at her udders hung;</l>
<l n="tr">She white herself, and white her thirty young.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas takes the mother and her brood,</l>
<l n="tr">And all on <persName>Juno</persName>'s altar are bestow'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The foll'wing night, and the succeeding day,</l>
<l n="tr">Propitious <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> smooth'd his wat'ry way:</l>
<l n="tr">He roll'd his river back, and pois'd he stood,</l>
<l n="tr">A gentle swelling, and a peaceful flood.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans mount their ships; they put from shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Borne on the waves, and scarcely dip an oar.</l>
<l n="tr">Shouts from the land give omen to their course,</l>
<l n="tr">And the pitch'd vessels glide with easy force.</l>
<l n="tr">The woods and waters wonder at the gleam</l>
<l n="tr">Of shields, and painted ships that stem the stream.</l>
<l n="tr">One summer's night and one whole day they pass</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt the greenwood shades, and cut the liquid glass.</l>
<l n="tr">The fiery sun had finish'd half his race,</l>
<l n="tr">Look'd back, and doubted in the middle space,</l>
<l n="tr">When they from far beheld the rising tow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">The tops of sheds, and shepherds' lowly bow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">Thin as they stood, which, then of homely clay,</l>
<l n="tr">Now rise in marble, from the Roman sway.</l>
<l n="tr">These cots (Evander's kingdom, mean and poor)</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan saw, and turn'd his ships to shore.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="102" unit="card"/>'T was on a solemn day:  th'  Arcadian states,</l>
<l n="tr">The king and prince, without the city gates,</l>
<l n="tr">Then paid their off'rings in a sacred grove</l>
<l n="tr">To <persName>Hercules</persName>, the warrior son of Jove.</l>
<l n="tr">Thick clouds of rolling smoke involve the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And fat of entrails on his altar fries.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But, when they saw the ships that stemm'd the flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And glitter'd thro' the covert of the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">They rose with fear, and left  th'  unfinish'd feast,</l>
<l n="tr">Till dauntless Pallas reassur'd the rest</l>
<l n="tr">To pay the rites. Himself without delay</l>
<l n="tr">A jav'lin seiz'd, and singly took his way;</l>
<l n="tr">Then gain'd a rising ground, and call'd from far:</l>
<l n="tr">“Resolve me, strangers, whence, and what you are;</l>
<l n="tr">Your bus'ness here; and bring you peace or war?”</l>
<l n="tr">High on the stern Aeneas his stand,</l>
<l n="tr">And held a branch of olive in his hand,</l>
<l n="tr">While thus he spoke: “The Phrygians' arms you see,</l>
<l n="tr">Expell'd from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, provok'd in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName></l>
<l n="tr">By Latian foes, with war unjustly made;</l>
<l n="tr">At first affianc'd, and at last betray'd.</l>
<l n="tr">This message bear: ‘The Trojans and their chief</l>
<l n="tr">Bring holy peace, and beg the king's relief.’</l>
<l n="tr">Struck with so great a name, and all on fire,</l>
<l n="tr">The youth replies: “Whatever you require,</l>
<l n="tr">Your fame exacts. Upon our shores descend.</l>
<l n="tr">A welcome guest, and, what you wish, a friend.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and, downward hasting to the strand,</l>
<l n="tr">Embrac'd the stranger prince, and join'd his hand.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Conducted to the grove,<milestone ed="p" n="126" unit="card"/>Aeneas broke</l>
<l n="tr">The silence first, and thus the king bespoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“Best of the Greeks, to whom, by fate's command,</l>
<l n="tr">I bear these peaceful branches in my hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Undaunted I approach you, tho' I know</l>
<l n="tr">Your birth is Grecian, and your land my foe;</l>
<l n="tr">From Atreus tho' your ancient lineage came,</l>
<l n="tr">And both the brother kings your kindred claim;</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, my self-conscious worth, your high renown,</l>
<l n="tr">Your virtue, thro' the neighb'ring nations blown,</l>
<l n="tr">Our fathers' mingled blood, Apollo's voice,</l>
<l n="tr">Have led me hither, less by need than choice.</l>
<l n="tr">Our founder Dardanus, as fame has sung,</l>
<l n="tr">And Greeks acknowledge, from Electra sprung:</l>
<l n="tr">Electra from the loins of Atlas came;</l>
<l n="tr">Atlas, whose head sustains the starry frame.</l>
<l n="tr">Your sire is Mercury, whom long before</l>
<l n="tr">On cold Cyllene's top fair Maia bore.</l>
<l n="tr">Maia the fair, on fame if we rely,</l>
<l n="tr">Was Atlas' daughter, who sustains the sky.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus from one common source our streams divide;</l>
<l n="tr">Ours is the Trojan, yours  th'  Areadian side.</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd by these hopes, I sent no news before,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor ask'd your leave, nor did your faith implore;</l>
<l n="tr">But come, without a pledge, my own ambassador.</l>
<l n="tr">The same Rutulians, who with arms pursue</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan race, are equal foes to you.</l>
<l n="tr">Our host expell'd, what farther force can stay</l>
<l n="tr">The victor troops from universal sway?</l>
<l n="tr">Then will they stretch their pow'r athwart the land,</l>
<l n="tr">And either sea from side to side command.</l>
<l n="tr">Receive our offer'd faith, and give us thine;</l>
<l n="tr">Ours is a gen'rous and experienc'd line:</l>
<l n="tr">We want not hearts nor bodies for the war;</l>
<l n="tr">In council cautious, and in fields we dare.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="152" unit="card"/>He said; and while spoke, with piercing eyes</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Evander</persName> view'd the man with vast surprise,</l>
<l n="tr">Pleas'd with his action, ravish'd with his face:</l>
<l n="tr">Then answer'd briefly, with a royal grace:</l>
<l n="tr">“O valiant leader of the Trojan line,</l>
<l n="tr">In whom the features of thy father shine,</l>
<l n="tr">How I recall Anchises! how I see</l>
<l n="tr">His motions, mien, and all my friend, in thee!</l>
<l n="tr">Long tho' it be, 't is fresh within my mind,</l>
<l n="tr">When Priam to his sister's court design'd</l>
<l n="tr">A welcome visit, with a friendly stay,</l>
<l n="tr">And thro'  th' Arcadian kingdom took his way.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, past a boy, the callow down began</l>
<l n="tr">To shade my chin, and call me first a man.</l>
<l n="tr">I saw the shining train with vast delight,</l>
<l n="tr">And Priam's goodly person pleas'd my sight:</l>
<l n="tr">But great Anchises, far above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">With awful wonder fir'd my youthful breast.</l>
<l n="tr">I long'd to join in friendship's holy bands</l>
<l n="tr">Our mutual hearts, and plight our mutual hands.</l>
<l n="tr">I first accosted him: I sued, I sought,</l>
<l n="tr">And, with a loving force, to Pheneus brought.</l>
<l n="tr">He gave me, when at length constrain'd to go,</l>
<l n="tr">A Lycian quiver and a Gnossian bow,</l>
<l n="tr">A vest embroider'd, glorious to behold,</l>
<l n="tr">And two rich bridles, with their bits of gold,</l>
<l n="tr">Which my son's coursers in obedience hold.</l>
<l n="tr">The league you ask, I offer, as your right;</l>
<l n="tr">And, when to-morrow's sun reveals the light,</l>
<l n="tr">With swift supplies you shall be sent away.</l>
<l n="tr">Now celebrate with us this solemn day,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose holy rites admit no long delay.</l>
<l n="tr">Honor our annual feast; and take your seat,</l>
<l n="tr">With friendly welcome, at a homely treat.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="175" unit="card"/>Thus having said, the bowls (remov'd for fear)</l>
<l n="tr">The youths replac'd, and soon restor'd the cheer.</l>
<l n="tr">On sods of turf he set the soldiers round:</l>
<l n="tr">A maple throne, rais'd higher from the ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Receiv'd the Trojan chief; and, o'er the bed,</l>
<l n="tr">A lion's shaggy hide for ornament they spread.</l>
<l n="tr">The loaves were serv'd in canisters; the wine</l>
<l n="tr">In bowls; the priest renew'd the rites divine:</l>
<l n="tr">Broil'd entrails are their food, and beef's continued chine.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="184" unit="card"/>But when the rage of hunger was repress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Thus spoke <persName>Evander</persName> to his royal guest:</l>
<l n="tr">“These rites, these altars, and this feast, O king,</l>
<l n="tr">From no vain fears or superstition spring,</l>
<l n="tr">Or blind devotion, or from blinder chance,</l>
<l n="tr">Or heady zeal, or brutal ignorance;</l>
<l n="tr">But, sav'd from danger, with a grateful sense,</l>
<l n="tr">The labors of a god we recompense.</l>
<l n="tr">See, from afar, yon rock that mates the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">About whose feet such heaps of rubbish lie;</l>
<l n="tr">Such indigested ruin; bleak and bare,</l>
<l n="tr">How desart now it stands, expos'd in air!</l>
<l n="tr">'T was once a robber's den, inclos'd around</l>
<l n="tr">With living stone, and deep beneath the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">The monster Cacus, more than half a beast,</l>
<l n="tr">This hold, impervious to the sun, possess'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The pavement ever foul with human gore;</l>
<l n="tr">Heads, and their mangled members, hung the door.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Vulcan</persName> this plague begot; and, like his sire,</l>
<l n="tr">Black clouds he belch'd, and flakes of livid fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Time, long expected, eas'd us of our load,</l>
<l n="tr">And brought the needful presence of a god.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' avenging force of <persName>Hercules</persName>, from <placeName key="tgn,1000095" authname="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Arriv'd in triumph, from Geryon slain:</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice liv'd the giant, and thrice liv'd in vain.</l>
<l n="tr">His prize, the lowing herds, Alcides drove</l>
<l n="tr">Near <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s bank, to graze the shady grove.</l>
<l n="tr">Allur'd with hope of plunder, and intent</l>
<l n="tr">By force to rob, by fraud to circumvent,</l>
<l n="tr">The brutal Cacus, as by chance they stray'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Four oxen thence, and four fair kine convey'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And, lest the printed footsteps might be seen,</l>
<l n="tr">He dragg'd 'em backwards to his rocky den.</l>
<l n="tr">The tracks averse a lying notice gave,</l>
<l n="tr">And led the searcher backward from the cave.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Meantime the herdsman hero shifts his place,</l>
<l n="tr">To find fresh pasture and untrodden grass.</l>
<l n="tr">The beasts, who miss'd their mates, fill'd all around</l>
<l n="tr">With bellowings, and the rocks restor'd the sound.</l>
<l n="tr">One heifer, who had heard her love complain,</l>
<l n="tr">Roar'd from the cave, and made the project vain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="219" unit="card"/>Alcides found the fraud; with rage he shook,</l>
<l n="tr">And toss'd about his head his knotted oak.</l>
<l n="tr">Swift as the winds, or Scythian arrows' flight,</l>
<l n="tr">He clomb, with eager haste,  th'  aerial height.</l>
<l n="tr">Then first we saw the monster mend his pace;</l>
<l n="tr">Fear his eyes, and paleness in his face,</l>
<l n="tr">Confess'd the god's approach. Trembling he springs,</l>
<l n="tr">As terror had increas'd his feet with wings;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor stay'd for stairs; but down the depth he threw</l>
<l n="tr">His body, on his back the door he drew</l>
<l n="tr">(The door, a rib of living rock; with pains</l>
<l n="tr">His father hew'd it out, and bound with iron chains):</l>
<l n="tr">He broke the heavy links, the mountain clos'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And bars and levers to his foe oppos'd.</l>
<l n="tr">The wretch had hardly made his dungeon fast;</l>
<l n="tr">The fierce avenger came with bounding haste;</l>
<l n="tr">Survey'd the mouth of the forbidden hold,</l>
<l n="tr">And here and there his raging eyes he roll'd.</l>
<l n="tr">He gnash'd his teeth; and thrice he compass'd round</l>
<l n="tr">With winged speed the circuit of the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice at the cavern's mouth he pull'd in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">And, panting, thrice desisted from his pain.</l>
<l n="tr">A pointed flinty rock, all bare and black,</l>
<l n="tr">Grew gibbous from behind the mountain's back;</l>
<l n="tr">Owls, ravens, all ill omens of the night,</l>
<l n="tr">Here built their nests, and hither wing'd their flight.</l>
<l n="tr">The leaning head hung threat'ning o'er the flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And nodded to the left. The hero stood</l>
<l n="tr">Adverse, with planted feet, and, from the right,</l>
<l n="tr">Tugg'd at the solid stone with all his might.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus heav'd, the fix'd foundations of the rock</l>
<l n="tr">Gave way; heav'n echo'd at the rattling shock.</l>
<l n="tr">Tumbling, it chok'd the flood: on either side</l>
<l n="tr">The banks leap backward, and the streams divide;</l>
<l n="tr">The sky shrunk upward with unusual dread,</l>
<l n="tr">And trembling <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> div'd beneath his bed.</l>
<l n="tr">The court of Cacus stands reveal'd to sight;</l>
<l n="tr">The cavern glares with new-admitted light.</l>
<l n="tr">So the pent vapors, with a rumbling sound,</l>
<l n="tr">Heave from below, and rend the hollow ground;</l>
<l n="tr">A sounding flaw succeeds; and, from on high,</l>
<l n="tr">The gods with hate beheld the nether sky:</l>
<l n="tr">The ghosts repine at violated night,</l>
<l n="tr">And curse  th'  invading sun, and sicken at the sight.</l>
<l n="tr">The graceless monster, caught in open day,</l>
<l n="tr">Inclos'd, and in despair to fly away,</l>
<l n="tr">Howls horrible from underneath, and fills</l>
<l n="tr">His hollow palace with unmanly yells.</l>
<l n="tr">The hero stands above, and from afar</l>
<l n="tr">Plies him with darts, and stones, and distant war.</l>
<l n="tr">He, from his nostrils huge mouth, expires</l>
<l n="tr">Black clouds of smoke, amidst his father's fires,</l>
<l n="tr">Gath'ring, with each repeated blast, the night,</l>
<l n="tr">To make uncertain aim, and erring sight.</l>
<l n="tr">The wrathful god then plunges from above,</l>
<l n="tr">And, where in thickest waves the sparkles drove,</l>
<l n="tr">There lights; and wades thro' fumes, and gropes his way,</l>
<l n="tr">Half sing'd, half stifled, till he grasps his prey.</l>
<l n="tr">The monster, spewing fruitless flames, he found;</l>
<l n="tr">He squeez'd his throat; he writh'd his neck around,</l>
<l n="tr">And in a knot his crippled members bound;</l>
<l n="tr">Then from their sockets tore his burning eyes:</l>
<l n="tr">Roll'd on a heap, the breathless robber lies.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="262" unit="card"/>The doors, unbarr'd, receive the rushing day,</l>
<l n="tr">And thoro' lights disclose the ravish'd prey.</l>
<l n="tr">The bulls, redeem'd, breathe open air again.</l>
<l n="tr">Next, by the feet, they drag him from his den.</l>
<l n="tr">The wond'ring neighborhood, with glad surprise,</l>
<l n="tr">Behold his shagged breast, his giant size,</l>
<l n="tr">His mouth that flames no more, and his extinguish'd eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">From that auspicious day, with rites divine,</l>
<l n="tr">We worship at the hero's holy shrine.</l>
<l n="tr">Potitius first ordain'd these annual vows:</l>
<l n="tr">As priests, were added the Pinarian house,</l>
<l n="tr">Who rais'd this altar in the sacred shade,</l>
<l n="tr">Where honors, ever due, for ever shall be paid.</l>
<l n="tr">For these deserts, and this high virtue shown,</l>
<l n="tr">Ye warlike youths, your heads with garlands crown:</l>
<l n="tr">Fill high the goblets with a sparkling flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And with deep draughts invoke our common god.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This said, a double wreath Evander twin'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And poplars black and white his temples bind.</l>
<l n="tr">Then brims his ample bowl. With like design</l>
<l n="tr">The rest invoke the gods, with sprinkled wine.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="280" unit="card"/>Meantime the sun descended from the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">And the bright evening star began to rise.</l>
<l n="tr">And now the priests, Potitius at their head,</l>
<l n="tr">In skins of beasts involv'd, the long procession led;</l>
<l n="tr">Held high the flaming tapers in their hands,</l>
<l n="tr">As custom had prescrib'd their holy bands;</l>
<l n="tr">Then with a second course the tables load,</l>
<l n="tr">And with full chargers offer to the god.</l>
<l n="tr">The Salii sing, and cense his altars round</l>
<l n="tr">With Saban smoke, their heads with poplar bound—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">One choir of old, another of the young,</l>
<l n="tr">To dance, and bear the burthen of the song.</l>
<l n="tr">The lay records the labors, and the praise,</l>
<l n="tr">And all  th'  immortal acts of Hercules:</l>
<l n="tr">First, how the mighty babe, when swath'd in bands,</l>
<l n="tr">The serpents strangled with his infant hands;</l>
<l n="tr">Then, as in years and matchless force he grew,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Oechalian walls, and Trojan, overthrew.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, a thousand hazards they relate,</l>
<l n="tr">Procur'd by Juno's and Eurystheus' hate:</l>
<l n="tr">“Thy hands, unconquer'd hero, could subdue</l>
<l n="tr">The cloud-born Centaurs, and the monster crew:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thy resistless arm the bull withstood,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor he, the roaring terror of the wood.</l>
<l n="tr">The triple porter of the Stygian seat,</l>
<l n="tr">With lolling tongue, lay fawning at thy feet,</l>
<l n="tr">And, seiz'd with fear, forgot his mangled meat.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' infernal waters trembled at thy sight;</l>
<l n="tr">Thee, god, no face of danger could affright;</l>
<l n="tr">Not huge Typhoeus, nor  th'  unnumber'd snake,</l>
<l n="tr">Increas'd with hissing heads, in <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>'s lake.</l>
<l n="tr">Hail, Jove's undoubted son! an added grace</l>
<l n="tr">To heav'n and the great author of thy race!</l>
<l n="tr">Receive the grateful off'rings which we pay,</l>
<l n="tr">And smile propitious on thy solemn day!”</l>
<l n="tr">In numbers thus they sung; above the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">The den and death of Cacus crown the feast.</l>
<l n="tr">The woods to hollow vales convey the sound,</l>
<l n="tr">The vales to hills, and hills the notes rebound.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="306" unit="card"/>The rites perform'd, the cheerful train retire.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Betwixt young Pallas and his aged sire,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan pass'd, the city to survey,</l>
<l n="tr">And pleasing talk beguil'd the tedious way.</l>
<l n="tr">The stranger cast around his curious eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">New objects viewing still, with new surprise;</l>
<l n="tr">With greedy joy enquires of various things,</l>
<l n="tr">And acts and monuments of ancient kings.</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus the founder of the Roman tow'rs:</l>
<l n="tr">“These woods were first the seat of sylvan pow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">Of Nymphs and Fauns, and salvage men, who took</l>
<l n="tr">Their birth from trunks of trees and stubborn oak.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor laws they knew, nor manners, nor the care</l>
<l n="tr">Of lab'ring oxen, or the shining share,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor arts of gain, nor what they gain'd to spare.</l>
<l n="tr">Their exercise the chase; the running flood</l>
<l n="tr">Supplied their thirst, the trees supplied their food.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Saturn came, who fled the pow'r of Jove,</l>
<l n="tr">Robb'd of his realms, and banish'd from above.</l>
<l n="tr">The men, dispers'd on hills, to towns he brought,</l>
<l n="tr">And laws ordain'd, and civil customs taught,</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="tgn,7003080" authname="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName> call'd the land where safe he lay</l>
<l n="tr">From his unduteous son, and his usurping sway.</l>
<l n="tr">With his mild empire, peace and plenty came;</l>
<l n="tr">And hence the golden times deriv'd their name.</l>
<l n="tr">A more degenerate and discolor'd age</l>
<l n="tr">Succeeded this, with avarice and rage.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Ausonians then, and bold Sicanians came;</l>
<l n="tr">And Saturn's empire often chang'd the name.</l>
<l n="tr">Then kings, gigantic Tybris, and the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">With arbitrary sway the land oppress'd:</l>
<l n="tr">For <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s flood was <placeName key="tgn,1121086" authname="tgn,1121086">Albula</placeName> before,</l>
<l n="tr">Till, from the tyrant's fate, his name it bore.</l>
<l n="tr">I last arriv'd, driv'n from my native home</l>
<l n="tr">By fortune's pow'r, and fate's resistless doom.</l>
<l n="tr">Long toss'd on seas, I sought this happy land,</l>
<l n="tr">Warn'd by my mother nymph, and call'd by Heav'n's command.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="337" unit="card"/>Thus, walking on, he spoke, and shew'd the gate,</l>
<l n="tr">Since call'd Carmental by the Roman state;</l>
<l n="tr">Where stood an altar, sacred to the name</l>
<l n="tr">Of old Carmenta, the prophetic dame,</l>
<l n="tr">Who to her son foretold  th'  Aenean race,</l>
<l n="tr">Sublime in fame, and <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>'s imperial place:</l>
<l n="tr">Then shews the forest, which, in after times,</l>
<l n="tr">Fierce Romulus for perpetrated crimes</l>
<l n="tr">A sacred refuge made; with this, the shrine</l>
<l n="tr">Where Pan below the rock had rites divine:</l>
<l n="tr">Then tells of Argus' death, his murder'd guest,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose grave and tomb his innocence attest.</l>
<l n="tr">Thence, to the steep Tarpeian rock he leads;</l>
<l n="tr">Now roof'd with gold, then thatch'd with homely reeds.</l>
<l n="tr">A reverent fear (such superstition reigns</l>
<l n="tr">Among the rude) ev'n then possess'd the swains.</l>
<l n="tr">Some god, they knew—what god, they could not tell—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Did there amidst the sacred horror dwell.</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Arcadians thought him Jove; and said they saw</l>
<l n="tr">The mighty Thund'rer with majestic awe,</l>
<l n="tr">Who took his shield, and dealt his bolts around,</l>
<l n="tr">And scatter'd tempests on the teeming ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Then saw two heaps of ruins, (once they stood</l>
<l n="tr">Two stately towns, on either side the flood,)</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,6005278" authname="tgn,6005278">Saturnia</placeName>'s and Janicula's remains;</l>
<l n="tr">And either place the founder's name retains.</l>
<l n="tr">Discoursing thus together, they resort</l>
<l n="tr">Where poor Evander kept his country court.</l>
<l n="tr">They view'd the ground of <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>'s litigious hall;</l>
<l n="tr">(Once oxen low'd, where now the lawyers bawl;)</l>
<l n="tr">Then, stooping, thro' the narrow gate they press'd,</l>
<l n="tr">When thus the king bespoke his Trojan guest:</l>
<l n="tr">“Mean as it is, this palace, and this door,</l>
<l n="tr">Receiv'd Alcides, then a conqueror.</l>
<l n="tr">Dare to be poor; accept our homely food,</l>
<l n="tr">Which feasted him, and emulate a god.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then underneath a lowly roof he led</l>
<l n="tr">The weary prince, and laid him on a bed;</l>
<l n="tr">The stuffing leaves, with hides of bears o'erspread.</l>
<l n="tr">Now Night had shed her silver dews around,</l>
<l n="tr">And with her sable wings embrac'd the ground,</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="370" unit="card"/>When love's fair goddess, anxious for her son,</l>
<l n="tr">(New tumults rising, and new wars begun,)</l>
<l n="tr">Couch'd with her husband in his golden bed,</l>
<l n="tr">With these alluring words invokes his aid;</l>
<l n="tr">And, that her pleasing speech his mind may move,</l>
<l n="tr">Inspires each accent with the charms of love:</l>
<l n="tr">“While cruel fate conspir'd with Grecian pow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">To level with the ground the Trojan tow'rs,</l>
<l n="tr">I ask'd not aid  th'  unhappy to restore,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did the succor of thy skill implore;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor urg'd the labors of my lord in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">A sinking empire longer to sustain,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho'much I ow'd to Priam's house, and more</l>
<l n="tr">The dangers of Aeneas did deplore.</l>
<l n="tr">But now, by Jove's command, and fate's decree,</l>
<l n="tr">His race is doom'd to reign in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>:</l>
<l n="tr">With humble suit I beg thy needful art,</l>
<l n="tr">O still propitious pow'r, that rules my heart!</l>
<l n="tr">A mother kneels a suppliant for her son.</l>
<l n="tr">By Thetis and Aurora thou wert won</l>
<l n="tr">To forge impenetrable shields, and grace</l>
<l n="tr">With fated arms a less illustrious race.</l>
<l n="tr">Behold, what haughty nations are combin'd</l>
<l n="tr">Against the relics of the Phrygian kind,</l>
<l n="tr">With fire and sword my people to destroy,</l>
<l n="tr">And conquer Venus twice, in conqu'ring <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.”</l>
<l n="tr">She said; and straight her arms, of snowy hue,</l>
<l n="tr">About her unresolving husband threw.</l>
<l n="tr">Her soft embraces soon infuse desire;</l>
<l n="tr">His bones and marrow sudden warmth inspire;</l>
<l n="tr">And all the godhead feels the wonted fire.</l>
<l n="tr">Not half so swift the rattling thunder flies,</l>
<l n="tr">Or forky lightnings flash along the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">The goddess, proud of her successful wiles,</l>
<l n="tr">And conscious of her form, in secret smiles.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus the pow'r, obnoxious to her charms,</l>
<l n="tr">Panting, and half dissolving in her arms:</l>
<l n="tr">“Why seek you reasons for a cause so just,</l>
<l n="tr">Or your own beauties or my love distrust?</l>
<l n="tr">Long since, had you requir'd my helpful hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' artificer and art you might command,</l>
<l n="tr">To labor arms for <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>: nor Jove, nor fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Confin'd their empire to so short a date.</l>
<l n="tr">And, if you now desire new wars to wage,</l>
<l n="tr">My skill I promise, and my pains engage.</l>
<l n="tr">Whatever melting metals can conspire,</l>
<l n="tr">Or breathing bellows, or the forming fire,</l>
<l n="tr">Is freely yours: your anxious fears remove,</l>
<l n="tr">And think no task is difficult to love.”</l>
<l n="tr">Trembling he spoke; and, eager of her charms,</l>
<l n="tr">He snatch'd the willing goddess to his arms;</l>
<l n="tr">Till in her lap infus'd, he lay possess'd</l>
<l n="tr">Of full desire, and sunk to pleasing rest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="407" unit="card"/>Now when the Night her middle race had rode,</l>
<l n="tr">And his first slumber had refresh'd the god—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">The time when early housewives leave the bed;</l>
<l n="tr">When living embers on the hearth they spread,</l>
<l n="tr">Supply the lamp, and call the maids to rise—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">With yawning mouths, and with half-open'd eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">They ply the distaff by the winking light,</l>
<l n="tr">And to their daily labor add the night:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus frugally they earn their children's bread,</l>
<l n="tr">And uncorrupted keep the nuptial bed—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Not less concern'd, nor at a later hour,</l>
<l n="tr">Rose from his downy couch the forging pow'r.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Sacred to <persName>Vulcan</persName>'s name, an isle there lay,</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicilia</placeName>'s coasts and Lipare,</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd high on smoking rocks; and, deep below,</l>
<l n="tr">In hollow caves the fires of <placeName key="tgn,7003867" authname="tgn,7003867">Aetna</placeName> glow.</l>
<l n="tr">The Cyclops here their heavy hammers deal;</l>
<l n="tr">Loud strokes, and hissings of tormented steel,</l>
<l n="tr">Are heard around; the boiling waters roar,</l>
<l n="tr">And smoky flames thro' fuming tunnels soar.</l>
<l n="tr">Hither the Father of the Fire, by night,</l>
<l n="tr">Thro' the brown air precipitates his flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="424" unit="card"/>On their eternal anvils here he found</l>
<l n="tr">The brethren beating, and the blows go round.</l>
<l n="tr">A load of pointless thunder now there lies</l>
<l n="tr">Before their hands, to ripen for the skies:</l>
<l n="tr">These darts, for angry Jove, they daily cast;</l>
<l n="tr">Consum'd on mortals with prodigious waste.</l>
<l n="tr">Three rays of writhen rain, of fire three more,</l>
<l n="tr">Of winged southern winds and cloudy store</l>
<l n="tr">As many parts, the dreadful mixture frame;</l>
<l n="tr">And fears are added, and avenging flame.</l>
<l n="tr">Inferior ministers, for Mars, repair</l>
<l n="tr">His broken axletrees and blunted war,</l>
<l n="tr">And send him forth again with furbish'd arms,</l>
<l n="tr">To wake the lazy war with trumpets' loud alarms.</l>
<l n="tr">The rest refresh the scaly snakes that fold</l>
<l n="tr">The shield of <persName>Pallas</persName>, and renew their gold.</l>
<l n="tr">Full on the crest the Gorgon's head they place,</l>
<l n="tr">With eyes that roll in death, and with distorted face.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“My sons,” said <persName>Vulcan</persName>, “set your tasks aside;</l>
<l n="tr">Your strength and master-skill must now be tried.</l>
<l n="tr">Arms for a hero forge; arms that require</l>
<l n="tr">Your force, your speed, and all your forming fire.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said. They set their former work aside,</l>
<l n="tr">And their new toils with eager haste divide.</l>
<l n="tr">A flood of molten silver, brass, and gold,</l>
<l n="tr">And deadly steel, in the large furnace roll'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Of this, their artful hands a shield prepare,</l>
<l n="tr">Alone sufficient to sustain the war.</l>
<l n="tr">Sev'n orbs within a spacious round they close:</l>
<l n="tr">One stirs the fire, and one the bellows blows.</l>
<l n="tr">The hissing steel is in the smithy drown'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The grot with beaten anvils groans around.</l>
<l n="tr">By turns their arms advance, in equal time;</l>
<l n="tr">By turns their hands descend, and hammers chime.</l>
<l n="tr">They turn the glowing mass with crooked tongs;</l>
<l n="tr">The fiery work proceeds, with rustic songs.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="454" unit="card"/>While, at the Lemnian god's command, they urge</l>
<l n="tr">Their labors thus, and ply  th'  Aeolian forge,</l>
<l n="tr">The cheerful morn salutes <persName>Evander</persName>'s eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And songs of chirping birds invite to rise.</l>
<l n="tr">He leaves his lowly bed: his buskins meet</l>
<l n="tr">Above his ankles; sandals sheathe his feet:</l>
<l n="tr">He sets his trusty sword upon his side,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er his shoulder throws a panther's hide.</l>
<l n="tr">Two menial dogs before their master press'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus clad, and guarded thus, he seeks his kingly guest.</l>
<l n="tr">Mindful of promis'd aid, he mends his pace,</l>
<l n="tr">But meets Aeneas in the middle space.</l>
<l n="tr">Young <persName>Pallas</persName> did his father's steps attend,</l>
<l n="tr">And true <persName>Achates</persName> waited on his friend.</l>
<l n="tr">They join their hands; a secret seat they choose;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Arcadian first their former talk renews:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="470" unit="card"/>“Undaunted prince, I never can believe</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojan empire lost, while you survive.</l>
<l n="tr">Command  th'  assistance of a faithful friend;</l>
<l n="tr">But feeble are the succors I can send.</l>
<l n="tr">Our narrow kingdom here the <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> bounds;</l>
<l n="tr">That other side the Latian state surrounds,</l>
<l n="tr">Insults our walls, and wastes our fruitful grounds.</l>
<l n="tr">But mighty nations I prepare, to join</l>
<l n="tr">Their arms with yours, and aid your just design.</l>
<l n="tr">You come, as by your better genius sent,</l>
<l n="tr">And fortune seems to favor your intent.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from hence there stands a hilly town,</l>
<l n="tr">Of ancient building, and of high renown,</l>
<l n="tr">Torn from the Tuscans by the Lydian race,</l>
<l n="tr">Who gave the name of Caere to the place,</l>
<l n="tr">Once Agyllina call'd. It flourish'd long,</l>
<l n="tr">In pride of wealth and warlike people strong,</l>
<l n="tr">Till curs'd Mezentius, in a fatal hour,</l>
<l n="tr">Assum'd the crown, with arbitrary pow'r.</l>
<l n="tr">What words can paint those execrable times,</l>
<l n="tr">The subjects' suff'rings, and the tyrant's crimes!</l>
<l n="tr">That blood, those murthers, O ye gods, replace</l>
<l n="tr">On his own head, and on his impious race!</l>
<l n="tr">The living and the dead at his command</l>
<l n="tr">Were coupled, face to face, and hand to hand,</l>
<l n="tr">Till, chok'd with stench, in loath'd embraces tied,</l>
<l n="tr">The ling'ring wretches pin'd away and died.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus plung'd in ills, and meditating more—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">The people's patience, tir'd, no longer bore</l>
<l n="tr">The raging monster; but with arms beset</l>
<l n="tr">His house, and vengeance and destruction threat.</l>
<l n="tr">They fire his palace: while the flame ascends,</l>
<l n="tr">They force his guards, and execute his friends.</l>
<l n="tr">He cleaves the crowd, and, favor'd by the night,</l>
<l n="tr">To Turnus' friendly court directs his flight.</l>
<l n="tr">By just revenge the Tuscans set on fire,</l>
<l n="tr">With arms, their king to punishment require:</l>
<l n="tr">Their num'rous troops, now muster'd on the strand,</l>
<l n="tr">My counsel shall submit to your command.</l>
<l n="tr">Their navy swarms upon the coasts; they cry</l>
<l n="tr">To hoist their anchors, but the gods deny.</l>
<l n="tr">An ancient augur, skill'd in future fate,</l>
<l n="tr">With these foreboding words restrains their hate:</l>
<l n="tr">‘Ye brave in arms, ye Lydian blood, the flow'r</l>
<l n="tr">Of Tuscan youth, and choice of all their pow'r,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom just revenge against Mezentius arms,</l>
<l n="tr">To seek your tyrant's death by lawful arms;</l>
<l n="tr">Know this: no native of our land may lead</l>
<l n="tr">This pow'rful people; seek a foreign head.’</l>
<l n="tr">Aw'd with these words, in camps they still abide,</l>
<l n="tr">And wait with longing looks their promis'd guide.</l>
<l n="tr">Tarchon, the Tuscan chief, to me has sent</l>
<l n="tr">Their crown, and ev'ry regal ornament:</l>
<l n="tr">The people join their own with his desire;</l>
<l n="tr">And all my conduct, as their king, require.</l>
<l n="tr">But the chill blood that creeps within my veins,</l>
<l n="tr">And age, and listless limbs unfit for pains,</l>
<l n="tr">And a soul conscious of its own decay,</l>
<l n="tr">Have forc'd me to refuse imperial sway.</l>
<l n="tr">My <persName>Pallas</persName> were more fit to mount the throne,</l>
<l n="tr">And should, but he's a Sabine mother's son,</l>
<l n="tr">And half a native; but, in you, combine</l>
<l n="tr">A manly vigor, and a foreign line.</l>
<l n="tr">Where Fate and smiling Fortune shew the way,</l>
<l n="tr">Pursue the ready path to sov'reign sway.</l>
<l n="tr">The staff of my declining days, my son,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall make your good or ill success his own;</l>
<l n="tr">In fighting fields from you shall learn to dare,</l>
<l n="tr">And serve the hard apprenticeship of war;</l>
<l n="tr">Your matchless courage and your conduct view,</l>
<l n="tr">And early shall begin T' admire and copy you.</l>
<l n="tr">Besides, two hundred horse he shall command;</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' few, a warlike and well-chosen band.</l>
<l n="tr">These in my name are listed; and my son</l>
<l n="tr">As many more has added in his own.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="520" unit="card"/>Scarce had he said; <persName>Achates</persName> and his guest,</l>
<l n="tr">With downcast eyes, their silent grief express'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Who, short of succors, and in deep despair,</l>
<l n="tr">Shook at the dismal prospect of the war.</l>
<l n="tr">But his bright mother, from a breaking cloud,</l>
<l n="tr">To cheer her issue, thunder'd thrice aloud;</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice forky lightning flash'd along the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">And Tyrrhene trumpets thrice were heard on high.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, gazing up, repeated peals they hear;</l>
<l n="tr">And, in a heav'n serene, refulgent arms appear:</l>
<l n="tr">Redd'ning the skies, and glitt'ring all around,</l>
<l n="tr">The temper'd metals clash, and yield a silver sound.</l>
<l n="tr">The rest stood trembling, struck with awe divine;</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas only, conscious to the sign,</l>
<l n="tr">Presag'd  th'  event, and joyful view'd, above,</l>
<l n="tr">Th' accomplish'd promise of the Queen of Love.</l>
<l n="tr">Then, to  th' Arcadian king: “This prodigy</l>
<l n="tr">(Dismiss your fear) belongs alone to me.</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'n calls me to the war:  th'  expected sign</l>
<l n="tr">Is giv'n of promis'd aid, and arms divine.</l>
<l n="tr">My goddess mother, whose indulgent care</l>
<l n="tr">Foresaw the dangers of the growing war,</l>
<l n="tr">This omen gave, when bright Vulcanian arms,</l>
<l n="tr">Fated from force of steel by Stygian charms,</l>
<l n="tr">Suspended, shone on high: she then foreshow'd</l>
<l n="tr">Approaching fights, and fields to float in blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Turnus shall dearly pay for faith forsworn;</l>
<l n="tr">And corps, and swords, and shields, on <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> borne,</l>
<l n="tr">Shall choke his flood: now sound the loud alarms;</l>
<l n="tr">And, Latian troops, prepare your perjur'd arms.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="541" unit="card"/>He said, and, rising from his homely throne,</l>
<l n="tr">The solemn rites of <persName>Hercules</persName> begun,</l>
<l n="tr">And on his altars wak'd the sleeping fires;</l>
<l n="tr">Then cheerful to his household gods retires;</l>
<l n="tr">There offers chosen sheep.  th' Arcadian king</l>
<l n="tr">And Trojan youth the same oblations bring.</l>
<l n="tr">Next, of his men and ships he makes review;</l>
<l n="tr">Draws out the best and ablest of the crew.</l>
<l n="tr">Down with the falling stream the refuse run,</l>
<l n="tr">To raise with joyful news his drooping son.</l>
<l n="tr">Steeds are prepar'd to mount the Trojan band,</l>
<l n="tr">Who wait their leader to the Tyrrhene land.</l>
<l n="tr">A sprightly courser, fairer than the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">The king himself presents his royal guest:</l>
<l n="tr">A lion's hide his back and limbs infold,</l>
<l n="tr">Precious with studded work, and paws of gold.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="554" unit="card"/>Fame thro' the little city spreads aloud</l>
<l n="tr">Th' intended march, amid the fearful crowd:</l>
<l n="tr">The matrons beat their breasts, dissolve in tears,</l>
<l n="tr">And double their devotion in their fears.</l>
<l n="tr">The war at hand appears with more affright,</l>
<l n="tr">And rises ev'ry moment to the sight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then old <persName>Evander</persName>, with a close embrace,</l>
<l n="tr">Strain'd his departing friend; and tears o'erflow his face.</l>
<l n="tr">“Would Heav'n,” said he, “my strength and youth recall,</l>
<l n="tr">Such as I was beneath Praeneste's wall;</l>
<l n="tr">Then when I made the foremost foes retire,</l>
<l n="tr">And set whole heaps of conquer'd shields on fire;</l>
<l n="tr">When Herilus in single fight I slew,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom with three lives Feronia did endue;</l>
<l n="tr">And thrice I sent him to the Stygian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Till the last ebbing soul return'd no more—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Such if I stood renew'd, not these alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor death, should rend me from my <persName>Pallas</persName>' arms;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor proud Mezentius, thus unpunish'd, boast</l>
<l n="tr">His rapes and murthers on the Tuscan coast.</l>
<l n="tr">Ye gods, and mighty Jove, in pity bring</l>
<l n="tr">Relief, and hear a father and a king!</l>
<l n="tr">If fate and you reserve these eyes, to see</l>
<l n="tr">My son return with peace and victory;</l>
<l n="tr">If the lov'd boy shall bless his father's sight;</l>
<l n="tr">If we shall meet again with more delight;</l>
<l n="tr">Then draw my life in length; let me sustain,</l>
<l n="tr">In hopes of his embrace, the worst of pain.</l>
<l n="tr">But if your hard decrees—which, O! I dread—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Have doom'd to death his undeserving head;</l>
<l n="tr">This, O this very moment, let me die!</l>
<l n="tr">While hopes and fears in equal balance lie;</l>
<l n="tr">While, yet possess'd of all his youthful charms,</l>
<l n="tr">I strain him close within these aged arms;</l>
<l n="tr">Before that fatal news my soul shall wound!”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and, swooning, sunk upon the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">His servants bore him off, and softly laid</l>
<l n="tr">His languish'd limbs upon his homely bed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="585" unit="card"/>The horsemen march; the gates are open'd wide;</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas at their head, <persName>Achates</persName> by his side.</l>
<l n="tr">Next these, the Trojan leaders rode along;</l>
<l n="tr">Last follows in the rear  th' Arcadian throng.</l>
<l n="tr">Young <persName>Pallas</persName> shone conspicuous o'er the rest;</l>
<l n="tr">Gilded his arms, embroider'd was his vest.</l>
<l n="tr">So, from the seas, exerts his radiant head</l>
<l n="tr">The star by whom the lights of heav'n are led;</l>
<l n="tr">Shakes from his rosy locks the pearly dews,</l>
<l n="tr">Dispels the darkness, and the day renews.</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling wives the walls and turrets crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">And follow, with their eyes, the dusty cloud,</l>
<l n="tr">Which winds disperse by fits, and shew from far</l>
<l n="tr">The blaze of arms, and shields, and shining war.</l>
<l n="tr">The troops, drawn up in beautiful array,</l>
<l n="tr">O'er heathy plains pursue the ready way.</l>
<l n="tr">Repeated peals of shouts are heard around;</l>
<l n="tr">The neighing coursers answer to the sound,</l>
<l n="tr">And shake with horny hoofs the solid ground.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A greenwood shade, for long religion known,</l>
<l n="tr">Stands by the streams that wash the Tuscan town,</l>
<l n="tr">Incompass'd round with gloomy hills above,</l>
<l n="tr">Which add a holy horror to the grove.</l>
<l n="tr">The first inhabitants of Grecian blood,</l>
<l n="tr">That sacred forest to Silvanus vow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The guardian of their flocks and fields; and pay</l>
<l n="tr">Their due devotions on his annual day.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from hence, along the river's side,</l>
<l n="tr">In tents secure, the Tuscan troops abide,</l>
<l n="tr">By Tarchon led. Now, from a rising ground,</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas cast his wond'ring eyes around,</l>
<l n="tr">And all the Tyrrhene army had in sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch'd on the spacious plain from left to right.</l>
<l n="tr">Thether his warlike train the Trojan led,</l>
<l n="tr">Refresh'd his men, and wearied horses fed.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="608" unit="card"/>Meantime the mother goddess, crown'd with charms,</l>
<l n="tr">Breaks thro' the clouds, and brings the fated arms.</l>
<l n="tr">Within a winding vale she finds her son,</l>
<l n="tr">On the cool river's banks, retir'd alone.</l>
<l n="tr">She shews her heav'nly form without disguise,</l>
<l n="tr">And gives herself to his desiring eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">“Behold,” she said, “perform'd in ev'ry part,</l>
<l n="tr">My promise made, and <persName>Vulcan</persName>'s labor'd art.</l>
<l n="tr">Now seek, secure, the Latian enemy,</l>
<l n="tr">And haughty Turnus to the field defy.”</l>
<l n="tr">She said; and, having first her son embrac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The radiant arms beneath an oak she plac'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of the gift, he roll'd his greedy sight</l>
<l n="tr">Around the work, and gaz'd with vast delight.</l>
<l n="tr">He lifts, he turns, he poises, and admires</l>
<l n="tr">The crested helm, that vomits radiant fires:</l>
<l n="tr">His hands the fatal sword and corslet hold,</l>
<l n="tr">One keen with temper'd steel, one stiff with gold:</l>
<l n="tr">Both ample, flaming both, and beamy bright;</l>
<l n="tr">So shines a cloud, when edg'd with adverse light.</l>
<l n="tr">He shakes the pointed spear, and longs to try</l>
<l n="tr">The plated cuishes on his manly thigh;</l>
<l n="tr">But most admires the shield's mysterious mold,</l>
<l n="tr">And Roman triumphs rising on the gold:</l>
<l n="tr">For these, emboss'd, the heav'nly smith had wrought</l>
<l n="tr">(Not in the rolls of future fate untaught)</l>
<l n="tr">The wars in order, and the race divine</l>
<l n="tr">Of warriors issuing from the Julian line.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="630" unit="card"/>The cave of <persName>Mars</persName> was dress'd with mossy greens:</l>
<l n="tr">There, by the wolf, were laid the martial twins.</l>
<l n="tr">Intrepid on her swelling dugs they hung;</l>
<l n="tr">The foster dam loll'd out her fawning tongue:</l>
<l n="tr">They suck'd secure, while, bending back her head,</l>
<l n="tr">She lick'd their tender limbs, and form'd them as they fed.</l>
<l n="tr">Not far from thence new <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> appears, with games</l>
<l n="tr">Projected for the rape of Sabine dames.</l>
<l n="tr">The pit resounds with shrieks; a war succeeds,</l>
<l n="tr">For breach of public faith, and unexampled deeds.</l>
<l n="tr">Here for revenge the Sabine troops contend;</l>
<l n="tr">The Romans there with arms the prey defend.</l>
<l n="tr">Wearied with tedious war, at length they cease;</l>
<l n="tr">And both the kings and kingdoms plight the peace.</l>
<l n="tr">The friendly chiefs before Jove's altar stand,</l>
<l n="tr">Both arm'd, with each a charger in his hand:</l>
<l n="tr">A fatted sow for sacrifice is led,</l>
<l n="tr">With imprecations on the perjur'd head.</l>
<l n="tr">Near this, the traitor Metius, stretch'd between</l>
<l n="tr">Four fiery steeds, is dragg'd along the green,</l>
<l n="tr">By Tullus' doom: the brambles drink his blood,</l>
<l n="tr">And his torn limbs are left the vulture's food.</l>
<l n="tr">There, Porsena to <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> proud Tarquin brings,</l>
<l n="tr">And would by force restore the banish'd kings.</l>
<l n="tr">One tyrant for his fellow-tyrant fights;</l>
<l n="tr">The Roman youth assert their native rights.</l>
<l n="tr">Before the town the Tuscan army lies,</l>
<l n="tr">To win by famine, or by fraud surprise.</l>
<l n="tr">Their king, half-threat'ning, half-disdaining stood,</l>
<l n="tr">While Cocles broke the bridge, and stemm'd the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">The captive maids there tempt the raging tide,</l>
<l n="tr">Scap'd from their chains, with Cloelia for their guide.</l>
<l n="tr">High on a rock heroic <persName>Manlius</persName> stood,</l>
<l n="tr">To guard the temple, and the temple's god.</l>
<l n="tr">Then <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> was poor; and there you might behold</l>
<l n="tr">The palace thatch'd with straw, now roof'd with gold.</l>
<l n="tr">The silver goose before the shining gate</l>
<l n="tr">There flew, and, by her cackle, sav'd the state.</l>
<l n="tr">She told the Gauls' approach;  th'  approaching Gauls,</l>
<l n="tr">Obscure in night, ascend, and seize the walls.</l>
<l n="tr">The gold dissembled well their yellow hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And golden chains on their white necks they wear.</l>
<l n="tr">Gold are their vests; long Alpine spears they wield,</l>
<l n="tr">And their left arm sustains a length of shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Hard by, the leaping Salian priests advance;</l>
<l n="tr">And naked thro' the streets the mad Luperci dance,</l>
<l n="tr">In caps of wool; the targets dropp'd from heav'n.</l>
<l n="tr">Here modest matrons, in soft litters driv'n,</l>
<l n="tr">To pay their vows in solemn pomp appear,</l>
<l n="tr">And odorous gums in their chaste hands they bear.</l>
<l n="tr">Far hence remov'd, the Stygian seats are seen;</l>
<l n="tr">Pains of the damn'd, and punish'd Catiline</l>
<l n="tr">Hung on a rock—the traitor; and, around,</l>
<l n="tr">The Furies hissing from the nether ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Apart from these, the happy souls he draws,</l>
<l n="tr">And <persName>Cato</persName>'s holy ghost dispensing laws.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="671" unit="card"/>Betwixt the quarters flows a golden sea;</l>
<l n="tr">But foaming surges there in silver play.</l>
<l n="tr">The dancing dolphins with their tails divide</l>
<l n="tr">The glitt'ring waves, and cut the precious tide.</l>
<l n="tr">Amid the main, two mighty fleets engage</l>
<l n="tr">Their brazen beaks, oppos'd with equal rage.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Actium,Acarnania" authname="perseus,Actium,Acarnania">Actium</placeName> surveys the well-disputed prize;</l>
<l n="tr">Leucate's wat'ry plain with foamy billows fries.</l>
<l n="tr">Young Caesar, on the stern, in armor bright,</l>
<l n="tr">Here leads the Romans and their gods to fight:</l>
<l n="tr">His beamy temples shoot their flames afar,</l>
<l n="tr">And o'er his head is hung the Julian star.</l>
<l n="tr">Agrippa seconds him, with prosp'rous gales,</l>
<l n="tr">And, with propitious gods, his foes assails:</l>
<l n="tr">A naval crown, that binds his manly brows,</l>
<l n="tr">The happy fortune of the fight foreshows.</l>
<l n="tr">Rang'd on the line oppos'd, Antonius brings</l>
<l n="tr">Barbarian aids, and troops of Eastern kings;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' Arabians near, and Bactrians from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">Of tongues discordant, and a mingled war:</l>
<l n="tr">And, rich in gaudy robes, amidst the strife,</l>
<l n="tr">His ill fate follows him—th' Egyptian wife.</l>
<l n="tr">Moving they fight; with oars and forky prows</l>
<l n="tr">The froth is gather'd, and the water glows.</l>
<l n="tr">It seems, as if the <placeName key="tgn,7011270" authname="tgn,7011270">Cyclades</placeName> again</l>
<l n="tr">Were rooted up, and justled in the main;</l>
<l n="tr">Or floating mountains floating mountains meet;</l>
<l n="tr">Such is the fierce encounter of the fleet.</l>
<l n="tr">Fireballs are thrown, and pointed jav'lins fly;</l>
<l n="tr">The fields of <persName>Neptune</persName> take a purple dye.</l>
<l n="tr">The queen herself, amidst the loud alarms,</l>
<l n="tr">With cymbals toss'd her fainting soldiers warms—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Fool as she was! who had not yet divin'd</l>
<l n="tr">Her cruel fate, nor saw the snakes behind.</l>
<l n="tr">Her country gods, the monsters of the sky,</l>
<l n="tr">Great <persName>Neptune</persName>, <persName>Pallas</persName>, and Love's Queen defy:</l>
<l n="tr">The dog Anubis barks, but barks in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor longer dares oppose  th'  ethereal train.</l>
<l n="tr"><persName>Mars</persName> in the middle of the shining shield</l>
<l n="tr">Is grav'd, and strides along the liquid field.</l>
<l n="tr">The Dirae souse from heav'n with swift descent;</l>
<l n="tr">And Discord, dyed in blood, with garments rent,</l>
<l n="tr">Divides the prease: her steps Bellona treads,</l>
<l n="tr">And shakes her iron rod above their heads.</l>
<l n="tr">This seen, Apollo, from his Actian height,</l>
<l n="tr">Pours down his arrows; at whose winged flight</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling Indians and Egyptians yield,</l>
<l n="tr">And soft Sabaeans quit the wat'ry field.</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal mistress hoists her silken sails,</l>
<l n="tr">And, shrinking from the fight, invokes the gales.</l>
<l n="tr">Aghast she looks, and heaves her breast for breath,</l>
<l n="tr">Panting, and pale with fear of future death.</l>
<l n="tr">The god had figur'd her as driv'n along</l>
<l n="tr">By winds and waves, and scudding thro' the throng.</l>
<l n="tr">Just opposite, sad Nilus opens wide</l>
<l n="tr">His arms and ample bosom to the tide,</l>
<l n="tr">And spreads his mantle o'er the winding coast,</l>
<l n="tr">In which he wraps his queen, and hides the flying host.</l>
<l n="tr">The victor to the gods his thanks express'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, triumphant, with his presence bless'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Three hundred temples in the town he plac'd;</l>
<l n="tr">With spoils and altars ev'ry temple grac'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Three shining nights, and three succeeding days,</l>
<l n="tr">The fields resound with shouts, the streets with praise,</l>
<l n="tr">The domes with songs, the theaters with plays.</l>
<l n="tr">All altars flame: before each altar lies,</l>
<l n="tr">Drench'd in his gore, the destin'd sacrifice.</l>
<l n="tr">Great Caesar sits sublime upon his throne,</l>
<l n="tr">Before Apollo's porch of Parian stone;</l>
<l n="tr">Accepts the presents vow'd for victory,</l>
<l n="tr">And hangs the monumental crowns on high.</l>
<l n="tr">Vast crowds of vanquish'd nations march along,</l>
<l n="tr">Various in arms, in habit, and in tongue.</l>
<l n="tr">Here, Mulciber assigns the proper place</l>
<l n="tr">For Carians, and  th'  ungirt Numidian race;</l>
<l n="tr">Then ranks the Thracians in the second row,</l>
<l n="tr">With Scythians, expert in the dart and bow.</l>
<l n="tr">And here the tam'd <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> humbly glides,</l>
<l n="tr">And there the <placeName key="tgn,7012611" authname="tgn,7012611">Rhine</placeName> submits her swelling tides,</l>
<l n="tr">And proud Araxes, whom no bridge could bind;</l>
<l n="tr">The Danes' unconquer'd offspring march behind,</l>
<l n="tr">And Morini, the last of humankind.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="729" unit="card"/>These figures, on the shield divinely wrought,</l>
<l n="tr">By Vulcan labor'd, and by Venus brought,</l>
<l n="tr">With joy and wonder fill the hero's thought.</l>
<l n="tr">Unknown the names, he yet admires the grace,</l>
<l n="tr">And bears aloft the fame and fortune of his race.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>