<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="9" org="uniform" sample="complete">
<milestone ed="p" n="1" unit="card"/>
<l n="tr">While these affairs in distant places pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The various Iris Juno sends with haste,</l>
<l n="tr">To find bold Turnus, who, with anxious thought,</l>
<l n="tr">The secret shade of his great grandsire sought.</l>
<l n="tr">Retir'd alone she found the daring man,</l>
<l n="tr">And op'd her rosy lips, and thus began:</l>
<l n="tr">“What none of all the gods could grant thy vows,</l>
<l n="tr">That, Turnus, this auspicious day bestows.</l>
<l n="tr">Aeneas, gone to seek  th'  Arcadian prince,</l>
<l n="tr">Has left the Trojan camp without defense;</l>
<l n="tr">And, short of succors there, employs his pains</l>
<l n="tr">In parts remote to raise the Tuscan swains.</l>
<l n="tr">Now snatch an hour that favors thy designs;</l>
<l n="tr">Unite thy forces, and attack their lines.”</l>
<l n="tr">This said, on equal wings she pois'd her weight,</l>
<l n="tr">And form'd a radiant rainbow in her flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The Daunian hero lifts his hands eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus invokes the goddess as she flies:</l>
<l n="tr">“Iris, the grace of heav'n, what pow'r divine</l>
<l n="tr">Has sent thee down, thro' dusky clouds to shine?</l>
<l n="tr">See, they divide; immortal day appears,</l>
<l n="tr">And glitt'ring planets dancing in their spheres!</l>
<l n="tr">With joy, these happy omens I obey,</l>
<l n="tr">And follow to the war the god that leads the way.”</l>
<l n="tr">Thus having said, as by the brook he stood,</l>
<l n="tr">He scoop'd the water from the crystal flood;</l>
<l n="tr">Then with his hands the drops to heav'n he throws,</l>
<l n="tr">And loads the pow'rs above with offer'd vows.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="25" unit="card"/>Now march the bold confed'rates thro' the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Well hors'd, well clad; a rich and shining train.</l>
<l n="tr">Messapus leads the van; and, in the rear,</l>
<l n="tr">The sons of Tyrrheus in bright arms appear.</l>
<l n="tr">In the main battle, with his flaming crest,</l>
<l n="tr">The mighty Turnus tow'rs above the rest.</l>
<l n="tr">Silent they move, majestically slow,</l>
<l n="tr">Like ebbing <placeName key="tgn,1127805" authname="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>, or Ganges in his flow.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans view the dusty cloud from far,</l>
<l n="tr">And the dark menace of the distant war.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,1121615" authname="tgn,1121615">Caicus</placeName> from the rampire saw it rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Black'ning the fields, and thick'ning thro' the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">Then to his fellows thus aloud he calls:</l>
<l n="tr">“What rolling clouds, my friends, approach the walls?</l>
<l n="tr">Arm! arm! and man the works! prepare your spears</l>
<l n="tr">And pointed darts! the Latian host appears.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus warn'd, they shut their gates; with shouts ascend</l>
<l n="tr">The bulwarks, and, secure, their foes attend:</l>
<l n="tr">For their wise gen'ral, with foreseeing care,</l>
<l n="tr">Had charg'd them not to tempt the doubtful war,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor, tho' provok'd, in open fields advance,</l>
<l n="tr">But close within their lines attend their chance.</l>
<l n="tr">Unwilling, yet they keep the strict command,</l>
<l n="tr">And sourly wait in arms the hostile band.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="47" unit="card"/>The fiery Turnus flew before the rest:</l>
<l n="tr">A piebald steed of Thracian strain he press'd;</l>
<l n="tr">His helm of massy gold, and crimson was his crest.</l>
<l n="tr">With twenty horse to second his designs,</l>
<l n="tr">An unexpected foe, he fac'd the lines.</l>
<l n="tr">“Is there,” he said, “in arms, who bravely dare</l>
<l n="tr">His leader's honor and his danger share?”</l>
<l n="tr">Then spurring on, his brandish'd dart he threw,</l>
<l n="tr">In sign of war: applauding shouts ensue.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Amaz'd to find a dastard race, that run</l>
<l n="tr">Behind the rampires and the battle shun,</l>
<l n="tr">He rides around the camp, with rolling eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">And stops at ev'ry post, and ev'ry passage tries.</l>
<l n="tr">So roams the nightly wolf about the fold:</l>
<l n="tr">Wet with descending show'rs, and stiff with cold,</l>
<l n="tr">He howls for hunger, and he grins for pain,</l>
<l n="tr">(His gnashing teeth are exercis'd in vain,)</l>
<l n="tr">And, impotent of anger, finds no way</l>
<l n="tr">In his distended paws to grasp the prey.</l>
<l n="tr">The mothers listen; but the bleating lambs</l>
<l n="tr">Securely swig the dug, beneath the dams.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus ranges eager Turnus o'er the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Sharp with desire, and furious with disdain;</l>
<l n="tr">Surveys each passage with a piercing sight,</l>
<l n="tr">To force his foes in equal field to fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus while he gazes round, at length he spies,</l>
<l n="tr">Where, fenc'd with strong redoubts, their navy lies,</l>
<l n="tr">Close underneath the walls; the washing tide</l>
<l n="tr">Secures from all approach this weaker side.</l>
<l n="tr">He takes the wish'd occasion, fills his hand</l>
<l n="tr">With ready fires, and shakes a flaming brand.</l>
<l n="tr">Urg'd by his presence, ev'ry soul is warm'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And ev'ry hand with kindled firs is arm'd.</l>
<l n="tr">From the fir'd pines the scatt'ring sparkles fly;</l>
<l n="tr">Fat vapors, mix'd with flames, involve the sky.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="77" unit="card"/>What pow'r, O Muses, could avert the flame</l>
<l n="tr">Which threaten'd, in the fleet, the Trojan name?</l>
<l n="tr">Tell: for the fact, thro' length of time obscure,</l>
<l n="tr">Is hard to faith; yet shall the fame endure.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>'T is said that, when the chief prepar'd his flight,</l>
<l n="tr">And fell'd his timber from Mount Ida's height,</l>
<l n="tr">The grandam goddess then approach'd her son,</l>
<l n="tr">And with a mother's majesty begun:</l>
<l n="tr">“Grant me,” she said, “the sole request I bring,</l>
<l n="tr">Since conquer'd heav'n has own'd you for its king.</l>
<l n="tr">On Ida's brows, for ages past, there stood,</l>
<l n="tr">With firs and maples fill'd, a shady wood;</l>
<l n="tr">And on the summit rose a sacred grove,</l>
<l n="tr">Where I was worship'd with religious love.</l>
<l n="tr">Those woods, that holy grove, my long delight,</l>
<l n="tr">I gave the Trojan prince, to speed his flight.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, fill'd with fear, on their behalf I come;</l>
<l n="tr">Let neither winds o'erset, nor waves intomb</l>
<l n="tr">The floating forests of the sacred pine;</l>
<l n="tr">But let it be their safety to be mine.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then thus replied her awful son, who rolls</l>
<l n="tr">The radiant stars, and heav'n and earth controls:</l>
<l n="tr">“How dare you, mother, endless date demand</l>
<l n="tr">For vessels molded by a mortal hand?</l>
<l n="tr">What then is fate? Shall bold Aeneas ride,</l>
<l n="tr">Of safety certain, on  th'  uncertain tide?</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, what I can, I grant; when, wafted o'er,</l>
<l n="tr">The chief is landed on the Latian shore,</l>
<l n="tr">Whatever ships escape the raging storms,</l>
<l n="tr">At my command shall change their fading forms</l>
<l n="tr">To nymphs divine, and plow the wat'ry way,</l>
<l n="tr">Like <placeName key="tgn,7010522" authname="tgn,7010522">Dotis</placeName> and the daughters of the sea.”</l>
<l n="tr">To seal his sacred vow, by Styx he swore,</l>
<l n="tr">The lake of liquid pitch, the dreary shore,</l>
<l n="tr">And Phlegethon's innavigable flood,</l>
<l n="tr">And the black regions of his brother god.</l>
<l n="tr">He said; and shook the skies with his imperial nod.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="107" unit="card"/>And now at length the number'd hours were come,</l>
<l n="tr">Prefix'd by fate's irrevocable doom,</l>
<l n="tr">When the great Mother of the Gods was free</l>
<l n="tr">To save her ships, and finish Jove's decree.</l>
<l n="tr">First, from the quarter of the morn, there sprung</l>
<l n="tr">A light that sign'd the heav'ns, and shot along;</l>
<l n="tr">Then from a cloud, fring'd round with golden fires,</l>
<l n="tr">Were timbrels heard, and Berecynthian choirs;</l>
<l n="tr">And, last, a voice, with more than mortal sounds,</l>
<l n="tr">Both hosts, in arms oppos'd, with equal horror wounds:</l>
<l n="tr">“O Trojan race, your needless aid forbear,</l>
<l n="tr">And know, my ships are my peculiar care.</l>
<l n="tr">With greater ease the bold Rutulian may,</l>
<l n="tr">With hissing brands, attempt to burn the sea,</l>
<l n="tr">Than singe my sacred pines. But you, my charge,</l>
<l n="tr">Loos'd from your crooked anchors, launch at large,</l>
<l n="tr">Exalted each a nymph: forsake the sand,</l>
<l n="tr">And swim the seas, at Cybele's command.”</l>
<l n="tr">No sooner had the goddess ceas'd to speak,</l>
<l n="tr">When, lo!  th'  obedient ships their haulsers break;</l>
<l n="tr">And, strange to tell, like dolphins, in the main</l>
<l n="tr">They plunge their prows, and dive, and spring again:</l>
<l n="tr">As many beauteous maids the billows sweep,</l>
<l n="tr">As rode before tall vessels on the deep.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="123" unit="card"/>The foes, surpris'd with wonder, stood aghast;</l>
<l n="tr">Messapus curb'd his fiery courser's haste;</l>
<l n="tr">Old <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> roar'd, and, raising up his head,</l>
<l n="tr">Call'd back his waters to their oozy bed.</l>
<l n="tr">Turnus alone, undaunted, bore the shock,</l>
<l n="tr">And with these words his trembling troops bespoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“These monsters for the Trojans' fate are meant,</l>
<l n="tr">And are by Jove for black presages sent.</l>
<l n="tr">He takes the cowards' last relief away;</l>
<l n="tr">For fly they cannot, and, constrain'd to stay,</l>
<l n="tr">Must yield unfought, a base inglorious prey.</l>
<l n="tr">The liquid half of all the globe is lost;</l>
<l n="tr">Heav'n shuts the seas, and we secure the coast.</l>
<l n="tr">Theirs is no more than that small spot of ground</l>
<l n="tr">Which myriads of our martial men surround.</l>
<l n="tr">Their fates I fear not, or vain oracles.</l>
<l n="tr">'T was giv'n to Venus they should cross the seas,</l>
<l n="tr">And land secure upon the Latian plains:</l>
<l n="tr">Their promis'd hour is pass'd, and mine remains.</l>
<l n="tr">'T is in the fate of Turnus to destroy,</l>
<l n="tr">With sword and fire, the faithless race of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l n="tr">Shall such affronts as these alone inflame</l>
<l n="tr">The Grecian brothers, and the Grecian name?</l>
<l n="tr">My cause and theirs is one; a fatal strife,</l>
<l n="tr">And final ruin, for a ravish'd wife.</l>
<l n="tr">Was 't not enough, that, punish'd for the crime,</l>
<l n="tr">They fell; but will they fall a second time?</l>
<l n="tr">One would have thought they paid enough before,</l>
<l n="tr">To curse the costly sex, and durst offend no more.</l>
<l n="tr">Can they securely trust their feeble wall,</l>
<l n="tr">A slight partition, a thin interval,</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt their fate and them; when <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, tho' built</l>
<l n="tr">By hands divine, yet perish'd by their guilt?</l>
<l n="tr">Lend me, for once, my friends, your valiant hands,</l>
<l n="tr">To force from out their lines these dastard bands.</l>
<l n="tr">Less than a thousand ships will end this war,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor <persName>Vulcan</persName> needs his fated arms prepare.</l>
<l n="tr">Let all the Tuscans, all  th'  Arcadians, join!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor these, nor those, shall frustrate my design.</l>
<l n="tr">Let them not fear the treasons of the night,</l>
<l n="tr">The robb'd Palladium, the pretended flight:</l>
<l n="tr">Our onset shall be made in open light.</l>
<l n="tr">No wooden engine shall their town betray;</l>
<l n="tr">Fires they shall have around, but fires by day.</l>
<l n="tr">No Grecian babes before their camp appear,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Hector's arms detain'd to the tenth tardy year.</l>
<l n="tr">Now, since the sun is rolling to the west,</l>
<l n="tr">Give we the silent night to needful rest:</l>
<l n="tr">Refresh your bodies, and your arms prepare;</l>
<l n="tr">The morn shall end the small remains of war.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The post of honor to Messapus falls,</l>
<l n="tr">To keep the nightly guard, to watch the walls,</l>
<l n="tr">To pitch the fires at distances around,</l>
<l n="tr">And close the Trojans in their scanty ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Twice seven Rutulian captains ready stand,</l>
<l n="tr">And twice seven hundred horse these chiefs command;</l>
<l n="tr">All clad in shining arms the works invest,</l>
<l n="tr">Each with a radiant helm and waving crest.</l>
<l n="tr">Stretch'd at their length, they press the grassy ground;</l>
<l n="tr">They laugh, they sing, (the jolly bowls go round,)</l>
<l n="tr">With lights and cheerful fires renew the day,</l>
<l n="tr">And pass the wakeful night in feasts and play.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="168" unit="card"/>The Trojans, from above, their foes beheld,</l>
<l n="tr">And with arm'd legions all the rampires fill'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Seiz'd with affright, their gates they first explore;</l>
<l n="tr">Join works to works with bridges, tow'r to tow'r:</l>
<l n="tr">Thus all things needful for defense abound.</l>
<l n="tr">Mnestheus and brave Seresthus walk the round,</l>
<l n="tr">Commission'd by their absent prince to share</l>
<l n="tr">The common danger, and divide the care.</l>
<l n="tr">The soldiers draw their lots, and, as they fall,</l>
<l n="tr">By turns relieve each other on the wall.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nigh where the foes their utmost guards advance,</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="176" unit="card"/>To watch the gate was warlike Nisus' chance.</l>
<l n="tr">His father Hyrtacus of noble blood;</l>
<l n="tr">His mother was a huntress of the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent him to the wars. Well could he bear</l>
<l n="tr">His lance in fight, and dart the flying spear,</l>
<l n="tr">But better skill'd unerring shafts to send.</l>
<l n="tr">Beside him stood Euryalus, his friend:</l>
<l n="tr">Euryalus, than whom the Trojan host</l>
<l n="tr">No fairer face, or sweeter air, could boasT'mdash;/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Scarce had the down to shade his cheeks begun.</l>
<l n="tr">One was their care, and their delight was one:</l>
<l n="tr">One common hazard in the war they shar'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And now were both by choice upon the guard.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Nisus thus: “Or do the gods inspire</l>
<l n="tr">This warmth, or make we gods of our desire?</l>
<l n="tr">A gen'rous ardor boils within my breast,</l>
<l n="tr">Eager of action, enemy to rest:</l>
<l n="tr">This urges me to fight, and fires my mind</l>
<l n="tr">To leave a memorable name behind.</l>
<l n="tr">Thou see'st the foe secure; how faintly shine</l>
<l n="tr">Their scatter'd fires! the most, in sleep supine</l>
<l n="tr">Along the ground, an easy conquest lie:</l>
<l n="tr">The wakeful few the fuming flagon ply;</l>
<l n="tr">All hush'd around. Now hear what I revolve—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">A thought unripe—and scarcely yet resolve.</l>
<l n="tr">Our absent prince both camp and council mourn;</l>
<l n="tr">By message both would hasten his return:</l>
<l n="tr">If they confer what I demand on thee,</l>
<l n="tr">(For fame is recompense enough for me,)</l>
<l n="tr">Methinks, beneath yon hill, I have espied</l>
<l n="tr">A way that safely will my passage guide.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Euryalus stood list'ning while he spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">With love of praise and noble envy struck;</l>
<l n="tr">Then to his ardent friend expos'd his mind:</l>
<l n="tr">“All this, alone, and leaving me behind!</l>
<l n="tr">Am I unworthy, Nisus, to be join'd?</l>
<l n="tr">Thinkist thou I can my share of glory yield,</l>
<l n="tr">Or send thee unassisted to the field?</l>
<l n="tr">Not so my father taught my childhood arms;</l>
<l n="tr">Born in a siege, and bred among alarms!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor is my youth unworthy of my friend,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor of the heav'n-born hero I attend.</l>
<l n="tr">The thing call'd life, with ease I can disclaim,</l>
<l n="tr">And think it over-sold to purchase fame.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Nisus thus: “Alas! thy tender years</l>
<l n="tr">Would minister new matter to my fears.</l>
<l n="tr">So may the gods, who view this friendly strife,</l>
<l n="tr">Restore me to thy lov'd embrace with life,</l>
<l n="tr">Condemn'd to pay my vows, (as sure I trust,)</l>
<l n="tr">This thy request is cruel and unjust.</l>
<l n="tr">But if some chance—as many chances are,</l>
<l n="tr">And doubtful hazards, in the deeds of war—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">If one should reach my head, there let it fall,</l>
<l n="tr">And spare thy life; I would not perish all.</l>
<l n="tr">Thy bloomy youth deserves a longer date:</l>
<l n="tr">Live thou to mourn thy love's unhappy fate;</l>
<l n="tr">To bear my mangled body from the foe,</l>
<l n="tr">Or buy it back, and fun'ral rites bestow.</l>
<l n="tr">Or, if hard fortune shall those dues deny,</l>
<l n="tr">Thou canst at least an empty tomb supply.</l>
<l n="tr">O let not me the widow's tears renew!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor let a mother's curse my name pursue:</l>
<l n="tr">Thy pious parent, who, for love of thee,</l>
<l n="tr">Forsook the coasts of friendly <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>,</l>
<l n="tr">Her age committing to the seas and wind,</l>
<l n="tr">When ev'ry weary matron stay'd behind.”</l>
<l n="tr">To this, Euryalus: “You plead in vain,</l>
<l n="tr">And but protract the cause you cannot gain.</l>
<l n="tr">No more delays, but haste!” With that, he wakes</l>
<l n="tr">The nodding watch; each to his office takes.</l>
<l n="tr">The guard reliev'd, the gen'rous couple went</l>
<l n="tr">To find the council at the royal tent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="224" unit="card"/>All creatures else forgot their daily care,</l>
<l n="tr">And sleep, the common gift of nature, share;</l>
<l n="tr">Except the Trojan peers, who wakeful sate</l>
<l n="tr">In nightly council for  th'  indanger'd state.</l>
<l n="tr">They vote a message to their absent chief,</l>
<l n="tr">Shew their distress, and beg a swift relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Amid the camp a silent seat they chose,</l>
<l n="tr">Remote from clamor, and secure from foes.</l>
<l n="tr">On their left arms their ample shields they bear,</l>
<l n="tr">The right reclin'd upon the bending spear.</l>
<l n="tr">Now Nisus and his friend approach the guard,</l>
<l n="tr">And beg admission, eager to be heard:</l>
<l n="tr">Th' affair important, not to be deferr'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius bids 'em be conducted in,</l>
<l n="tr">Ord'ring the more experienc'd to begin.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Nisus thus: “Ye fathers, lend your ears;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor judge our bold attempt beyond our years.</l>
<l n="tr">The foe, securely drench'd in sleep and wine,</l>
<l n="tr">Neglect their watch; the fires but thinly shine;</l>
<l n="tr">And where the smoke in cloudy vapors flies,</l>
<l n="tr">Cov'ring the plain, and curling to the skies,</l>
<l n="tr">Betwixt two paths, which at the gate divide,</l>
<l n="tr">Close by the sea, a passage we have spied,</l>
<l n="tr">Which will our way to great Aeneas guide.</l>
<l n="tr">Expect each hour to see him safe again,</l>
<l n="tr">Loaded with spoils of foes in battle slain.</l>
<l n="tr">Snatch we the lucky minute while we may;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor can we be mistaken in the way;</l>
<l n="tr">For, hunting in the vale, we both have seen</l>
<l n="tr">The rising turrets, and the stream between,</l>
<l n="tr">And know the winding course, with ev'ry ford.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="246" unit="card"/>He ceas'd; and old Aletes took the word:</l>
<l n="tr">“Our country gods, in whom our trust we place,</l>
<l n="tr">Will yet from ruin save the Trojan race,</l>
<l n="tr">While we behold such dauntless worth appear</l>
<l n="tr">In dawning youth, and souls so void of fear.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then into tears of joy the father broke;</l>
<l n="tr">Each in his longing arms by turns he took;</l>
<l n="tr">Panted and paus'd; and thus again he spoke:</l>
<l n="tr">“Ye brave young men, what equal gifts can we,</l>
<l n="tr">In recompense of such desert, decree?</l>
<l n="tr">The greatest, sure, and best you can receive,</l>
<l n="tr">The gods and your own conscious worth will give.</l>
<l n="tr">The rest our grateful gen'ral will bestow,</l>
<l n="tr">And young Ascanius till his manhood owe.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“And I, whose welfare in my father lies,”</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius adds, “by the great deities,</l>
<l n="tr">By my dear country, by my household gods,</l>
<l n="tr">By hoary Vesta's rites and dark abodes,</l>
<l n="tr">Adjure you both, (on you my fortune stands;</l>
<l n="tr">That and my faith I plight into your hands,)</l>
<l n="tr">Make me but happy in his safe return,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose wanted presence I can only mourn;</l>
<l n="tr">Your common gift shall two large goblets be</l>
<l n="tr">Of silver, wrought with curious imagery,</l>
<l n="tr">And high emboss'd, which, when old Priam reign'd,</l>
<l n="tr">My conqu'ring sire at sack'd Arisba gain'd;</l>
<l n="tr">And more, two tripods cast in antic mold,</l>
<l n="tr">With two great talents of the finest gold;</l>
<l n="tr">Beside a costly bowl, ingrav'd with art,</l>
<l n="tr">Which Dido gave, when first she gave her heart.</l>
<l n="tr">But, if in conquer'd <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> we reign,</l>
<l n="tr">When spoils by lot the victor shall obtain—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Thou saw'st the courser by proud Turnus press'd:</l>
<l n="tr">That, Nisus, and his arms, and nodding crest,</l>
<l n="tr">And shield, from chance exempt, shall be thy share:</l>
<l n="tr">Twelve lab'ring slaves, twelve handmaids young and fair</l>
<l n="tr">All clad in rich attire, and train'd with care;</l>
<l n="tr">And, last, a Latian field with fruitful plains,</l>
<l n="tr">And a large portion of the king's domains.</l>
<l n="tr">But thou, whose years are more to mine allied—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">No fate my vow'd affection shall divide</l>
<l n="tr">From thee, heroic youth! Be wholly mine;</l>
<l n="tr">Take full possession; all my soul is thine.</l>
<l n="tr">One faith, one fame, one fate, shall both attend;</l>
<l n="tr">My life's companion, and my bosom friend:</l>
<l n="tr">My peace shall be committed to thy care,</l>
<l n="tr">And to thy conduct my concerns in war.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus the young Euryalus replied:</l>
<l n="tr">“Whatever fortune, good or bad, betide,</l>
<l n="tr">The same shall be my age, as now my youth;</l>
<l n="tr">No time shall find me wanting to my truth.</l>
<l n="tr">This only from your goodness let me gain</l>
<l n="tr">(And, this ungranted, all rewards are vain)</l>
<l n="tr">Of Priam's royal race my mother came—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">And sure the best that ever bore the name—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Whom neither <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> nor <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> could hold</l>
<l n="tr">From me departing, but, o'erspent and old,</l>
<l n="tr">My fate she follow'd. Ignorant of this</l>
<l n="tr">(Whatever) danger, neither parting kiss,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor pious blessing taken, her I leave,</l>
<l n="tr">And in this only act of all my life deceive.</l>
<l n="tr">By this right hand and conscious Night I swear,</l>
<l n="tr">My soul so sad a farewell could not bear.</l>
<l n="tr">Be you her comfort; fill my vacant place</l>
<l n="tr">(Permit me to presume so great a grace)</l>
<l n="tr">Support her age, forsaken and distress'd.</l>
<l n="tr">That hope alone will fortify my breast</l>
<l n="tr">Against the worst of fortunes, and of fears.”</l>
<l n="tr">He said. The mov'd assistants melt in tears.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then thus Ascanius, wonderstruck to see</l>
<l n="tr">That image of his filial piety:</l>
<l n="tr">“So great beginnings, in so green an age,</l>
<l n="tr">Exact the faith which I again ingage.</l>
<l n="tr">Thy mother all the dues shall justly claim,</l>
<l n="tr">Creusa had, and only want the name.</l>
<l n="tr">Whate'er event thy bold attempt shall have,</l>
<l n="tr">'T is merit to have borne a son so brave.</l>
<l n="tr">Now by my head, a sacred oath, I swear,</l>
<l n="tr">(My father us'd it,) what, returning here</l>
<l n="tr">Crown'd with success, I for thyself prepare,</l>
<l n="tr">That, if thou fail, shall thy lov'd mother share.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He said, and weeping, while he spoke the word,</l>
<l n="tr">From his broad belt he drew a shining sword,</l>
<l n="tr">Magnificent with gold. Lycaon made,</l>
<l n="tr">And in an ivory scabbard sheath'd the blade.</l>
<l n="tr">This was his gift. Great Mnestheus gave his friend</l>
<l n="tr">A lion's hide, his body to defend;</l>
<l n="tr">And good Aletes furnish'd him, beside,</l>
<l n="tr">With his own trusty helm, of temper tried.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thus arm'd they went. The noble Trojans wait</l>
<l n="tr">Their issuing forth, and follow to the gate</l>
<l n="tr">With prayers and vows. Above the rest appears</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius, manly far beyond his years,</l>
<l n="tr">And messages committed to their care,</l>
<l n="tr">Which all in winds were lost, and flitting air.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="314" unit="card"/>The trenches first they pass'd; then took their way</l>
<l n="tr">Where their proud foes in pitch'd pavilions lay;</l>
<l n="tr">To many fatal, ere themselves were slain.</l>
<l n="tr">They found the careless host dispers'd upon the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, gorg'd, and drunk with wine, supinely snore.</l>
<l n="tr">Unharness'd chariots stand along the shore:</l>
<l n="tr">Amidst the wheels and reins, the goblet by,</l>
<l n="tr">A medley of debauch and war, they lie.</l>
<l n="tr">Observing Nisus shew'd his friend the sight:</l>
<l n="tr">“Behold a conquest gain'd without a fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Occasion offers, and I stand prepar'd;</l>
<l n="tr">There lies our way; be thou upon the guard,</l>
<l n="tr">And look around, while I securely go,</l>
<l n="tr">And hew a passage thro' the sleeping foe.”</l>
<l n="tr">Softly he spoke; then striding took his way,</l>
<l n="tr">With his drawn sword, where haughty Rhamnes lay;</l>
<l n="tr">His head rais'd high on tapestry beneath,</l>
<l n="tr">And heaving from his breast, he drew his breath;</l>
<l n="tr">A king and prophet, by King Turnus lov'd:</l>
<l n="tr">But fate by prescience cannot be remov'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Him and his sleeping slaves he slew; then spies</l>
<l n="tr">Where Remus, with his rich retinue, lies.</l>
<l n="tr">His armor-bearer first, and next he kills</l>
<l n="tr">His charioteer, intrench'd betwixt the wheels</l>
<l n="tr">And his lov'd horses; last invades their lord;</l>
<l n="tr">Full on his neck he drives the fatal sword:</l>
<l n="tr">The gasping head flies off; a purple flood</l>
<l n="tr">Flows from the trunk, that welters in the blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Which, by the spurning heels dispers'd around,</l>
<l n="tr">The bed besprinkles and bedews the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">Lamus the bold, and Lamyrus the strong,</l>
<l n="tr">He slew, and then Serranus fair and young.</l>
<l n="tr">From dice and wine the youth retir'd to rest,</l>
<l n="tr">And puff'd the fumy god from out his breast:</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n then he dreamt of drink and lucky play—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">More lucky, had it lasted till the day.</l>
<l n="tr">The famish'd lion thus, with hunger bold,</l>
<l n="tr">O'erleaps the fences of the nightly fold,</l>
<l n="tr">And tears the peaceful flocks: with silent awe</l>
<l n="tr">Trembling they lie, and pant beneath his paw.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nor with less rage Euryalus employs</l>
<l n="tr">The wrathful sword, or fewer foes destroys;</l>
<l n="tr">But on  th'  ignoble crowd his fury flew;</l>
<l n="tr">He Fadus, Hebesus, and Rhoetus slew.</l>
<l n="tr">Oppress'd with heavy sleep the former fell,</l>
<l n="tr">But Rhoetus wakeful, and observing all:</l>
<l n="tr">Behind a spacious jar he slink'd for fear;</l>
<l n="tr">The fatal iron found and reach'd him there;</l>
<l n="tr">For, as he rose, it pierc'd his naked side,</l>
<l n="tr">And, reeking, thence return'd in crimson dyed.</l>
<l n="tr">The wound pours out a stream of wine and blood;</l>
<l n="tr">The purple soul comes floating in the flood.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, where Messapus quarter'd, they arrive.</l>
<l n="tr">The fires were fainting there, and just alive;</l>
<l n="tr">The warrior-horses, tied in order, fed.</l>
<l n="tr">Nisus observ'd the discipline, and said:</l>
<l n="tr">“Our eager thirst of blood may both betray;</l>
<l n="tr">And see the scatter'd streaks of dawning day,</l>
<l n="tr">Foe to nocturnal thefts. No more, my friend;</l>
<l n="tr">Here let our glutted execution end.</l>
<l n="tr">A lane thro' slaughter'd bodies we have made.”</l>
<l n="tr">The bold Euryalus, tho' loth, obey'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Of arms, and arras, and of plate, they find</l>
<l n="tr">A precious load; but these they leave behind.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet, fond of gaudy spoils, the boy would stay</l>
<l n="tr">To make the rich caparison his prey,</l>
<l n="tr">Which on the steed of conquer'd Rhamnes lay.</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did his eyes less longingly behold</l>
<l n="tr">The girdle-belt, with nails of burnish'd gold.</l>
<l n="tr">This present Caedicus the rich bestow'd</l>
<l n="tr">On Remulus, when friendship first they vow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And, absent, join'd in hospitable ties:</l>
<l n="tr">He, dying, to his heir bequeath'd the prize;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, by the conqu'ring Ardean troops oppress'd,</l>
<l n="tr">He fell; and they the glorious gift possess'd.</l>
<l n="tr">These glitt'ring spoils (now made the victor's gain)</l>
<l n="tr">He to his body suits, but suits in vain:</l>
<l n="tr">Messapus' helm he finds among the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">And laces on, and wears the waving crest.</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of their conquest, prouder of their prey,</l>
<l n="tr">They leave the camp, and take the ready way.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="367" unit="card"/>But far they had not pass'd, before they spied</l>
<l n="tr">Three hundred horse, with Volscens for their guide.</l>
<l n="tr">The queen a legion to King Turnus sent;</l>
<l n="tr">But the swift horse the slower foot prevent,</l>
<l n="tr">And now, advancing, sought the leader's tent.</l>
<l n="tr">They saw the pair; for, thro' the doubtful shade,</l>
<l n="tr">His shining helm Euryalus betray'd,</l>
<l n="tr">On which the moon with full reflection play'd.</l>
<l n="tr">“'T is not for naught,” cried Volscens from the crowd,</l>
<l n="tr">“These men go there;” then rais'd his voice aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“Stand! stand! why thus in arms? And whither bent?</l>
<l n="tr">From whence, to whom, and on what errand sent?”</l>
<l n="tr">Silent they scud away, and haste their flight</l>
<l n="tr">To neighb'ring woods, and trust themselves to night.</l>
<l n="tr">The speedy horse all passages belay,</l>
<l n="tr">And spur their smoking steeds to cross their way,</l>
<l n="tr">And watch each entrance of the winding wood.</l>
<l n="tr">Black was the forest: thick with beech it stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Horrid with fern, and intricate with thorn;</l>
<l n="tr">Few paths of human feet, or tracks of beasts, were worn.</l>
<l n="tr">The darkness of the shades, his heavy prey,</l>
<l n="tr">And fear, misled the younger from his way.</l>
<l n="tr">But Nisus hit the turns with happier haste,</l>
<l n="tr">And, thoughtless of his friend, the forest pass'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And Alban plains, from Alba's name so call'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Where King Latinus then his oxen stall'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, turning at the length, he stood his ground,</l>
<l n="tr">And miss'd his friend, and cast his eyes around:</l>
<l n="tr">“Ah wretch!” he cried, “where have I left behind</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unhappy youth? where shall I hope to find?</l>
<l n="tr">Or what way take?” Again he ventures back,</l>
<l n="tr">And treads the mazes of his former track.</l>
<l n="tr">He winds the wood, and, list'ning, hears the noise</l>
<l n="tr">Of tramping coursers, and the riders' voice.</l>
<l n="tr">The sound approach'd; and suddenly he view'd</l>
<l n="tr">The foes inclosing, and his friend pursued,</l>
<l n="tr">Forelaid and taken, while he strove in vain</l>
<l n="tr">The shelter of the friendly shades to gain.</l>
<l n="tr">What should he next attempt? what arms employ,</l>
<l n="tr">What fruitless force, to free the captive boy?</l>
<l n="tr">Or desperate should he rush and lose his life,</l>
<l n="tr">With odds oppress'd, in such unequal strife?</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Resolv'd at length, his pointed spear he shook;</l>
<l n="tr">And, casting on the moon a mournful look:</l>
<l n="tr">“Guardian of groves, and goddess of the night,</l>
<l n="tr">Fair queen,” he said, “direct my dart aright.</l>
<l n="tr">If e'er my pious father, for my sake,</l>
<l n="tr">Did grateful off'rings on thy altars make,</l>
<l n="tr">Or I increas'd them with my sylvan toils,</l>
<l n="tr">And hung thy holy roofs with savage spoils,</l>
<l n="tr">Give me to scatter these.” Then from his ear</l>
<l n="tr">He pois'd, and aim'd, and launch'd the trembling spear.</l>
<l n="tr">The deadly weapon, hissing from the grove,</l>
<l n="tr">Impetuous on the back of <persName>Sulmo</persName> drove;</l>
<l n="tr">Pierc'd his thin armor, drank his vital blood,</l>
<l n="tr">And in his body left the broken</l>
<l n="tr">He staggers round; his eyeballs roll in death,</l>
<l n="tr">And with short sobs he gasps away his breath.</l>
<l n="tr">All stand amaz'd—a second jav'lin flies</l>
<l n="tr">With equal strength, and quivers thro' the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">This thro' thy temples, <persName>Tagus</persName>, forc'd the way,</l>
<l n="tr">And in the brainpan warmly buried lay.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="420" unit="card"/>Fierce Volscens foams with rage, and, gazing round,</l>
<l n="tr">Descried not him who gave the fatal wound,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor knew to fix revenge: “But thou,” he cries,</l>
<l n="tr">“Shalt pay for both,” and at the pris'ner flies</l>
<l n="tr">With his drawn sword. Then, struck with deep despair,</l>
<l n="tr">That cruel sight the lover could not bear;</l>
<l n="tr">But from his covert rush'd in open view,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent his voice before him as he flew:</l>
<l n="tr">“Me! me!” he cried, “turn all your swords alone</l>
<l n="tr">On me—the fact confess'd, the fault my own.</l>
<l n="tr">He neither could nor durst, the guiltless youth:</l>
<l n="tr">Ye moon and stars, bear witness to the truth!</l>
<l n="tr">His only crime (if friendship can offend)</l>
<l n="tr">Is too much love to his unhappy friend.”</l>
<l n="tr">Too late he speaks: the sword, which fury guides,</l>
<l n="tr">Driv'n with full force, had pierc'd his tender sides.</l>
<l n="tr">Down fell the beauteous youth: the yawning wound</l>
<l n="tr">Gush'd out a purple stream, and stain'd the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">His snowy neck reclines upon his breast,</l>
<l n="tr">Like a fair flow'r by the keen share oppress'd;</l>
<l n="tr">Like a white poppy sinking on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">Whose heavy head is overcharg'd with rain.</l>
<l n="tr">Despair, and rage, and vengeance justly vow'd,</l>
<l n="tr">Drove Nisus headlong on the hostile crowd.</l>
<l n="tr">Volscens he seeks; on him alone he bends:</l>
<l n="tr">Borne back and bor'd by his surrounding friends,</l>
<l n="tr">Onward he press'd, and kept him still in sight;</l>
<l n="tr">Then whirl'd aloft his sword with all his might:</l>
<l n="tr">Th' unerring steel descended while he spoke,</l>
<l n="tr">Piered his wide mouth, and thro' his weazon broke.</l>
<l n="tr">Dying, he slew; and, stagg'ring on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">With swimming eyes he sought his lover slain;</l>
<l n="tr">Then quiet on his bleeding bosom fell,</l>
<l n="tr">Content, in death, to be reveng'd so well.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="446" unit="card"/>O happy friends! for, if my verse can give</l>
<l n="tr">Immortal life, your fame shall ever live,</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd as the Capitol's foundation lies,</l>
<l n="tr">And spread, where'er the Roman eagle flies!</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="450" unit="card"/>The conqu'ring party first divide the prey,</l>
<l n="tr">Then their slain leader to the camp convey.</l>
<l n="tr">With wonder, as they went, the troops were fill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">To see such numbers whom so few had kill'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Serranus, Rhamnes, and the rest, they found:</l>
<l n="tr">Vast crowds the dying and the dead surround;</l>
<l n="tr">And the yet reeking blood o'erflows the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">All knew the helmet which Messapus lost,</l>
<l n="tr">But mourn'd a purchase that so dear had cost.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="459" unit="card"/>Now rose the ruddy morn from Tithon's bed,</l>
<l n="tr">And with the dawn of day the skies o'erspread;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor long the sun his daily course withheld,</l>
<l n="tr">But added colors to the world reveal'd:</l>
<l n="tr">When early Turnus, wak'ning with the light,</l>
<l n="tr">All clad in armor, calls his troops to fight.</l>
<l n="tr">His martial men with fierce harangue he fir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">And his own ardor in their souls inspir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">This done—to give new terror to his foes,</l>
<l n="tr">The heads of Nisus and his friend he shows,</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd high on pointed spears—a ghastly sight:</l>
<l n="tr">Loud peals of shouts ensue, and barbarous delight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Meantime the Trojans run, where danger calls;</l>
<l n="tr">They line their trenches, and they man their walls.</l>
<l n="tr">In front extended to the left they stood;</l>
<l n="tr">Safe was the right, surrounded by the flood.</l>
<l n="tr">But, casting from their tow'rs a frightful view,</l>
<l n="tr">They saw the faces, which too well they knew,</l>
<l n="tr">Tho' then disguis'd in death, and smear'd all o'er</l>
<l n="tr">With filth obscene, and dropping putrid gore.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="473" unit="card"/>Soon hasty fame thro' the sad city bears</l>
<l n="tr">The mournful message to the mother's ears.</l>
<l n="tr">An icy cold benumbs her limbs; she shakes;</l>
<l n="tr">Her cheeks the blood, her hand the web forsakes.</l>
<l n="tr">She runs the rampires round amidst the war,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor fears the flying darts; she rends her hair,</l>
<l n="tr">And fills with loud laments the liquid air.</l>
<l n="tr">“Thus, then, my lov'd Euryalus appears!</l>
<l n="tr">Thus looks the prop my declining years!</l>
<l n="tr">Was't on this face my famish'd eyes I fed?</l>
<l n="tr">Ah! how unlike the living is the dead!</l>
<l n="tr">And could'st thou leave me, cruel, thus alone?</l>
<l n="tr">Not one kind kiss from a departing son!</l>
<l n="tr">No look, no last adieu before he went,</l>
<l n="tr">In an ill-boding hour to slaughter sent!</l>
<l n="tr">Cold on the ground, and pressing foreign clay,</l>
<l n="tr">To Latian dogs and fowls he lies a prey!</l>
<l n="tr">Nor was I near to close his dying eyes,</l>
<l n="tr">To wash his wounds, to weep his obsequies,</l>
<l n="tr">To call about his corpse his crying friends,</l>
<l n="tr">Or spread the mantle (made for other ends)</l>
<l n="tr">On his dear body, which I wove with care,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor did my daily pains or nightly labor spare.</l>
<l n="tr">Where shall I find his corpse? what earth sustains</l>
<l n="tr">His trunk dismember'd, and his cold remains?</l>
<l n="tr">For this, alas! I left my needful ease,</l>
<l n="tr">Expos'd my life to winds and winter seas!</l>
<l n="tr">If any pity touch Rutulian hearts,</l>
<l n="tr">Here empty all your quivers, all your darts;</l>
<l n="tr">Or, if they fail, thou, Jove, conclude my woe,</l>
<l n="tr">And send me thunderstruck to shades below!”</l>
<l n="tr">Her shrieks and clamors pierce the Trojans' ears,</l>
<l n="tr">Unman their courage, and augment their fears;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor young Ascanius could the sight sustain,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor old Ilioneus his tears restrain,</l>
<l n="tr">But Actor and Idaeus jointly sent,</l>
<l n="tr">To bear the madding mother to her tent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="503" unit="card"/>And now the trumpets terribly, from far,</l>
<l n="tr">With rattling clangor, rouse the sleepy war.</l>
<l n="tr">The soldiers' shouts succeed the brazen sounds;</l>
<l n="tr">And heav'n, from pole to pole, the noise rebounds.</l>
<l n="tr">The Volscians bear their shields upon their head,</l>
<l n="tr">And, rushing forward, form a moving shed.</l>
<l n="tr">These fill the ditch; those pull the bulwarks down:</l>
<l n="tr">Some raise the ladders; others scale the town.</l>
<l n="tr">But, where void spaces on the walls appear,</l>
<l n="tr">Or thin defense, they pour their forces there.</l>
<l n="tr">With poles and missive weapons, from afar,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans keep aloof the rising war.</l>
<l n="tr">Taught, by their ten years' siege, defensive fight,</l>
<l n="tr">They roll down ribs of rocks, an unresisted weight,</l>
<l n="tr">To break the penthouse with the pond'rous blow,</l>
<l n="tr">Which yet the patient Volscians undergo:</l>
<l n="tr">But could not bear  th'  unequal combat long;</l>
<l n="tr">For, where the Trojans find the thickest throng,</l>
<l n="tr">The ruin falls: their shatter'd shields give way,</l>
<l n="tr">And their crush'd heads become an easy prey.</l>
<l n="tr">They shrink for fear, abated of their rage,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor longer dare in a blind fight engage;</l>
<l n="tr">Contented now to gall them from below</l>
<l n="tr">With darts and slings, and with the distant bow.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Elsewhere Mezentius, terrible to view,</l>
<l n="tr">A blazing pine within the trenches threw.</l>
<l n="tr">But brave Messapus, Neptune's warlike son,</l>
<l n="tr">Broke down the palisades, the trenches won,</l>
<l n="tr">And loud for ladders calls, to scale the town.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="525" unit="card"/>Calliope, begin! Ye sacred Nine,</l>
<l n="tr">Inspire your poet in his high design,</l>
<l n="tr">To sing what slaughter manly Turnus made,</l>
<l n="tr">What souls he sent below the Stygian shade,</l>
<l n="tr">What fame the soldiers with their captain share,</l>
<l n="tr">And the vast circuit of the fatal war;</l>
<l n="tr">For you in singing martial facts excel;</l>
<l n="tr">You best remember, and alone can tell.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="530" unit="card"/>There stood a tow'r, amazing to the sight,</l>
<l n="tr">Built up of beams, and of stupendous height:</l>
<l n="tr">Art, and the nature of the place, conspir'd</l>
<l n="tr">To furnish all the strength that war requir'd.</l>
<l n="tr">To level this, the bold Italians join;</l>
<l n="tr">The wary Trojans obviate their design;</l>
<l n="tr">With weighty stones o'erwhelm their troops below,</l>
<l n="tr">Shoot thro' the loopholes, and sharp jav'lins throw.</l>
<l n="tr">Turnus, the chief, toss'd from his thund'ring hand</l>
<l n="tr">Against the wooden walls, a flaming brand:</l>
<l n="tr">It stuck, the fiery plague; the winds were high;</l>
<l n="tr">The planks were season'd, and the timber dry.</l>
<l n="tr">Contagion caught the posts; it spread along,</l>
<l n="tr">Scorch'd, and to distance drove the scatter'd throng.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans fled; the fire pursued amain,</l>
<l n="tr">Still gath'ring fast upon the trembling train;</l>
<l n="tr">Till, crowding to the corners of the wall,</l>
<l n="tr">Down the defense and the defenders fall.</l>
<l n="tr">The mighty flaw makes heav'n itself resound:</l>
<l n="tr">The dead and dying Trojans strew the ground.</l>
<l n="tr">The tow'r, that follow'd on the fallen crew,</l>
<l n="tr">Whelm'd o'er their heads, and buried whom it slew:</l>
<l n="tr">Some stuck upon the darts themselves had sent;</l>
<l n="tr">All the same equal ruin underwent.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Young Lycus and Helenor only scape;</l>
<l n="tr">Sav'd—how, they know noT'mdash;from the steepy leap.</l>
<l n="tr">Helenor, elder of the two: by birth,</l>
<l n="tr">On one side royal, one a son of earth,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom to the Lydian king Licymnia bare,</l>
<l n="tr">And sent her boasted bastard to the war</l>
<l n="tr">(A privilege which none but freemen share).</l>
<l n="tr">Slight were his arms, a sword and silver shield:</l>
<l n="tr">No marks of honor charg'd its empty field.</l>
<l n="tr">Light as he fell, so light the youth arose,</l>
<l n="tr">And rising, found himself amidst his foes;</l>
<l n="tr">Nor flight was left, nor hopes to force his way.</l>
<l n="tr">Embolden'd by despair, he stood at bay;</l>
<l n="tr">And—like a stag, whom all the troop surrounds</l>
<l n="tr">Of eager huntsmen and invading hounds—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Resolv'd on death, he dissipates his fears,</l>
<l n="tr">And bounds aloft against the pointed spears:</l>
<l n="tr">So dares the youth, secure of death; and throws</l>
<l n="tr">His dying body on his thickest foes.</l>
<l n="tr">But Lycus, swifter of his feet by far,</l>
<l n="tr">Runs, doubles, winds and turns, amidst the war;</l>
<l n="tr">Springs to the walls, and leaves his foes behind,</l>
<l n="tr">And snatches at the beam he first can find;</l>
<l n="tr">Looks up, and leaps aloft at all the stretch,</l>
<l n="tr">In hopes the helping hand of some kind friend to reach.</l>
<l n="tr">But Turnus follow'd hard his hunted prey</l>
<l n="tr">(His spear had almost reach'd him in the way,</l>
<l n="tr">Short of his reins, and scarce a span behind)</l>
<l n="tr">“Fool!” said the chief, “tho' fleeter than the wind,</l>
<l n="tr">Couldst thou presume to scape, when I pursue?”</l>
<l n="tr">He said, and downward by the feet he drew</l>
<l n="tr">The trembling dastard; at the tug he falls;</l>
<l n="tr">Vast ruins come along, rent from the smoking walls.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus on some silver swan, or tim'rous hare,</l>
<l n="tr">Jove's bird comes sousing down from upper air;</l>
<l n="tr">Her crooked talons truss the fearful prey:</l>
<l n="tr">Then out of sight she soars, and wings her way.</l>
<l n="tr">So seizes the grim wolf the tender lamb,</l>
<l n="tr">In vain lamented by the bleating dam.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then rushing onward with a barb'rous cry,</l>
<l n="tr">The troops of Turnus to the combat fly.</l>
<l n="tr">The ditch with fagots fill'd, the daring foe</l>
<l n="tr">Toss'd firebrands to the steepy turrets throw.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Ilioneus, as bold Lucetius came</l>
<l n="tr">To force the gate, and feed the kindling flame,</l>
<l n="tr">Roll'd down the fragment of a rock so right,</l>
<l n="tr">It crush'd him double underneath the weight.</l>
<l n="tr">Two more young <persName>Liger</persName> and Asylas slew:</l>
<l n="tr">To bend the bow young <persName>Liger</persName> better knew;</l>
<l n="tr">Asylas best the pointed jav'lin threw.</l>
<l n="tr">Brave Caeneus laid Ortygius on the plain;</l>
<l n="tr">The victor Caeneus was by Turnus slain.</l>
<l n="tr">By the same hand, Clonius and Itys fall,</l>
<l n="tr">Sagar, and Ida, standing on the wall.</l>
<l n="tr">From Capys' arms his fate Privernus found:</l>
<l n="tr">Hurt by Themilla first-but slight the wound—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">His shield thrown by, to mitigate the smart,</l>
<l n="tr">He clapp'd his hand upon the wounded part:</l>
<l n="tr">The second shaft came swift and unespied,</l>
<l n="tr">And pierc'd his hand, and nail'd it to his side,</l>
<l n="tr">Transfix'd his breathing lungs and beating heart:</l>
<l n="tr">The soul came issuing out, and hiss'd against the dart.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The son of Arcens shone amid the rest,</l>
<l n="tr">In glitt'ring armor and a purple vest,</l>
<l n="tr">(Fair was his face, his eyes inspiring love,)</l>
<l n="tr">Bred by his father in the Martian grove,</l>
<l n="tr">Where the fat altars of Palicus flame,</l>
<l n="tr">And send in arms to purchase early fame.</l>
<l n="tr">Him when he spied from far, the Tuscan king</l>
<l n="tr">Laid by the lance, and took him to the sling,</l>
<l n="tr">Thrice whirl'd the thong around his head, and threw:</l>
<l n="tr">The heated lead half melted as it flew;</l>
<l n="tr">It pierc'd his hollow temples and his brain;</l>
<l n="tr">The youth came tumbling down, and spurn'd the plain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="590" unit="card"/>Then young Ascanius, who, before this day,</l>
<l n="tr">Was wont in woods to shoot the savage prey,</l>
<l n="tr">First bent in martial strife the twanging bow,</l>
<l n="tr">And exercis'd against a human foe—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">With this bereft Numanus of his life,</l>
<l n="tr">Who Turnus' younger sister took to wife.</l>
<l n="tr">Proud of his realm, and of his royal bride,</l>
<l n="tr">Vaunting before his troops, and lengthen'd with a stride,</l>
<l n="tr">In these insulting terms the Trojans he defied:</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“Twice-conquer'd cowards, now your shame is shown—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Coop'd up a second time within your town!</l>
<l n="tr">Who dare not issue forth in open field,</l>
<l n="tr">But hold your walls before you for a shield.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus threat you war? thus our alliance force?</l>
<l n="tr">What gods, what madness, hether steer'd your course?</l>
<l n="tr">You shall not find the sons of Atreus here,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor need the frauds of sly Ulysses fear.</l>
<l n="tr">Strong from the cradle, of a sturdy brood,</l>
<l n="tr">We bear our newborn infants to the flood;</l>
<l n="tr">There bath'd amid the stream, our boys we hold,</l>
<l n="tr">With winter harden'd, and inur'd to cold.</l>
<l n="tr">They wake before the day to range the wood,</l>
<l n="tr">Kill ere they eat, nor taste unconquer'd food.</l>
<l n="tr">No sports, but what belong to war, they know:</l>
<l n="tr">To break the stubborn colt, to bend the bow.</l>
<l n="tr">Our youth, of labor patient, earn their bread;</l>
<l n="tr">Hardly they work, with frugal diet fed.</l>
<l n="tr">From plows and harrows sent to seek renown,</l>
<l n="tr">They fight in fields, and storm the shaken town.</l>
<l n="tr">No part of life from toils of war is free,</l>
<l n="tr">No change in age, or diff'rence in degree.</l>
<l n="tr">We plow and till in arms; our oxen feel,</l>
<l n="tr">Instead of goads, the spur and pointed steel;</l>
<l n="tr">Th' inverted lance makes furrows in the plain.</l>
<l n="tr">Ev'n time, that changes all, yet changes us in vain:</l>
<l n="tr">The body, not the mind; nor can control</l>
<l n="tr">Th' immortal vigor, or abate the soul.</l>
<l n="tr">Our helms defend the young, disguise the gray:</l>
<l n="tr">We live by plunder, and delight in prey.</l>
<l n="tr">Your vests embroider'd with rich purple shine;</l>
<l n="tr">In sloth you glory, and in dances join.</l>
<l n="tr">Your vests have sweeping sleeves; with female pride</l>
<l n="tr">Your turbants underneath your chins are tied.</l>
<l n="tr">Go, Phrygians, to your Dindymus again!</l>
<l n="tr">Go, less than women, in the shapes of men!</l>
<l n="tr">Go, mix'd with eunuchs, in the Mother's rites,</l>
<l n="tr">Where with unequal sound the flute invites;</l>
<l n="tr">Sing, dance, and howl, by turns, in Ida's shade:</l>
<l n="tr">Resign the war to men, who know the martial trade!”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="621" unit="card"/>This foul reproach Ascanius could not hear</l>
<l n="tr">With patience, or a vow'd revenge forbear.</l>
<l n="tr">At the full stretch of both his hands he drew,</l>
<l n="tr">And almost join'd the horns of the tough yew.</l>
<l n="tr">But, first, before the throne of Jove he stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus with lifted hands invok'd the god:</l>
<l n="tr">“My first attempt, great <persName>Jupiter</persName>, succeed!</l>
<l n="tr">An annual off'ring in thy grove shall bleed;</l>
<l n="tr">A snow-white steer, before thy altar led,</l>
<l n="tr">Who, like his mother, bears aloft his head,</l>
<l n="tr">Butts with his threat'ning brows, and bellowing stands,</l>
<l n="tr">And dares the fight, and spurns the yellow sands.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Jove bow'd the heav'ns, and lent a gracious ear,</l>
<l n="tr">And thunder'd on the left, amidst the clear.</l>
<l n="tr">Sounded at once the bow; and swiftly flies</l>
<l n="tr">The feather'd death, and hisses thro' the skies.</l>
<l n="tr">The steel thro' both his temples forc'd the way:</l>
<l n="tr">Extended on the ground, Numanus lay.</l>
<l n="tr">“Go now, vain boaster, and true valor scorn!</l>
<l n="tr">The Phrygians, twice subdued, yet make this third return.”</l>
<l n="tr">Ascanius said no more. The Trojans shake</l>
<l n="tr">The heav'ns with shouting, and new vigor take.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="638" unit="card"/>Apollo then bestrode a golden cloud,</l>
<l n="tr">To view the feats of arms, and fighting crowd;</l>
<l n="tr">And thus the beardless victor he bespoke aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“Advance, illustrious youth, increase in fame,</l>
<l n="tr">And wide from east to west extend thy name;</l>
<l n="tr">Offspring of gods thyself; and <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> shall owe</l>
<l n="tr">To thee a race of demigods below.</l>
<l n="tr">This is the way to heav'n: the pow'rs divine</l>
<l n="tr">From this beginning date the Julian line.</l>
<l n="tr">To thee, to them, and their victorious heirs,</l>
<l n="tr">The conquer'd war is due, and the vast world is theirs.</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> is too narrow for thy name.” He said,</l>
<l n="tr">And plunging downward shot his radiant head;</l>
<l n="tr">Dispell'd the breathing air, that broke his flight:</l>
<l n="tr">Shorn of his beams, a man to mortal sight.</l>
<l n="tr">Old Butes' form he took, Anchises' squire,</l>
<l n="tr">Now left, to rule Ascanius, by his sire:</l>
<l n="tr">His wrinkled visage, and his hoary hairs,</l>
<l n="tr">His mien, his habit, and his arms, he wears,</l>
<l n="tr">And thus salutes the boy, too forward for his years:</l>
<l n="tr">“Suffice it thee, thy father's worthy son,</l>
<l n="tr">The warlike prize thou hast already won.</l>
<l n="tr">The god of archers gives thy youth a part</l>
<l n="tr">Of his own praise, nor envies equal art.</l>
<l n="tr">Now tempt the war no more.” He said, and flew</l>
<l n="tr">Obscure in air, and vanish'd from their view.</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans, by his arms, their patron know,</l>
<l n="tr">And hear the twanging of his heav'nly bow.</l>
<l n="tr">Then duteous force they use, and Phoebus' name,</l>
<l n="tr">To keep from fight the youth too fond of fame.</l>
<l n="tr">Undaunted, they themselves no danger shun;</l>
<l n="tr">From wall to wall the shouts and clamors run.</l>
<l n="tr">They bend their bows; they whirl their slings around;</l>
<l n="tr">Heaps of spent arrows fall, and strew the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">And helms, and shields, and rattling arms resound.</l>
<l n="tr">The combat thickens, like the storm that flies</l>
<l n="tr">From westward, when the show'ry Kids arise;</l>
<l n="tr">Or patt'ring hail comes pouring on the main,</l>
<l n="tr">When <persName>Jupiter</persName> descends in harden'd rain,</l>
<l n="tr">Or bellowing clouds burst with a stormy sound,</l>
<l n="tr">And with an armed winter strew the ground.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="672" unit="card"/>Pand'rus and Bitias, thunderbolts of war,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom Hiera to bold Alcanor bare</l>
<l n="tr">On Ida's top, two youths of height and size</l>
<l n="tr">Like firs that on their mother mountain rise,</l>
<l n="tr">Presuming on their force, the gates unbar,</l>
<l n="tr">And of their own accord invite the war.</l>
<l n="tr">With fates averse, against their king's command,</l>
<l n="tr">Arm'd, on the right and on the left they stand,</l>
<l n="tr">And flank the passage: shining steel they wear,</l>
<l n="tr">And waving crests above their heads appear.</l>
<l n="tr">Thus two tall oaks, that <placeName key="tgn,7010018" authname="tgn,7010018">Padus</placeName>' banks adorn,</l>
<l n="tr">Lift up to heav'n their leafy heads unshorn,</l>
<l n="tr">And, overpress'd with nature's heavy load,</l>
<l n="tr">Dance to the whistling winds, and at each other nod.</l>
<l n="tr">In flows a tide of Latians, when they see</l>
<l n="tr">The gate set open, and the passage free;</l>
<l n="tr">Bold Quercens, with rash Tmarus, rushing on,</l>
<l n="tr">Equicolus, that in bright armor shone,</l>
<l n="tr">And Haemon first; but soon repuls'd they fly,</l>
<l n="tr">Or in the well-defended pass they die.</l>
<l n="tr">These with success are fir'd, and those with rage,</l>
<l n="tr">And each on equal terms at length ingage.</l>
<l n="tr">Drawn from their lines, and issuing on the plain,</l>
<l n="tr">The Trojans hand to hand the fight maintain.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="691" unit="card"/>Fierce Turnus in another quarter fought,</l>
<l n="tr">When suddenly  th' unhop'd-for news was brought,</l>
<l n="tr">The foes had left the fastness of their place,</l>
<l n="tr">Prevail'd in fight, and had his men in chase.</l>
<l n="tr">He quits  th'  attack, and, to prevent their fate,</l>
<l n="tr">Runs where the giant brothers guard the gate.</l>
<l n="tr">The first he met, Antiphates the brave,</l>
<l n="tr">But base-begotten on a Theban slave,</l>
<l n="tr">Sarpedon's son, he slew: the deadly dart</l>
<l n="tr">Found passage thro' his breast, and pierc'd his heart.</l>
<l n="tr">Fix'd in the wound  th'  Italian cornel stood,</l>
<l n="tr">Warm'd in his lungs, and in his vital blood.</l>
<l n="tr">Aphidnus next, and Erymanthus dies,</l>
<l n="tr">And Meropes, and the gigantic size</l>
<l n="tr">Of Bitias, threat'ning with his ardent eyes.</l>
<l n="tr">Not by the feeble dart he fell oppress'd</l>
<l n="tr">(A dart were lost within that roomy breast),</l>
<l n="tr">But from a knotted lance, large, heavy, strong,</l>
<l n="tr">Which roar'd like thunder as it whirl'd along:</l>
<l n="tr">Not two bull hides  th'  impetuous force withhold,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor coat of double mail, with scales of gold.</l>
<l n="tr">Down sunk the monster bulk and press'd the ground;</l>
<l n="tr">His arms and clatt'ring shield on the vast body sound,</l>
<l n="tr">Not with less ruin than the Bajan mole,</l>
<l n="tr">Rais'd on the seas, the surges to control—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">At once comes tumbling down the rocky wall;</l>
<l n="tr">Prone to the deep, the stones disjointed fall</l>
<l n="tr">Of the vast pile; the scatter'd ocean flies;</l>
<l n="tr">Black sands, discolor'd froth, and mingled mud arise:</l>
<l n="tr">The frighted billows roll, and seek the shores;</l>
<l n="tr">Then trembles Prochyta, then <placeName key="tgn,7010392" authname="tgn,7010392">Ischia</placeName> roars:</l>
<l n="tr">Typhoeus, thrown beneath, by Jove's command,</l>
<l n="tr">Astonish'd at the flaw that shakes the land,</l>
<l n="tr">Soon shifts his weary side, and, scarce awake,</l>
<l n="tr">With wonder feels the weight press lighter on his back.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="717" unit="card"/>The warrior god the Latian troops inspir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">New strung their sinews, and their courage fir'd,</l>
<l n="tr">But chills the Trojan hearts with cold affright:</l>
<l n="tr">Then black despair precipitates their flight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When Pandarus beheld his brother kill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">The town with fear and wild confusion fill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">He turns the hinges of the heavy gate</l>
<l n="tr">With both his hands, and adds his shoulders to the weight</l>
<l n="tr">Some happier friends within the walls inclos'd;</l>
<l n="tr">The rest shut out, to certain death expos'd:</l>
<l n="tr">Fool as he was, and frantic in his care,</l>
<l n="tr">T' admit young Turnus, and include the war!</l>
<l n="tr">He thrust amid the crowd, securely bold,</l>
<l n="tr">Like a fierce tiger pent amid the fold.</l>
<l n="tr">Too late his blazing buckler they descry,</l>
<l n="tr">And sparkling fires that shot from either eye,</l>
<l n="tr">His mighty members, and his ample breast,</l>
<l n="tr">His rattling armor, and his crimson crest.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Far from that hated face the Trojans fly,</l>
<l n="tr">All but the fool who sought his destiny.</l>
<l n="tr">Mad Pandarus steps forth, with vengeance vow'd</l>
<l n="tr">For Bitias' death, and threatens thus aloud:</l>
<l n="tr">“These are not <placeName key="perseus,Ardea" authname="perseus,Ardea">Ardea</placeName>'s walls, nor this the town</l>
<l n="tr">Amata proffers with Lavinia's crown:</l>
<l n="tr">'T is hostile earth you tread. Of hope bereft,</l>
<l n="tr">No means of safe return by flight are left.”</l>
<l n="tr">To whom, with count'nance calm, and soul sedate,</l>
<l n="tr">Thus Turnus: “Then begin, and try thy fate:</l>
<l n="tr">My message to the ghost of Priam bear;</l>
<l n="tr">Tell him a new Achilles sent thee there.”</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A lance of tough ground ash the Trojan threw,</l>
<l n="tr">Rough in the rind, and knotted as it grew:</l>
<l n="tr">With his full force he whirl'd it first around;</l>
<l n="tr">But the soft yielding air receiv'd the wound:</l>
<l n="tr">Imperial Juno turn'd the course before,</l>
<l n="tr">And fix'd the wand'ring weapon in the door.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>“But hope not thou,” said Turnus, “when I strike,</l>
<l n="tr">To shun thy fate: our force is not alike,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor thy steel temper'd by the Lemnian god.”</l>
<l n="tr">Then rising, on his utmost stretch he stood,</l>
<l n="tr">And aim'd from high: the full descending blow</l>
<l n="tr">Cleaves the broad front and beardless cheeks in two.</l>
<l n="tr">Down sinks the giant with a thund'ring sound:</l>
<l n="tr">His pond'rous limbs oppress the trembling ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Blood, brains, and foam gush from the gaping wound:</l>
<l n="tr">Scalp, face, and shoulders the keen steel divides,</l>
<l n="tr">And the shar'd visage hangs on equal sides.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="756" unit="card"/>The Trojans fly from their approaching fate;</l>
<l n="tr">And, had the victor then secur'd the gate,</l>
<l n="tr">And to his troops without unclos'd the bars,</l>
<l n="tr">One lucky day had ended all his wars.</l>
<l n="tr">But boiling youth, and blind desire of blood,</l>
<l n="tr">Push'd on his fury, to pursue the crowd.</l>
<l n="tr">Hamstring'd behind, unhappy Gyges died;</l>
<l n="tr">Then Phalaris is added to his side.</l>
<l n="tr">The pointed jav'lins from the dead he drew,</l>
<l n="tr">And their friends' arms against their fellows threw.</l>
<l n="tr">Strong Halys stands in vain; weak Phlegys flies;</l>
<l n="tr"><placeName key="tgn,6005278" authname="tgn,6005278">Saturnia</placeName>, still at hand, new force and fire supplies.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Halius, Prytanis, Alcander fall—/L&gt;</l>
<l n="tr">Ingag'd against the foes who scal'd the wall:</l>
<l n="tr">But, whom they fear'd without, they found within.</l>
<l n="tr">At last, tho' late, by Lynceus he was seen.</l>
<l n="tr">He calls new succors, and assaults the prince:</l>
<l n="tr">But weak his force, and vain is their defense.</l>
<l n="tr">Turn'd to the right, his sword the hero drew,</l>
<l n="tr">And at one blow the bold aggressor slew.</l>
<l n="tr">He joints the neck; and, with a stroke so strong,</l>
<l n="tr">The helm flies off, and bears the head along.</l>
<l n="tr">Next him, the huntsman Amycus he kill'd,</l>
<l n="tr">In darts invenom'd and in poison skill'd.</l>
<l n="tr">Then Clytius fell beneath his fatal spear,</l>
<l n="tr">And Creteus, whom the Muses held so dear:</l>
<l n="tr">He fought with courage, and he sung the fight;</l>
<l n="tr">Arms were his bus'ness, verses his delight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="p" n="778" unit="card"/>The Trojan chiefs behold, with rage and grief,</l>
<l n="tr">Their slaughter'd friends, and hasten their relief.</l>
<l n="tr">Bold Mnestheus rallies first the broken train,</l>
<l n="tr">Whom brave Seresthus and his troop sustain.</l>
<l n="tr">To save the living, and revenge the dead,</l>
<l n="tr">Against one warrior's arms all <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> they led.</l>
<l n="tr">“O, void of sense and courage!” Mnestheus cried,</l>
<l n="tr">“Where can you hope your coward heads to hide?</l>
<l n="tr">Ah! where beyond these rampires can you run?</l>
<l n="tr">One man, and in your camp inclos'd, you shun!</l>
<l n="tr">Shall then a single sword such slaughter boast,</l>
<l n="tr">And pass unpunish'd from a num'rous host?</l>
<l n="tr">Forsaking honor, and renouncing fame,</l>
<l n="tr">Your gods, your country, and your king you shame!”</l>
<l n="tr">This just reproach their virtue does excite:</l>
<l n="tr">They stand, they join, they thicken to the fight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now Turnus doubts, and yet disdains to yield,</l>
<l n="tr">But with slow paces measures back the field,</l>
<l n="tr">And inches to the walls, where <placeName key="tgn,1130786" authname="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>'s tide,</l>
<l n="tr">Washing the camp, defends the weaker side.</l>
<l n="tr">The more he loses, they advance the more,</l>
<l n="tr">And tread in ev'ry step he trod before.</l>
<l n="tr">They shout: they bear him back; and, whom by might</l>
<l n="tr">They cannot conquer, they oppress with weight.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As, compass'd with a wood of spears around,</l>
<l n="tr">The lordly lion still maintains his ground;</l>
<l n="tr">Grins horrible, retires, and turns again;</l>
<l n="tr">Threats his distended paws, and shakes his mane;</l>
<l n="tr">He loses while in vain he presses on,</l>
<l n="tr">Nor will his courage let him dare to run:</l>
<l n="tr">So Turnus fares, and, unresolved of flight,</l>
<l n="tr">Moves tardy back, and just recedes from fight.</l>
<l n="tr">Yet twice, inrag'd, the combat he renews,</l>
<l n="tr">Twice breaks, and twice his broken foes pursues.</l>
<l n="tr">But now they swarm, and, with fresh troops supplied,</l>
<l n="tr">Come rolling on, and rush from ev'ry side:</l>
<l n="tr">Nor Juno, who sustain'd his arms before,</l>
<l n="tr">Dares with new strength suffice  th'  exhausted store;</l>
<l n="tr">For Jove, with sour commands, sent Iris down,</l>
<l n="tr">To force  th'  invader from the frighted town.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>With labor spent, no longer can he wield</l>
<l n="tr">The heavy fanchion, or sustain the shield,</l>
<l n="tr">O'erwhelm'd with darts, which from afar they fling:</l>
<l n="tr">The weapons round his hollow temples ring;</l>
<l n="tr">His golden helm gives way, with stony blows</l>
<l n="tr">Batter'd, and flat, and beaten to his brows.</l>
<l n="tr">His crest is rash'd away; his ample shield</l>
<l n="tr">Is falsified, and round with jav'lins fill'd.</l>
<l n="tr"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The foe, now faint, the Trojans overwhelm;</l>
<l n="tr">And Mnestheus lays hard load upon his helm.</l>
<l n="tr">Sick sweat succeeds; he drops at ev'ry pore;</l>
<l n="tr">With driving dust his cheeks are pasted o'er;</l>
<l n="tr">Shorter and shorter ev'ry gasp he takes;</l>
<l n="tr">And vain efforts and hurtless blows he makes.</l>
<l n="tr">Plung'd in the flood, and made the waters fly.</l>
<l n="tr">The yellow god the welcome burthen bore,</l>
<l n="tr">And wip'd the sweat, and wash'd away the gore;</l>
<l n="tr">Then gently wafts him to the farther coast,</l>
<l n="tr">And sends him safe to cheer his anxious host.</l></div1></body></text></TEI.2>